<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable treatise wherein is proved that King William (commonly call'd the Conqueror) did not get the imperial crown of England by the sword, but by the election and consent of the people to whom he swore to observe the original contract between king and people.</title>
            <author>Cooke, Edward, of the Middle Temple.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12325612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12325612</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 207:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable treatise wherein is proved that King William (commonly call'd the Conqueror) did not get the imperial crown of England by the sword, but by the election and consent of the people to whom he swore to observe the original contract between king and people.</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Edward, of the Middle Temple.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], clxiv p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"This is a duplicate of the 'Argumentum Anti-Normannicum' in all but title page, frontpiece and 'explanation of the frontpiece'"--BM.</note>
                  <note>Written by Edward Cooke. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.); BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  I, --  King of England, 1027 or 8-1087.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William I, 1066-1087.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Seaſonable Treatiſe; Wherein is proved, That KING <hi>WILLIAM</hi> (commonly call'd The CONQUEROR)</p>
            <p>Did not get the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by the Sword, but by the Election and Conſent of the People.</p>
            <p>To whom he ſwore to obſerve the Original Contract between King and People.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Norman</hi> ſwore to Laws, by which we're free; Laws here more His, than Our Security.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation">
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:2"/>
            <head>An Explanation of the Frontispiece, warranted by the Authorities cited in the following Argument.</head>
            <p>NO ſooner had the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>King</hi> Harold <hi>victorious over the K. of</hi> Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark <hi>&amp;</hi> Toſta, Harold'<hi>s Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at</hi> York.</note> 
               <hi>Valiant HAROLD</hi> conquered the Daniſh King, and his <hi>own Brother,</hi> the daring <hi>TOSTA,</hi> but news was brought him, <note n="†" place="margin">William <hi>D. of</hi> Normandy, <hi>at the ſame time, lands in</hi> Suſſex<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> That the NORMAN Duke was arrived at <hi>Pemſey</hi> in <hi>Suſſex;</hi> whereupon, with haſte he went to meet him, and at <note n="*" place="margin">Harold <hi>meets him at</hi> Haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>where they fight.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Haſtings</hi> gave the NORMAN battel, which proved fatal to him.</p>
            <p>For he was, as you may ſee, <note n="*" place="margin">Haroid <hi>ſlain.</hi>
               </note> ſlain, between the NORMAN <hi>Long-Bows,</hi> and ENGLISH <hi>Spears,</hi> leaving the <hi>Duke</hi> VICTOR in the Field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> proud with this Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The D. comes up to</hi> London.</note> marches with all ſpeed up to <hi>Berk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamſtead,</hi> near <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reſt</hi> of the ENGLISH (if they had look'd upon his coming, as a Deſign to <hi>conquer</hi> the <hi>Nation,</hi> and not to aſſert his <hi>pretended legal Title</hi> againſt <hi>HAROLD,</hi>) were then able
<pb facs="tcp:59543:3"/> to have driven him back to his <hi>own Country,</hi> or at leaſt found him a <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulary</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> (for there was not a <hi>fifth part</hi> of the <hi>Strength</hi> of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that felt the <hi>Force</hi> of his <hi>Arms</hi>)<note place="margin">Enters into Compact with the Engliſh, to make him King.</note> but Duke <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and the ENGLISH ſoon came to an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the latter entred into <hi>ſolemn Compact</hi> to make him <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereupon <hi>BRITANNIA</hi>
               <note place="margin">Britan. <hi>gives him the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </note> holds forth to him the Scepter with <hi>one</hi> Hand, And</p>
            <p>With the <hi>other</hi> ſhews him the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And</hi> St. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward'<hi>s Laws to keep.</hi>
               </note> and moſt <hi>famous Laws</hi> of St. <hi>EDWARD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, at the ſame Time, a <hi>Noble</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Biſhop ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oath.</note> 
               <hi>Prelat</hi> tenders him the <hi>Coronation-Oath:</hi> The ENGLISH <hi>firſt</hi> being asked, by the Biſhop, If they would <hi>aſſent</hi> to have the <hi>Duke</hi> their KING? and if he ſhould then be <hi>crowned?</hi> To which they all, with an <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent,</hi> anſwered, <hi>Yea, Yea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Oath</hi> VVilliam <hi>took at his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> Whereupon he takes the <hi>Coronation-Oath;</hi> the ſence of which take as follows.</p>
            <p>This Scepter, (<hi>Faireſt Queen</hi>) I moſt<note place="margin">
                  <p>Sacramentum Willielmi Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioris. Ante Altare S. Petri Apoſtoli co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Clero &amp; Populo jure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurando; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit ſe velle Sanctas Dei Eccleſias ac Rectores earum defendere, nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non &amp; cunctum Populum, ſibi ſubjectum juſte, ac Regali providentia regere, rectam Legem Statuere &amp; tenere, rapinas injuſta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> judicia pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitùs interdicere. <hi>Hoveden</hi> pars Prior. <hi>fol.</hi> 258. l. 14.</p>
                  <p>Exacto prius coram omni Populo jurejurando, quod ſe modeſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga ſubjectos ageret, &amp; aequo Jure <hi>Anglos,</hi> quo <hi>Francos,</hi> tractaret. <hi>Malmsb.</hi> lib. 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 154. b. l. 8.</p>
                  <p>Rex pro bono pacis, juravit ſuper omnes Reliquias Eccleſiae Sancti Albani, Tactiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sacro ſanctis Evangeliis, bonas &amp; approbatas Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas Regni Leges, quas Sancti ac pii Angliae Reges ejus Anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; Maxime Rex Edwardus Statuit, inviolabiliter obſervare. <hi>Mat. Paris.</hi> Vitae Viginti trium Sancti Albani Abbatuum. <hi>fol.</hi> 48. l. 37.</p>
               </note> thankfully receive, and with it do <hi>ſolemnly Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Swear,</hi> to <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:3"/> both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I vow to <hi>Rule</hi> my <hi>Subjects</hi> with that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>prudent Care,</hi> as becomes a <hi>good King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will (<hi>with the Advice and Conſent of my Great Council</hi>) enact <hi>right Law:</hi> Which done, <note n="*" place="margin">The Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> be <hi>Witneſs all ye Saints,</hi> that to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> of my <hi>Power,</hi> I will my ſelf <hi>religiouſly keep</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> it.</p>
            <p>For what can be more <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>common Reaſon</hi> of all <hi>Mankind,</hi> than for a <hi>Prince</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and <hi>ſolemnly</hi> to <hi>ordain</hi> a <hi>Law,</hi> and the next moment after to <hi>break</hi> and <hi>abrogate</hi> it in his <hi>Cloſet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Rapines I will forbid, and all falſe Judgments; no <hi>illegal</hi> or ARBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRARY
<pb facs="tcp:59543:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:5"/> ACTS, under pretence of the <hi>Prerogative-Royal,</hi> will I ſuffer or permit to the <hi>oppreſsion</hi> of my ENGLISH <hi>Subjects,</hi> between <hi>whom,</hi> and my <hi>Normans,</hi> I will adminiſter EQUAL RIGHT.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>God, Angels,</hi> my NOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANS, and <hi>You,</hi> (O <hi>Sacred <hi>Queen</hi>
               </hi>) may all be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> to the <hi>ſincerity</hi> of my Heart, That I will not take the <hi>Engliſh-men's Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances</hi> by <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> or thruſt them out of their <hi>Paternal Poſſeſsions</hi> by <hi>wrong;</hi> That I have not, nor will pretend to any <hi>Abſolute,</hi> or <hi>Deſpotical</hi> Power over their <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates;</hi> nor <hi>violate,</hi> break, or <hi>alter,</hi> the <hi>Fundamental Rights</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> (as <hi>Tyrants</hi> do, who <hi>only</hi> deſign to <hi>enſlave</hi> their <hi>People</hi>). I do here ſolemnly <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>ſwear,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>all Ye mighty Powers, inviolably</hi> to <hi>obſerve</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>Sacred Laws</hi> of <hi>St. Edward</hi> my <hi>Kinſman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſaid, the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> of <hi>York</hi> ſets the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> upon <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM</hi>'s Head; and thus of a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>NORMANDY,</hi> he was <hi>created</hi> KING of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:5"/>
            <head>TO MY Worthy FRIEND, The Learned Author of <hi>Argumentum Anti-Normannicum.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GReat Britain!</hi> faireſt Queen of all the Iſles,</l>
               <l>Inrich'd at Home with bounteous Natures ſmiles!</l>
               <l>Thou ſuch a ſelf-ſufficiency doſt own,</l>
               <l>All Countries need thy Stores, but thou want'ſt none;</l>
               <l>Divided from the World, Thou to thy ſelf art one.</l>
               <l>The Sea, and Continent, proclaim Thee Great,</l>
               <l>Proud Monarchs have lain Captives at thy Feet:</l>
               <l>The Scales of th' Weſtern World are in thy Hand;</l>
               <l>Each Kingdom's Fate depends on thy Command.</l>
               <l>Where e're thy Friendſhip, and thy Force combine,</l>
               <l>Againſt that State in vain the Reſt deſign.</l>
               <l>To Thee no Ills from Forreign Foes can come,</l>
               <l>The baſeſt and more dangerous are at Home.</l>
               <l>No Deſert Beaſts of Prey thy Land does bear,</l>
               <l>But yet worſe Beaſts within thy Bowels are,</l>
               <l>Who would thy Rights and Ancient Glories tear.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:6"/>
               <l>Thoſe having loſt their Liberty of Mind,</l>
               <l>From vanquiſh'd Sires a weak excuſe would find.</l>
               <l>Are theſe thy Sons? Or Marks of thy diſgrace?</l>
               <l>Who own themſelves a ſlaviſh conquer'd Race?</l>
               <l>The Norman Duke on Terms receiv'd the Crown,</l>
               <l>Swore, He'd by <hi>Edward</hi>'s Laws ſupport his Throne,</l>
               <l>Which ſure <hi>no abſolute Victor</hi> would have done.</l>
               <l>That Title which his Great Succeſſor hath,</l>
               <l>Came from the Pact, not from the Breach of Faith.</l>
               <l>That gives the Bounds to all incroaching Might,</l>
               <l>And ſets the Banks about the Subjects Right:</l>
               <l>Who pulls them down, lets in a raging Sea,</l>
               <l>Which drowns, and ſwallows up all Property.</l>
               <l>Who e're attempt to let that Torrent in,</l>
               <l>At their own Houſes may the Waſte begin;</l>
               <l>Let them for others Till their proper Land;</l>
               <l>Or under ſome baſe Favourites Command,</l>
               <l>May they, whilſt others riot with their Stores,</l>
               <l>Without Relief beg at their Native Doors.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder their Countries Curſe, their Tyrant's Scorn,</l>
               <l>May they with never-ceaſing Pangs be torn,</l>
               <l>Who violate the Sacred Truſt to which they're born.</l>
               <l>But bleſt be Thou, and all, who dare, like Thee,</l>
               <l>Bravely aſſert their Countries Liberty.</l>
               <l>Our well-built Freedom thou doſt make to'appear,</l>
               <l>And its Foundation from Time's Rubbiſh clear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Norman ſwore to Laws by which we're free,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laws were more his, than our Security.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:6"/>
               <l>Him <hi>King</hi> the People's <hi>joint Conſent</hi> alone</l>
               <l>Did make, which by that <hi>Sacred Oath</hi> he won:</l>
               <l>Or that <hi>ſame joint Conſent</hi> had made him none.</l>
               <l>We were no Norman Slaves; nor French could be,</l>
               <l>Had we enough True Engliſhmen like Thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now, my Muſe, before you end, take care</l>
               <l>Humbly to cloſe up all with Heav'n in Prayer;</l>
               <l>Prayer for that King, who doth <hi>Great Britain</hi> Rule,</l>
               <l>Who of this Iſle is th' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Soul:</l>
               <l>In whom ſo many glorious Vertues ſhine,</l>
               <l>As make him ſeem to be of Race Divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May Heav'n continually His Guardian prove,</l>
               <l>And keep Him ſafe in all His Subjects Love!</l>
               <l>Long may unruffled Peace adorn His Crown;</l>
               <l>May all the Laws in their ſmooth Channel run;</l>
               <l>And flowing Juſtice ſtill ſupport His Throne.</l>
               <l>Thus bleſt, and thus united here at Home,</l>
               <l>What cannot <hi>Britain</hi>'s Monarch overcome?</l>
               <l>Oh may Great <hi>Edward</hi>'s, and Fifth <hi>Henry's</hi> Soul,</l>
               <l>By Heav'nly Pow'r be transfus'd to him whole!</l>
               <l>May He ride Mighty Admiral of the Seas,</l>
               <l>Scourging His ſtubborn Enemies into Peace;</l>
               <l>His Envying Neighbours all their Powers diſown,</l>
               <l>Strike to His Flag, and tremble at His Frown;</l>
               <l>And th' humbled World be glad to pay him fear,</l>
               <l>And awful veneration every where.</l>
               <l>That this may be,—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:59543:7"/>
               <l>May the Illuſtrious Senate of the Land,</l>
               <l>With their Wiſe Councils, ever by him ſtand;</l>
               <l>He pleas'd in them, and they reſolv'd to ſhow,</l>
               <l>What th' utmoſt ſtretch of Loyalty can do.</l>
               <l>Then will his Glories ſhine in brighteſt ſtate,</l>
               <l>At th' Head of ſuch a joint Triumvirate:</l>
               <l>Then King and People doubly will be bleſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Europe</hi> then enjoy a laſting Reſt.</l>
               <l>For this let all our Vows to Heav'en be ſent,</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>Great Charles</hi> happy in's <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:59543:7"/>
            <head>Argumentum Anti-Normannicum.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou were pleaſed, ſome time ſince, (in my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of a ſhort, but free converſation with you) to tell me, You had a mind to read how far I could give you ſatisfaction in a <hi>few Points</hi> you had raiſed to your ſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Norman Conqueſt;</hi> and that within a little while I ſhould have a <hi>Paper</hi> from you wherein they ſhould be contained: You were not long, Sir, in juſtly acquitting your ſelf of your promiſe to me; I did receive the <hi>Furniture</hi> of theſe enſuing <hi>Arguments,</hi> by the <hi>four Queſtions</hi> you ſent me, and hope there is nothing to be found in them, but unbyaſſed and venerable
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:59543:8"/> Truth, which ſurely none will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended to hear. I have endeavoured to pay all poſſible Reſpect to You, and to Juſtice; and, as far as my Abilities could reach, in ſo ſmall a Treatiſe, have impartially offered my Thoughts upon them, and now beg your candour in judging me.</p>
            <p>Your Queſtions, Sir, are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <label>The Firſt Queſtion.</label>
               <item>I. Whether <hi>William,</hi> Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> (who was afterwards <hi>William</hi> the Firſt) got the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the Sword, and made an <hi>abſolute Conqueſt</hi> of the Nation at his first Entrance?</item>
               <label>The Second Queſtion.</label>
               <item>II. Whether this firſt <hi>William</hi> did <hi>aboliſh all the <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> and changed the whole Frame and Conſtitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:59543:8"/>The Third Queſtion.</label>
               <item>III. Whether it be true, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had neither Eſtates nor Fortunes left, but all was divided between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans?</hi>
               </item>
               <label>The Fourth Queſtion.</label>
               <item>IV. Whether it be not a grand Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to affirm, That there were no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council</hi> of the whole Kingdom?</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall take them, Sir, in the order you have ſent them to me; and ſo firſt begin with your firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:59543:9"/>
               <head>The Firſt Queſtion.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Whether</hi> William, <hi>Duke of</hi> Normandy, (<hi>who was afterwards</hi> William <hi>the Firſt) got the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of</hi> England <hi>by the Sword, and made an</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">For <hi>England</hi> thus much I dare ſpeak, and under the rule of Modeſty proteſt, That ſithence the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> who firſt commanded and impoſed Tribute upon this Land, (for Conquerors may command) Tribute and Subſidie have been as juſtly, both by the Law of God, and the Law of Nations, paid in <hi>England,</hi> as in <hi>Jewry;</hi> yea, and juſtly continued, as a remembrance of a <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulbec</hi> Pandects of the Law of Nations, <hi>c. 10. p.</hi> 69. One <hi>Blackwood</hi> wrote a Book, which concluded, That <hi>we</hi> are all <hi>Slaves</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Conqueſt. Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Petyt.</hi> Miſc. Parl. <hi>p.</hi> 66. And this Poſition is maintained by an <hi>Anonimus Author,</hi> in his <hi>full</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Petyt</hi>'s Ancient Right of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> aſſerted. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35. in the Margin.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſolute Conqueſt <hi>of the Nation at his firſt entrance?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS you have ſtated the Queſtion, Sir, and deſire to know what is my Opinion of it; with ſubmiſſion to others, better informed, and who are more able to maintain the Truth of thoſe Principles I proceed upon, than my ſelf, I ſhall return you this modeſt Anſwer, as my Sence and Judgment in the Point, <hi>viz.</hi> That I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:59543:9"/> in the Affirmative, for theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral conſtraining Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>William</hi> laid a far greater ſtreſs upon his Claim and Titles to this Kingdom, than ever he did upon his great and mighty <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> will be very plain and evident, if you pleaſe but to conſider with me theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Particulars.</p>
               <p>1. In that before his Conqueſt, when the <hi>People</hi> had choſen <hi>Harold,</hi> the Son of Earl <hi>Godwin</hi> for their King, after the Death of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, and had put aſide <hi>Edgar Atheling,</hi> by right of Blood and Inheritance entit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Crown: This Norman Duke made his loud Complaints of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done him, in not <hi>elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> him, for he was <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Edward <hi>the Confeſſor was Son to</hi> Egelred <hi>K. of</hi> England <hi>by</hi> Emma, <hi>Siſter to</hi> Rich. 2. <hi>Duke of</hi> Normandy, <hi>who was Grandfather to Duke</hi> William; <hi>ſo that K</hi> Edward <hi>and Duke</hi> William <hi>were Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Germans once removed, as this farther ſhews you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Richard 1.
<list>
                              <item>Richard 2.</item>
                              <item>Robert.</item>
                              <item>William.</item>
                              <item>Emma.</item>
                              <item>Edward.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note> Coſen German to the Confeſſor, who died <note n="†" place="margin">Edward <hi>married</hi> Edith, <hi>the Daughter of E.</hi> Godwin; <hi>but whether upon a vow of Chaſtity, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impotency of Nature, or upon any hatred to her Father, or ſuſpicion againſt her ſelf (for all theſe Cauſes are alledged by ſeveral Writers of thoſe Times) he forbore all private Familiarities with her.</hi>
                  </note> without Iſſue; and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore pretended that the Right truly devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon him. But, it ſeems, as ill luck would have it, this Duke they knew to
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:59543:10"/> be a Baſtard, and neither the Saxon Law, nor the Norman Cuſtom, could help him in ſuch a Caſe, and ſo that Title did him but little good. Well, what therefore was to be his next Work? Why,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Truly his Pretence was then,<note place="margin">Mat. Paris. 1. <hi>Antiq Brit. Eccleſ. 96.</hi>
                  </note> That the Confeſſor had deſigned him for his Succeſſor, and by his laſt Will had bequeathed this Kingdom to him; And this was confirmed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Nobility, and principally of <hi>Harold</hi> himſelf: and hereupon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how <hi>Harold</hi> had trickt him, and ſet the Crown on his own Head, he ſends over ſeveral Ambaſſadors, with Commiſſion to require him to remember the Oath he had formerly made to the ſaid <hi>William</hi> in the time of his Extremity, when he was his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <hi>Normandy;</hi> Which was, That he, the ſaid <hi>Harold,</hi> ſhould aſſiſt him in the obtaining of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> if ever <hi>Edward</hi> died without Iſſue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And receiving but unkind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns from <hi>Harold,</hi> by way of Anſwer to his Demands, which thus the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian relates, <hi>De Regno addebat prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuoſum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wil. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmesb. <hi>lib. 3. fol. 56. l. 25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>fuiſſe, quòd abſque Generali Senatus &amp; Populi conventu &amp; Edicto,
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:59543:10"/> alienam illi haereditatem juraverit;</hi> 
                  <q>That as for him to take an Oath to deliver up the Inheritance of any Realm, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the general conſentand allowance <note n="*" place="margin">That is, without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Wittenagemot, Mycel Synod, or Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iament.</note> of the Senate and People, could not but be a great piece of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, yea, altho' he might have juſt title ſo to do; <note n="†" place="margin">Praeterea iniquum poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, ut imperio decedat, quod tanto favore civium regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſuſceperit. <hi>Malmsb.</hi> l. 3. f. 56. l. 30.</note> wherefore it was an unreaſonable Requeſt of the Duke now to require him to renounce the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in which he was ſo well ſetled to the good liking and content of his People.</q> This Norman Duke, not to be his own Judg, refers himſelf to the Pope (then <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond) to decide the Matter, and ſo reſolved that the infallible Chair ſhould deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine who had the Juſteſt Title to the Crown and Kingdom, <hi>Harold</hi> or Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And the good old Gentleman (who would not be behind-hand with him in civility for ſo great a kindneſs, as was the Appealing to him, and ſo flattering him with a Judicatory Power over Princes) eaſily was induced to pronounce ſentence on <hi>William</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
               <pb n="vili" facs="tcp:59543:11"/>
               <p>But all theſe bluſtering Pretences of nearneſs in Blood, (which it ſeems his Son <hi>Henry</hi> thought to be the beſt flower in his Garland, when he <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In his Charter, whereby he advanced the Abby of</hi> Ely <hi>into the degree of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick.</hi>
                  </note> calls himſelf the Son of <hi>William the Great,</hi> (pray, Sir, be pleaſed to obſerve, it is not of <hi>William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seldeni</hi> ad Eadmerum &amp; Notae &amp; Spicileg. <hi>fol. 211. lin. 39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui</hi> Edwardo <hi>Regi Haereditario Jure ſucceſſit in Regnum,</hi> Who ſucceeded to King <hi>Edward</hi> in the Kingdom, by Right of Inheritance) or the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's bequeſt of the Crown to him. Or laſtly, the Pope's definitive Sentence in <hi>William</hi>'s favour. All theſe bluſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pretences of his, I ſay, availed but little with <hi>Harold;</hi> and therefore you muſt think, it could not but incenſe the Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> very greatly, ſo that he had now a juſt cauſe of open quarrel againſt <hi>Harold,</hi> for the Reaſons you have heard: And thereupon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening his Parliament, or Aſſembly of three Eſtates, which conſiſted</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nobility is taken in</hi> France <hi>for Gentlemen, as well as for Earls, or perſons of like dignity.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>of the Clergie, Nobility, and Commons; the Nobility, in fine, promiſed to ſerve him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſtegan'<hi>s reſtitution of decayed Intelligence in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities, dedicated to King</hi> James. <hi>pag. 173.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and the Clergie and People to aid him with Mony, according
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:59543:11"/> to their ſeveral Abilities, and ſuch offers as they made, were forthwith ſet down in writing by a Secretary there preſent.</hi> So that being thus ſupplied, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with ſeveral other of his Friends, he makes for <hi>England;</hi> and was no ſooner arrived at a place in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Peveneſſey,</hi> (now <hi>Pemſey</hi>) and got well on Land, but, by his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he declared upon what Occaſions he thus entred the Realm; and ſo preparing to give <hi>Harold</hi> Battle, he hereby ſeemed as if he would have all the World to know, his Quarrel was more Perſonal than National. But this I will ſpeak more particularly and largely to, when I come to mention ſome of the Charters he made after he was eſtabliſhed King.</p>
               <p>And as Perjury ſeldom or never e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes unpuniſhed; ſo here was a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inſtance of the Divine Juſtice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Harold</hi> for his breach of Oath and Covenant to the Duke; for in the Battle of <hi>Haſtings</hi> he met with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, loſing both his Crown and his Life at once, and leaving <hi>William</hi> to finiſh the day with Victory, over thoſe that were yet reſolved to diſpute the Cauſe with him.</p>
               <pb n="x" facs="tcp:59543:12"/>
               <p>And now being rid of his ſtubborn Enemy, and in the heat of the Chaſe got to <hi>London,</hi> he poſſeſſed himſelf of that Kingdom which he pretended was his own by Right before from the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles we have already mentioned. Yet however it was in no ſuch haughty and inſulting way, as many boaſt of, and would gladly have their unwary Readers to believe, upon their bare Credit and Teſtimony; but he choſe the more grateful and complying Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of a Courtier, and ſetled himſelf in it by a kind of mutual Agreement, and expreſs compact, as now I hope will be clearly demonſtrated by what I ſhall offer to you after this his (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended abſolute) Conqueſt. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Tho' he was victorious over his great Adverſary <hi>Harold,</hi> yet if he had been an abſolute Conqueror, (as hath been of late ſo vigorouſly aſſerted by our Modern Writers) what urgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity was there for him, or how did it ſtand him in ſuch mighty ſtead, ſtill to keep himſelf armed with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Titles, that ſo he might have the more colourable pretence of Right and Juſtice on his ſide, in laying a legal Claim to this Imperial Crown? For,
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:59543:12"/> me-thinks, if he had a full poſſeſſion upon ſuch a forcible entry, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, this had been a ſtronger Title than any thing elſe he could have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: for how could, or durſt, a vanquiſhed, enſlaved Nation, diſpute with him, when he rode triumphing on their Backs, and had laſhed them into an entire ſubmiſſion of vaſſalage? But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us ſee the manner of this firſt King <hi>William</hi>'s Coronation; and whether or no he did not take an Oath at the ſame time, which was, in ſence and ſubſtance (if not juſt in the words themſelves) the very ſame with that which the Ancient Saxon Kings uſed likewiſe to take upon their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronations. And for your full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction herein, I ſhall give you the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of them both together, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin firſt with</p>
               <p>The Oath of either King <hi>Edward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In vita</hi> Ael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredi <hi>Magni, fol.</hi> 62. Promiſſio Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis vel <hi>Edvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> vel <hi>Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redi,</hi> (utrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que euim <hi>Dunſtanus Kingstoniae</hi> Coronavit) circa Ann. 970.</note> or King <hi>Ethelred,</hi> (for <hi>Dunſtan</hi> crowned both of them at <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi>) about the Year 970.</p>
               <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:59543:13"/>
               <p>This writing, punctually to a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Hoc Scripto, de litera ad li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teram, deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt ad ſcriptum illud, quod <hi>Dunſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus tradebat Domino no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro <hi>Kingsto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae,</hi> ipſo illo die quo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratus erat in Regem; at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illi interdice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat ne ullam ſponſionem daret praeter ſponſionem illam, quam depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerat in Altari Chriſti, quemadmodum Epiſcopus illi dictaret.</note> correſponds with that Writing which <hi>Dunſtan</hi> the Arch-biſhop deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to our Lord the King at <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> that very day of his Coronation; and did then forbid the King, that thenceforth he ſhould make any other Oath, than that which he had made at the Holy Altar, or what the Biſhop ſhould dictate then unto him.</p>
               <p>In the Name of the Holy Trinity, I<note place="margin">In Nomine S. Trinitatis, Ego tria pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto Populo Chriſtiano, meiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſubditis.</note> do promiſe three things to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian People, and my Subjects.
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Oath of the Saxon Kings at their Coronation.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">The Oath which <hi>William</hi> the Firſt took at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <q>1. That I will peaceably govern the Church of God, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</q>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. <hi>That he would</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1. Dei Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ac Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum mei Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii Populum Chriſtianum vera pace frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum.</note> 
                           <hi>defend the Churches of God, and all their Paſtors.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:59543:13"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">K. <hi>William</hi>'s Oath.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Saxon Kings Oath.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>That he would govern all People that were his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects with Juſtice, and with that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a good King.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. <q>That I will<note place="margin">2. Me Rapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, omnem<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> iniquitatem, omnibus ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturum.</note> utterly interdict Rapines, and all Injuſtice to all Orders of Men.</q>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>That he would both enact, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf keep, right Law, and to the utmoſt of his Power, would interdict all Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, and falſe Judgments.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. <q>That I do<note place="margin">3. Me promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurum &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daturum in omnibus Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis, Juſtitiam &amp; Miſericordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am; ut nobis omnibus, pro infinita ſua miſeratione, propitius fit, Clemens ac Miſericors Deus, qui vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit &amp; regnat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </note> promiſe, and will command, That in all Judgments, Juſtice and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhall be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together, to the end, that God, who is the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Judg of the World, and ruleth over all, may be pleaſed, out of his infinite Compaſſion, to be propitiouſly good and merciful to us all.</q>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. And he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one Article more to the Oath, than was in that of the Saxon Kings; and it was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be done, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> and that was, <hi>Quod aequo jure Anglos &amp; Francos Tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:59543:14"/>That he would govern both the Engliſh and French by the ſame equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>This Oath too<note place="margin">Chriſtianus Rex, qui haec obſervaverit, ſibi promere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur honorem mundanum; quinetiam illi Deus aeternus miſerebitur tam in hac vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta preſenti, quam in Aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na illa, quae nunquam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit.</note> he took at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> before ever he was Conſecrated, and the <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Laity</hi> were equally Parties and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: After which he was Anointed and Crowned by <hi>Aldred</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York;</hi> for <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gand</hi> the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was not admitted to that Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <q>That Chriſtian King who ſhall obſerve theſe things, ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly acquire all earthly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; moreover the everlaſting Lord God ſhall take Compaſſion on him, as well in this Life, as that which is Eternal and Endleſs.</q>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="xv" facs="tcp:59543:14"/>
                  <p>But if he ſhall do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> irritum fecerit quod Deo etat promiſſum, tum deinceps egregiè verget in pejus, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quidem in popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſuo; &amp; omne demum quicquid fit, convertetur in peſſimum.</note> to what he promiſed God, thenceforth he ſhall daily decline, and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhall fail in their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and every thing will be turned from bad to ſtark nought, unleſs in time he reforms the Errors of his Ways.</p>
                  <p>Meditate often with<note place="margin">Hoc tecum ſaepe meditare, quod debeas in Dei Judicio gregem proferré &amp; ſiſtere, in quem Paſtor in hac vita conſtitutus es; &amp; proſpice quomodo conſervaſti quod Chriſtus Sanguine ſuo olim redemit.</note> thy ſelf, that thou ſhalt one day bring thy whole Flock before the Tribunal of God, whoſe Shepherd thou art here ordained, and therefore often conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with thy ſelf, and look forward how thou haſt kept thoſe whom Chriſt with his own dear Blood, hath formerly redeemed.</p>
                  <p>It is the Office of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed<note place="margin">Regis Conſecrati jus eſt male judicare nemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s; Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duas, Orphanos &amp; Perigri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos tueri &amp; conſervare; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inia prohibere; ſcorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores corrigere; inceſtuoſos disj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngere ac funditus extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eneficas &amp; incanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores delere; Parricidas &amp; perjuros terris exterminare; pauperes eleemoſynis ſuble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare.</note> King to judg no Man unrighteouſly; to protect Widdows, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans and Strangers; to interdict Robberies; to puniſh Whoredoms; to ſeparate and utterly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:59543:15"/> all inceſtuous Perſons; to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh and cut off Witches and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters; to baniſh Parricides and perjured Perſons out of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to comfort the Poor with Almes.</p>
                  <p>To call Grave, Sober,<note place="margin">Senes, Prudentes, &amp; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brios ſibi in conſillarios a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribere.</note> and wiſe Men to counſel and adviſe him.</p>
                  <p>To chuſe juſt and good<note place="margin">Juſtos ſibi in Miniſtros conſtituere; quia quicquid ipſi iniuſtum fecerint ejus (Autoritate) univerſi il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius rationem tenetur ille reddere in die Judicii.</note> Men for his Miniſters and Officers, becauſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever illegal Actions they ſhall commit (under his Authority) he muſt, at the Day of Judgment, give an account for.</p>
               </q>
               <p>And the reaſon of all this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, both from the Laws of God and Man; the King is <hi>Debitor Juſtitiae</hi> to all his People, to rule and govern them<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exact Collect.</hi> p. 28, 29.</note> by Law: <hi>Which,</hi> as his late Majeſty ſaid, <hi>is the Inheritance of every Subject, and the only ſecurity he can have for his Life and Eſtate. Ad hoc autem creatus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tract. <hi>lib. 3. fol.</hi> 107. a. b.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt &amp; electus,</hi> writes <hi>Bracton, ut Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam faciat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis:</hi> and that <hi>dum facit juſtitiam Vicarius eſt Regis aeterni,
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:59543:15"/> Miniſter autem Diaboli, dum declinet ad injuriam. Henry</hi> the Third, upon a Charter granted by his Father King <hi>John,</hi> and confirmed by himſelf, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Qui vero id quod dictus Pater</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rot. Clauſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>H.</hi> 3. pars pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. m. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>noſter eis per Chartam ſuam conceſſit, &amp; nos poſtmodum annuimus infringere nſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaquam volumus, ſicut nec de jure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemus;</hi> much leſs a Coronation Oath. <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt tells the Pope, upon a Meſſage ſent him, That he could not anſwer without conſulting his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and gives this for his Reaſon, <hi>Jurejurando in Coronatione noſtra pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtito</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rot. Clauſ. 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. m. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Schedula.</note> 
                  <hi>ſumus adſtricti, quod Jura Regni noſtri ſervabimus illibata, nec aliquid, quod Diadema tangat, Regni ejuſdem abſque ipſorum requiſito conſilio facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve, laſtly, that <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, that famous Conqueror of two Kings, the Scottiſh and French, hath left recorded to Poſterity a definitive Sentence and Judgment in this Point, as an indiſputable rule of Right and Juſtice;</p>
               <p>That he ought, and was bound by<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pulton</hi> Stat. 25. <hi>E. 3. f. 150.</hi>
                  </note> his Coronation Oath, to keep the Law of the Realm.</p>
               <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:59543:16"/>
               <p>This Law of the Realm, or Land,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cited in</hi> White'<hi>s Sacred Laws,</hi> p. 69.</note> was looked upon, in the judgment of theſe Parliaments, as <note n="*" place="margin">27. E. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Law of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Time,</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">25. E. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>of old Time uſed,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">42. E. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>the Old Law;</hi> whoſe Age made it the more venerable, and gave an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of honour to it.</p>
               <p>Well, having thus ſhewn you the Coronation of King <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, and given you the Solemn Oath he at the ſame time took, even before his Conſecration, that ſo he might give all poſſible ſatisfaction to the Engliſh, of his reſolving to rule accordingly; and alſo having made it plain, that it was the ſame in ſubſtance with that the Ancient Saxons took before him; I ſhall now deſcend briefly to ſet before you ſome of his own Charters, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome of <hi>William</hi> the Second's, and of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt's, his Children, and ſucceeding Kings; and from them evidence to you, I hope demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that it was not ſo much his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> he relied upon, when he was ſetled in this Imperial Throne, as his claim to the Crown of <hi>England, Jure Hereditario,</hi> by Right of Inheritance. And for the proof of this, be pleaſed
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:59543:16"/> to accept of theſe enſuing Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Nomine Patris, &amp; Filii, &amp;<note place="margin">Carta Antiqua litera D. N. 4.</note> Spiritus Sancti, Amen. Ego Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Dei Gratia Rex Anglorum, <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditario Jure</hi> Factus.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In Nomine Patris, &amp; Filii, &amp;<note place="margin">Carta 4. E. 4. m. 27. per In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpex.</note> Spiritus Sancti, Amen. Ego Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Rex Anglorum <hi>Haereditario Jure</hi> Factus.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In nomine Sanctae &amp; individuae<note place="margin">Monaſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican. <hi>Vol. 1. fol. 317.</hi>
                  </note> Trinitatis, Ego Willielmus Dei Gratia Rex Anglorum, notum facio omnibus, tam poſteris quam praeſentibus Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitibus, Baronibus, &amp; omnibus <hi>fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus Francis &amp; Anglis,</hi> Quod cum in Angliam veniſſem, &amp; in finibus Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting cum excercitu applicuiſſem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra hoſtes meos, qui mihi Regnum Angliae injuſtè conabatur auferre.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In ore gladii (<hi>ſaith</hi> William <hi>the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carra Weſtm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> per Inſpex. 1. E. 4. parte ſeptima m. 26. <hi>Mr.</hi> Seld. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view,</hi> p. 483.</note> 
                  <hi>First's Charter</hi>) Regnum adeptus ſum, Anglorum devicto Haroldo Rege cum ſuis Complicibus, qui mihi Regnum cum providentia Dei deſtinatum &amp; beneficio <hi>conceſſionis</hi> Domini, &amp; <hi>Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati</hi> mei glorioſi Regis <hi>Edwardi</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum conati ſunt auferre, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="xx" facs="tcp:59543:17"/>
                  <head>Come we now to his Second Son, <hi>William Rufus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="5">5. Willielmus Rex Anglorum, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmo<note place="margin">Carta Regis Willielmi Rufi vide Monaſt. Anglican. <hi>Vol. 1. fol. 352.</hi>
                     </note> Vicecomiti Filio Baldewini, &amp; omnibus Baronibus ſuis &amp; Miniſtris, qui habitant in Devoneſcira, Salutem. Notifico vobis, quod mea condonati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Eccleſia beati Olavi Regis, &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyris à Monachis belli aedificata, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore beati Nicholai, quam cum omni terra quae pertinet ad Eccleſiam ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripti Martyris meo privilegio, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet Literis &amp; Sigillo, liberam facio, &amp; ita liberam &amp; quietam per om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia cum ſaca &amp; ſoca, &amp; thol &amp; theam, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangenetheof, &amp; warpeni, &amp; murdro, &amp; omnibus conſuetudinibus, &amp; operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; auxiliis, ſicut Pater meus libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram fecit Eccleſiam Sancti Martini de bello, <hi>ubi hoſtem devicit,</hi> &amp; ubi <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> Regni <hi>haereditariam ſibi bellando adquiſivit.</hi> T. Walchelino Wintoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enſi Epiſcopo &amp; Rogero Bigot apud Wintoniam.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:59543:17"/>
                  <head>From <hi>William Rufus</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed we to his Brother, <hi>Henry the Firſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>And, ſaith he,</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In Nomine Sanctae &amp; Individuae<note place="margin">Ex Hiſt. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis Eccleſ. M. S. in Bibl. Bodleana (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Codices Cant. <hi>l. 58.) lib. 3. fol</hi> 2. a. Monaſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican. <hi>Vol. 1. fol. 95.</hi>
                     </note> Trinitatis, Patris, &amp; Filii, &amp; Spiritus Sancti, Anno Incarnationis Dominicae MCVIII Indictione ....... Anno vero Pontificatus Domini Paſchalis Papae ſecundi <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, Regni quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mei ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, Ego Henricus providente<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina clementia Rex Anglorum &amp; Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannorum Dux, Willielmi Magni Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Filius, qui Edwardo Regi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tario Jure</hi> ſucceſſit in Regnum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Again,</hi> Ego Henricus Dei Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<note place="margin">Monaſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican. <hi>Vol. 2. fol, 845.</hi>
                     </note> Rex Anglorum, Filius Magni Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Willielmi, qui beatae memoriae Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardo in Regnum <hi>Succeſſit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. To give you one Charter more.<note place="margin">Ex MS. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Rogeri Owen Equit. Aurati.</note> The words of that of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, to the Abby of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> are, Pro memoria <hi>Edwardi</hi> Cognati mei, qui <hi>Patrem</hi> meum <hi>liberoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> illius in Regnum ſuum adoptivos <hi>haeredes</hi> inſtituit.</p>
                  <pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:59543:18"/>
                  <p>And thus have I given you, as it were, a three-fold Cord (not eaſily to be ſnapt aſunder) to bind hard my Aſſertion, and to convince thoſe, who will not ſuffer themſelves to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run by an obſtinate Prejudice, or cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated by a byaſs'd Intereſt, that our firſt <hi>William,</hi> when he came in, gained <hi>nor</hi> ſuch an <hi>abſolute Victory</hi> as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, over this Nation, (for when he came in, he had not ſubdued the fifth part of it) but came to the Crown by the Election and Conſent of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and People. And, <hi>foedus pepigit,</hi> he made a Solemn Covenant with the Engliſh, to obſerve and keep thoſe Laws, which were <hi>bonae &amp; approbatae, &amp; antiquae Leges Regni.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this, Sir, is what I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour clearly to make out to you in my Anſwer to your Second Queſtion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:59543:18"/>
               <head>The Second Queſtion.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether this firſt <hi>William</hi> did <hi>aboliſh</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> all the <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> and changed the whole <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Government?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd doubtleſs not; for as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Grounds of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lord</hi> Coke'<hi>s Preface to his 8th Report.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>our Common<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Laws at this day, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Memory or Regiſter of any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and the ſame which the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex vitâ Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Sancti Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bani.</note> 
                  <hi>Conqueror then found within this Realm of England:</hi> And thoſe Laws he ſwore to obſerve, which were good, approved, and ancient.</p>
               <p>Now, that theſe were only his <hi>Norwegian</hi> Laws, ſure none can, or ought to believe, after they have throughly examined theſe plain Truths, which I ſhall here offer to their fair peruſal.</p>
               <p>1. If they pleaſe to conſider what was the Title of the Laws, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Laws of King <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi>
                  <pb n="xxiv" facs="tcp:59543:19"/> with his learned Notes upon <hi>Eadmer,</hi> (and ſince with the Saxon Laws).</p>
               <p>Why, truly, the Title was plainly this; <hi>Theſe are the Laws and Cuſtoms which</hi> William<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elden <hi>ad Endmerum, fol. 173.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the King granted to the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ce ſont les Leis &amp; les Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes que li Reis William grantut a tut le <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euple de Engleterre, apres le Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt de la Terre. Ice les meiſmes que le Reis Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſun Coſin tiht devant luy.</note> 
                  <hi>whole People of</hi> England <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Conqueſt of the Land. Theſe were thoſe which the King</hi> Edward <hi>his Couſin held before him.</hi> In theſe Laws recited by <hi>Hoveden,</hi> in the Life of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Laws are confirmed in theſe words; <hi>This we command, That all Men have and hold the Law of</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the King in all things; together with thoſe Laws which we have added for the profit of the Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that here was no aboliſhing of the Old Saxon Laws that he found, when he came to govern this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor any ſetting up of new ones in their ſtead: No, ſo far was he from any ſuch Deſigns of introducing new Laws, (which muſt needs be then the abſolute Reſults of Arbitrary Will and Pleaſure, to ſhew the ſad and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:59543:19"/> Effects of an entire Conqueſt) to the overthrow of thoſe ſo firmly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed already; that, you ſee, he gives his Confirmation to King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Laws, which indeed, generally ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were but a Collection of thoſe the Hiſtorian calls, <hi>Bonas Leges ab an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malmesb. de Geſt. Regn. Angl. <hi>lib. 2. fo. 42. l. 21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>regibus latas, non quod ille ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, ſed quod obſervaverit;</hi> not ſo much the Laws of his own making, as thoſe he cauſed to be ſtrictly obſerved and put in execution.</p>
               <p>From the Title of his Laws, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed we</p>
               <p>2. To the Confirmation it ſelf, and here I ſhall acquaint you with the manner of it, in all its neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Particulars.</p>
               <p>This <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, with his French and Normans, putting many hardſhips upon the Engliſh, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned great Diſorders and Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the State; ſeveral of the Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons chief Nobility, betook themſelves to Arms for the ſake of their <hi>Avitae Conſuetudines,</hi> to which they bore an immutable and an immortal Love, and which they feared ſome were endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:59543:20"/> to take away and change them, though on the other hand they were obſtinately reſolved never to part from them, for they had <hi>à Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seld. <hi>Tit. of Hon. fol. 523.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>didiciſſe aut Libertatem aut Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem;</hi> and they would rather undergo the worſt Calamities of a more cruel War, than they would tamely quit and abandon thoſe dear Laws and Cuſtoms, to which they had ſo long been uſed, and were ſo well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with.</p>
               <p>The King hereupon, to keep the<note place="margin">Ex lib. Monaſt. de Litchfield. Co. 8. <hi>Rep. in Pref.</hi>
                  </note> People in a greater obſervance of their Duty, and withal, not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Oath he had taken at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, cauſed <hi>twelve of the moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and wiſe Men, in every Shire throughout all</hi> England, to take an Oath before himſelf, to deal ſincerely and uprightly, without turning either, <hi>ad dextram, aut ſiniſtram,</hi> that is, as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> interprets it, <q>neither to flatter Prerogative, or extend Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg;</q> and to declare and lay open the Conſtitutions of their Laws and Cuſtoms, without concealing, adding, or in any ſort varying from the Truth. But finding <hi>William</hi> and his Norman Barons, who were <hi>Norwegians</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:59543:20"/> were for introducing the<note place="margin">Apud Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard. <hi>fol. 149.</hi>
                  </note> Norwegian Laws: This the Engliſh thought a more killing blow than that of his Victory; and therefore <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi Compatriotae qui Leges edixerant, triſtes affecti,</hi> being all of them in a great Conſternation, they beſeeched him that they might ſtill retain <hi>Leges proprias,</hi> their own Laws; and enjoy <hi>Conſuetudines Antiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> their Ancient Cuſtoms, in which their Fathers lived, <hi>&amp; ipſi in eis nati &amp; nutriti ſunt, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>durum valde foret ſibi ſuſcipere Leges ignotas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; judicare de eis quas neſcie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,</hi> and themſelves were born and bred up in, becauſe it would be very hard to receive Laws unknown, and to judg of thoſe things they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not. And when <hi>William</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they warmly reinforced their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and then conjured him, <hi>per Animam Regis Edwardi,</hi> by the Soul of King <hi>Edward, qui ſibi poſt diem ſuum conceſſerat Coronam &amp; Regnum, &amp; cujus erant Leges,</hi> that he would not impoſe a Yoke upon them which they were not able to bear, and which would only gall their Necks, and make them the more fretting and unruly.</p>
               <pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:59543:21"/>
               <p>King <hi>William</hi> finding there was no Remedy, tho' he was long reſolute, at laſt, in a <hi>Common Council</hi> of his Kingdom, yields; and by his <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (the ground-work of all thoſe that after followed) he confirmed to<note place="margin">Apud Cl. Lambard. <hi>fol. 158.</hi>
                  </note> them their Ancient Laws, <hi>ad praeces Communitatis Anglorum.</hi> Bleſſing it with the Seal of Security, and Wiſh of Eternity; cloſing it up with this<note place="margin">Co. li. 8. <hi>in Pref.</hi>
                  </note> general: And we further Command, That all Men keep, and obſerve duly the Laws of King <hi>Edward;</hi> rearing up the Frontiſpiece of his Gracious<note place="margin">Ex Libro MS. de legib. antiq.</note> Work with his Glorious Stile, <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmus Dei Gratia Rex Anglorum, Dux Normannorum, Omnibus hominibus ſuis Francis &amp; Anglicis, Salutem. Statui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius imprimis ſuper omnia unum Deum per totum Regnum noſtrum venerari, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam fidem Chriſti ſemper inviolatam cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodiri, pacem, &amp; ſecuritatem, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam, judicium &amp; juſtitiam inter Anglos &amp; Normannos, Francos &amp; Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones Walliae &amp; Cornubiae, Pictos &amp; Scotos Albaniae, ſimiliter inter—&amp; Inſulanos, Provincias &amp; Patrias quae pertinent ad Coronam &amp; dignitatem, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſionem &amp; obſervationem &amp; honorem Regni noſtri, &amp; inter omnes nobis Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectos
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:59543:21"/> per <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſam Monarchiam Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Britanniae firmiter &amp; inviolabiliter obſervari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ingulphus,</hi> Secretary to <hi>William</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and afterwards made Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>Crowland</hi> by him, is an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable Witneſs, to prove that the Engliſh Laws were then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new confirmed; and he ſaith, <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex</hi> Ingulpho <hi>Abbate</hi> Crowlandenſe, <hi>fol.</hi> 519. b. <hi>l.</hi> 37. Att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li eadem vice mecum de Londonijs in meum Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterium Leges aequiſſimi Regis Edwardi, quas Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus meus inclitus Rex Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus authenticas eſſe &amp; perpetuas, per totum Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Angliae inviolabiliter tenendas ſub poenis graviffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is toclamâret, &amp; ſuis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiarils commendâret, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem idiomate, quo editae ſunt.</note> 
                  <q>I brought this time with me, from <hi>London,</hi>
                  </q> (where he had been about the buſineſs of his Houſe) <q>to my Monaſtery, the Laws of the moſt juſt King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> which my Lord <hi>William,</hi> the renowned King of <hi>England,</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed authentick and perpetual all <hi>England</hi> over to be kept, under moſt grievous Penalties, and commended to his Juſtice in the ſame Tongue they were ſet forth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And this Proclamation was not all (to allay the Storms, which perhaps the violation of theſe Laws had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed); <q>For the good of Peace,</q> ſaith an ancient Monk, <q>he ſwears, upon all the Reliques of the Church of
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:59543:22"/> Saint <hi>Albane,</hi> touching the Holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Abbot <hi>Fredrick</hi> miniſtring the Oath, <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. Paris <hi>in vit.</hi> Frethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici <hi>Abbatis S. Albani. fol. 48. l.</hi> 39.Bonas &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatas anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas Regni Leges, quas Sancti &amp; Pii Angliae Reges ejus Anteceſſores &amp; maximè Rex Edwardus ſtatuit, inviolabiliter obſervare.</note> the good and approved an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Laws of the Realm, which the Holy and Pious Kings of <hi>England,</hi> his Anceſtors, and eſpecially King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſet forth, inviolably to keep.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee the Mighty Conqueror is himſelf conquered, and ſolemnly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing all Arbitrary Will and Power, ſubmits his Will to be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and governed by Juſtice, and the ancient Rights of the Engliſh Men.</p>
               <p>Beſides that, the Laws that were continued and confirmed, were the old Saxon Laws, and the Additional Laws were made for the Benefit and Advantage of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> And thoſe Laws of Saint <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> which the Engliſh were ſo fond of, this <hi>William</hi> ſolemnly ſwore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, Angels, and Men, for ever inviolably to keep and obſerve.</p>
               <p>But before I leave this your Second Queſtion, Sir, I think it will be no ways improper to give you the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:59543:22"/> of the word <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and in what ſence Hiſtorians, and learned Antiquaries have underſtood it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> hath it thus, <hi>Rex</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. Paris. <hi>fol. 941.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Angliae ex <hi>Conqueſtu,</hi> dicitur tamen, quod beatus Edwardus, eo quòd haerede caruit, Regnum legavit Willielmo Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardo Duci Normannorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> in his Gloſſary,<note place="margin">Spelm. <hi>Gloſs. tit.</hi> Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus. <hi>fol. 145.</hi>
                  </note> ſays, <hi>Willielmus Primus <hi>Conqueſtor</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, quia Angliam conquiſivit, id eſt, acquiſivit,</hi> purchaſed, <hi>non quod ſubegit,</hi> not that he ſubdued it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sir <hi>John Skene,</hi> Clark of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter<note place="margin">Skene. <hi>p. 39.</hi>
                  </note> Council, and Rolls, to King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in his Book, <hi>De Verborum ſignificatione,</hi> tells us, That <hi>Conqueſtus</hi> ſignifies Lands <hi>quhilk ony</hi> Perſon <hi>acquiris,</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſis, privato jure, vel ſingulari titulo, veluti donatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, vel ſingulari aliquo contractu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. And it ſeems to me not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Title of <hi>Conqueror,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than of <hi>Victor,</hi> was aſſumed by him, as being a word more mild, and originally ſignifying, as it does in
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:59543:23"/> 
                  <hi>Scotland,</hi> a <hi>Purchaſer;</hi> which is, he that cometh to a real Eſtate, not by hereditary Deſcent, but by Bargain or Gift, <hi>&amp;c. Conqueſtus dicitur ratione</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Skene</hi> de Verborum ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie. verbo Conqueſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>primi Conqueſtoris, &amp; cum tranſmittitur ad ejus haeredem, exuit naturam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtus, &amp; induit naturam Haereditatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And that the word <hi>Conqueſtus</hi> did ſignify what the Hiſtorians ſay it did, we have Records to juſtify their Expoſition, whereof I ſhall produce one, and that is above 480 Years ago. It ſays, <hi>Robertus Filius Nigelli petit verſus Richardum Battail Capitale Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuagium,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ricardus venit &amp; dicit quod pater,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>fuit perſona Eccleſiae de Conqueſtu ſuo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; dedit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Placita de terris. Mich. 2. Johan. penes Camerar. Scaccar. remanen.</hi> Now ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly none can make the word <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> here, to ſignify that the Father of Battel got the Advowſon by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> in our modern ſenſe, but that he had it by his own purchaſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sir <hi>Roger Twiſden,</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before King <hi>William</hi>'s Laws, and he well enough underſtood the full meaning of the word <hi>Conqueſtus,</hi>
                  <pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:23"/> ſays, <hi>Non exiſtimo <hi>Willielmum primum</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardum. <hi>in Prefac. 155.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>de omnium Anglorum terris ad <hi>volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> ſuam &amp; pro <hi>libitu</hi> in modum <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutae</hi> dominationis diſpoſuiſſe.</hi> I do not in the leaſt imagine, that <hi>William the Firſt</hi> had the diſpoſition of the Lands of all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> according to his own <hi>Arbitrary Will</hi> and Pleaſure, and after the manner of an <hi>Abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Sir, by theſe ſeveral Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the word, I think it is very obvious to any impartial Conſiderer, that, (however we conſtrue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it now, being either urged by Flattery or Intereſt ſo to do) it never did, even in that Age it ſelf, import or ſignifie ſuch an <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>entire Conqueſt,</hi> as to carry along with it the <hi>enſlaving</hi> of the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after <hi>William</hi>'s Victory over <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold.</hi> Nay, tho' every Body will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, that this <hi>Harold</hi> came to the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">à totius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae Primati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Culmen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus. Abrev. Chron. Rad. de dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to. <hi>fo. 479.</hi>
                  </note> by a general Election of the Chief of the Nation, yet there is an Ancient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor calls him <hi>Conqueror;</hi> And what then ſhall we think of the ſignification of the word, but that it was an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb n="xxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:24"/> at moſt, and that too by the Voice and Suffrage of the People; ſaith he, <hi>Heraldus ſtrenuus Dux <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtor</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">MS. ex Bib. Domini Wild defuncti.</note> 
                  <hi>Angliae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Sir, this is not all; I muſt beg your patience and leave, for the better illuſtration of the word <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> and to diſabuſe the World in this Point, to preſent you with this following</p>
               <p>Summary SERIES</p>
               <p>Of the Stiles of our ſeveral deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Kings, from this <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, incluſively, to the Great King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third; and therein make an Obſervation, which perhaps as yet hath ſcarcely been taken notice of.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:59543:24"/>
                  <head>The Stiles of the Kings.</head>
                  <item>1. WIllielmus Rex Anglorum, &amp;c.<note place="margin">W. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſometimes</hi> Willielmus Cognomento Baſtardus Rex Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. Willielmus Rufus Rex Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,<note place="margin">W. 2.</note> &amp;c. <hi>and ſometimes</hi> Willielmus Dei Gratia Rex Anglorum, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. Henricus Rex Anglorum, &amp;c. <hi>and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">H. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>ſometimes</hi> Henricus Willielmi Magni Regis Filius.</item>
                  <item>4. Stephanus Rex Anglorum, &amp;c. <hi>and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Steph.</note> 
                     <hi>ſometimes</hi> Stephanus Dei Gratia Rex Anglorum, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>5. Henricus <hi>omitted</hi> Dei Gratia, <hi>and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">H. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>uſed this Stile,</hi> Henricus Rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, &amp;c. <hi>and ſometimes</hi> Henricus Filius Imperatricis Matildae Rex Angliae, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>6. Richardus Rex Angliae, &amp;c.<note place="margin">R. 1.</note>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:59543:25"/>
                  <item>7. Johannes Rex Angliae, &amp;c. <hi>and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John.</note> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> Dominus Hiberniae.</item>
                  <item>8. Henricus Filius Johannis Rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae,<note place="margin">H. 3.</note> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>9. Edwardus Rex Angliae, &amp;c.<note place="margin">E. 1.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>10. Edwardus Filius Edwardi primi,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>E.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Rex Angliae, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And now we are come to the great <hi>Epocha</hi> of Time, when the Stile of our Kings altered. <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, in the beginning of his Reign, in ſeveral Records, writ himſelf, <hi>Edwardus Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Edwardi Filii Edwardi,</hi> that is, <hi>Edward,</hi> the Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt. But this diſtinction not being well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, and having conſidered, that before the Conqueſt there had been two King <hi>Edwards,</hi> he in all Fines, and in general Records, writ himſelf, <hi>Edwardus Rex Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>tertius poſt Conqueſtum,</hi> which was done in the ſecond Year of his Reign, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Dom.</hi> 1328. which Rule was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Richard 2. Hen. 4. Hen.</hi> 5.
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:59543:25"/> 
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. and ſo to ſucceeding Kings downwards.</p>
               <p>And, Sir, to give you a further proof, that King <hi>William</hi> did not Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel and <hi>Aboliſh</hi> all the <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> nor change, as is ſo much affirmed, the whole Frame and Conſtitution of the Government, be pleaſed to hear the Judgment of Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> and the Opinion of Sir <hi>Winſton Churchill;</hi> and I hope they are ſuch unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Authorities, as may ſufficiently bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, if not totally depreſs the fierceſt of Gain-ſayers.</p>
               <p>I ſhall begin with the great and ever famous <hi>Selden,</hi> (for whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as truly deſerving, I have the higheſt regards) and ſhall tranſcribe his words at large, which may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve for a good Solution to this your Second Queſtion, but indeed may poſſibly fully ſatisfy you as to your other three.</p>
               <p>His words are;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Laws of before, as well as of<note place="margin">Selden'<hi>s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of his Hiſtory of Tithes.</hi> p. 482, 483, 484.</note> after the <hi>Norman Conqueſt,</hi> (as it is vulgarly called) are here gathered, and are perhaps equally obſervable, as the Reſt, in the conſequent of a
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:59543:26"/> 
                     <hi>general conſecration of Tithes</hi> to the Church in <hi>England.</hi> For neither were the <hi>Laws</hi> formerly made, <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd</hi> by that <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> altho' by Law of <note n="i" place="margin">Vid. Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian. lib. 5. Inſtitution. cap. 10. Athe. Gentil. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re belli. lib. 3. cap. 5. &amp; Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman illuſt. Quaeſt. 5.</note> War, regularly all Rights and Laws of the Place conquered, be wholly ſubject to the <hi>Conqueror's</hi> Will. For in this of the <hi>Norman,</hi> not only the <hi>Conqueeor's</hi> Will was not declared, that the former Laws ſhould be abrogated, (and until ſuch Declaration, Laws remain in force, by the Opinion of <note n="k" place="margin">Calvin's Can. <hi>fol.</hi> 17. b</note> ſome, in all Conqueſts of Chriſtians againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) but alſo the ancient and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Laws of the Kingdom were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by him. For in his fourth Year, by the Advice of his Baronage, he ſummoned to <hi>London, omnes No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, ſapientes, &amp; Lege ſua eruditos, ut eorum Leges &amp; Conſuetudines audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> as the words are of the Book of <hi>Litchfield,</hi> and afterward confirmed them, as is further alſo related by <note n="l" place="margin">in H. 2. p. 347.</note> 
                     <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Hoveden.</hi> Thoſe, <hi>Lege ſuâ eruditi,</hi> were common Lawyers of that Time, as <hi>Godrie</hi> and <hi>Alfwin</hi> were then alſo, who are ſpoken of in the Book of <note n="m" place="margin">MS lib. 2. p. 33. &amp; 30. in Biol. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Abingdom,</hi> to be, <hi>Legibus Patriae optime inſtituti, quibus tanta
<pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:59543:26"/> ſecularium facundia &amp; praeteritorum memoria eventorum inerat, ut caeteri circumqua<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> facilè eorum ſententiam ratam fuiſſe, quem edicerent, approbarent.</hi> And theſe two, and divers other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers then lived in the Abby of <hi>Abingdon, Quorum collationi nemo ſapiens</hi> (ſays the Author) <hi>refragabatur, quibus rem Eccleſia publicam tuentibus ejus oblocutores elingues fiebant.</hi> You muſt know, that in thoſe days, every Monk here in <hi>England,</hi> that would, might remain ſo ſecular, that he might get Mony for himſelf, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or receive by deſcent to his own uſe. And therefore it was fit enough for practiſing Lawyers to live in Monaſteries. But what had thoſe <hi>praeteritorum memoria eventorum</hi> (that is, Reports, and adjudged Caſes of the Saxon Times) availed in their skill, if the former Laws had not continued? More obvious Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to this purpoſe, are had out of <note n="u" place="margin">Videſis <hi>Cok.</hi> Praefar. ad Relat. 3. &amp; 8. &amp; ſi placet Not. ad for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſc. <hi>p.</hi> 7, &amp; 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Gervaſe</hi> of <hi>Tilbury, Ingulphus,</hi> and others, and we here omit them. But alſo, indeed, it was not to be reputed a <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> or an Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by right of War, (which might have deſtroyed the former Laws) ſo
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:59543:27"/> much as a violent recovering of the Kingdom out of the hands of Rebels, which withſtood the Duke's pretence of a lawful Title, claimed by the <hi>Confeſſor's</hi> adoption, or deſignation of him for his Succeſſor; his near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Blood on the Mother's ſide, not a little alſo aiding ſuch a pretence to a Crown. For the <hi>Confeſſor's</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Emme,</hi> was Siſter to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> to whom, <hi>William</hi> was Grand-child and Heir. But theſe were only ſpecious Titles, and perhaps examined curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, neither of them were at that time enough. And howſoever his Conſcience ſo moved him at his death, that he profeſt he had got <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtoria Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donenſis.</note> 
                     <hi>England</hi> only by Blood and the Sword; yet alſo by expreſs Declaration in ſome of his Patents, he before pretended his Right from the <hi>Confeſſor's</hi> Gift. <note n="p" place="margin">Chart. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl. ſ. Weſtm in inſpex. part 7. 1. Ed. 4. m. 26. &amp; vid. <hi>Camb.</hi> pag. 104.</note> 
                     <hi>In ore gladii,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Regnum adeptus ſum Anglorum, devicto Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldo Rege, cum ſuis complicibus, qui mihi Regnum cum providentia Dei deſtinatum, &amp; beneficio conceſſionis Domini, &amp; cognati mei glorioſi Regis Edwardi conceſſum conati ſunt aufer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> &amp;c. And the Stories commonly
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:59543:27"/> tells us, That the Confeſſor <hi>Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Angliae ei dedit.</hi> And although <hi>Harold</hi> alſo pretended a Deviſe of the Kingdom to himſelf made by the <hi>Confeſſor <hi>in extremis,</hi>
                     </hi> and urged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the Cuſtom of <hi>England</hi> had been from the time of <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s coming hither, <note n="q" place="margin">MS. ſive Autor Guil. Pictav. ſive quis alius, ſit in Bibl. Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> 
                     <hi>Donationem quam in ultimo fine quis fecerit, eam ratam haberi;</hi> and that the former Gift to the <hi>Norman,</hi> and his own Oath for eſtabliſhment of it, were not of force, becauſe they were made, <note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>Malmesb.</hi> lib. 5. de Geſt. Regum <hi>p.</hi> 56. a. ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in Will. 1. &amp; videſis <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> in Hen. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1257. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Londin.</note> 
                     <hi>abſque generali Senatus &amp; Populi conventu &amp; edicto;</hi> yet for his own part, he was driven to put all upon the Fortune of the Field, and ſo loſt it. And the <hi>Norman</hi> with his Sword, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the ſufficiency and prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Gift made to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, got the Crown, as if he had been a lawful Succeſſor to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> and not an <hi>Vniverſal Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi> All this is plain out of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and juſtified infallibly by that of the Titles of many common Perſons made to their Poſſeſſions in <hi>England,</hi> after his Kingdom ſetled, upon the poſſeſſion of themſelves or their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, in time of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings,
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:59543:28"/> eſpecially of the <hi>Confeſſor.</hi> But this was always in caſe, where they by whoſe poſſeſſion the Title was made, had not incurr'd Forfeiture by Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. Many ſuch Titles are clearly allowed in the Book of <hi>Dooms-day,</hi> written in the <hi>Conqueror's</hi> Time: One eſpecially is noted by the moſt learned <hi>Camden</hi> in his <hi>Norfolk.</hi> That, as I remember, is touched in <hi>Dooms-day</hi> alſo, but enough others are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed there which agree with it. How could ſuch Titles have held, if he had made an <hi>abſolute Conqueſt</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> wherein an <hi>Vniverſal Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of all had been to the <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> and no Title could have been derived, but only from or under him? More might be brought to clear this, but we add here only the judicious Aſſertion of a great <note n="s" place="margin">
                        <hi>Shard.</hi> in caſ. in itin. temp. Ed. 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 143. b.</note> Lawyer of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third's Time; <hi>Le Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ne vient pas pur ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter eux que avoient droiturell poſſeſſion, mes de ouſter eux que de leur tort avo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent occupie aſcun terre en diſheritance del Roy, &amp; ſon Corone.</hi> It was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon an Objection made in a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> againſt the Abbot of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> touching a Charter of
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:59543:28"/> King <hi>Edgar,</hi> which the King's Councel would have had void, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, by the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> all Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they ſaid, were devolved to the Crown. But, by the way, for that of his nearneſs of Blood, which could not but aid his other pretended Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; let it not ſeem meerly vain, in regard of his being a Baſtard. There was good pretence for the help of that defect alſo. For, although the Laws of this Kingdom, and, I think of all other Civil States at this day, exclude Baſtards (without a ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Legitimation) from Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; yet by the old Laws uſed by his Anceſtors and Country-men, that is, by thoſe of <hi>Norway,</hi> a Prince's Son gotten <note n="t" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Roger</hi> de <hi>Hoveden</hi> in Rich. 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 425, &amp; 347.</note> on a Concubine bond or free, was equally inheritable as any other born in Wedlock; which was, I believe no ſmall Reaſon, why he ſtood at firſt ſo much for the Laws of <hi>Norway</hi> to have been generally received in this Kingdom. And ſome Stories alſo which make mention of Duke <hi>Robert</hi> his getting <hi>William</hi> on that <hi>Arlet</hi> or <hi>Arlec</hi> (as ſhe is ſometimes written) ſay, That ſhe was to him a good while <hi>vice <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris.</hi> So <hi>Henry</hi>
                     <pb n="xliv" facs="tcp:59543:29"/> of <note n="u" place="margin">In Bibl. Cotton.</note> 
                     <hi>Knyghton</hi> Abbot of <hi>Leiceſter: Tranſiens</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Robertus aſiquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do per Phaleriam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem Normaniae, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit puellam</hi> Arlec <hi>nomine Pelleparii Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, inter caeteras in Chorea tripudian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nocte ſequente illam ſibi conjunxit, quam vice <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris aliquamdiù tenens Willielmum ex ea generavit.</hi> And he tells us alſo the common Tale of tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Smock. If ſhe were ſo his Concubine, or <hi>Vice-conjux,</hi> (between whom and a Wife, even the old <note n="x" place="margin">Fide Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. 3. L. Item Legato 49. §. 4</note> Imperials make no other difference but Honour and Dignity; and by them alſo ſome kind of Inheritance is allowed to <note n="y" place="margin">Authent. 89. <hi>c.</hi> 12. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis igitur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> ſuch Baſtards as are <hi>Naturales liberi,</hi> that is gotten on Concubines); it was much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that her Son ſhould be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Legitimate, than that the Son of every ſingle Woman, bond or free, whether Concubine or no, ſhould be ſo, as the Laws of <hi>Norway</hi> allow. And when he had inherited his Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he made, doubtleſs, no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but that his Blood was as good in regard of all other Inheritances, that might by any colour be derived through it. And therefore <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> well ſtiles him <hi>proximè
<pb n="xlv" facs="tcp:59543:29"/> conſanguineus</hi> alſo to the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> as he was indeed on the Mother's ſide. And thoſe <note n="z" place="margin">Videſis <hi>Malmsb.</hi> de Geſt. Reg. lib. 2. <hi>fol 52.</hi>
                     </note> of the Poſterity of <hi>Edward</hi> Son to <hi>Iron-ſide,</hi> were then ſo excluded or neglected, that their nearneſs on the Father's ſide could not prevent him. You may ſee the common Stories of them. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that excellent <note n="a" place="margin">18. E. 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 30. a.</note> Lawyer <hi>Littleton</hi> ſays, That <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror <hi>was called a Baſtard, becauſe he was born before Marriage had between his Father and Mother, and that after he was born they were married,</hi>
                     </hi> (which indeed by the <note n="b" place="margin">C. tit. de Nat. lib. c. eum quis 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Imperials, and by the general Law of <note n="c" place="margin">Videſis <hi>Bacquet</hi> de Domaino du fr-tract. du Baſtardiſe. <hi>c. 9, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>France,</hi> would have made him wholy legitimate); I doubt he had but little or no ground to juſtify it. Had he been ſo legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, it is not likely he ſhould have been ſtiled ſo commonly and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently <hi>Baſtardus;</hi> which Name, even in his <note n="d" place="margin">Apud <hi>Cambden</hi> in Richmondia.</note> own Charters he ſometimes uſed with <hi>cognomento;</hi> as alſo the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards of the old <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> were wont to do; although of later Time it be reputed as a Name of diſhonour; and the <hi>actio injuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or an Action upon the Caſe lies where-ever it be falſly objected, as
<pb n="xlvi" facs="tcp:59543:30"/> ſome will <note n="e" place="margin">Videſis Pont. Heute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de liberis Natural. <hi>c. 12.</hi>
                     </note> have it. But theſe things prove enough, that this <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> ſeized the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> not as <hi>conquered,</hi> but by pretence of Gift or Adoption, aided and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by nearneſs of Blood; and ſo the <hi>Saxon</hi> Laws formerly in force could not but continue: And ſuch of them as are now abrogated, were not at all abrogated by his <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Parliaments or Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Time, and of his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or elſe by non-uſage or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cuſtom. </q>
               </p>
               <p>Surely then none can believe, that <hi>William</hi> claimed <hi>only</hi> by the Sword, and made an <hi>abſolute Conqueſt;</hi> or that he <hi>aboliſh'd</hi> all the old Saxon <hi>Laws,</hi> and conſtituted a new Frame and Syſteme of Government, entirely for the Intereſt of his <hi>Normans,</hi> and to the ſlavery and ruin of the whole <hi>Engliſh;</hi> nor can any one, me-thinks, after this, categorically atteſt that there were no <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> in the Common Council of the whole Kingdom; or that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had neither Eſtates nor Fortunes left; and that therefore it were of no great matter and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to them, by what Law, Right,
<pb n="xlvii" facs="tcp:59543:30"/> or Property, other Men held their Eſtates.</p>
               <p>But not to dwell upon the great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Learned Man, we will now hear what Sir <hi>Winſton Churchill</hi> can inform us as to your Second Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; <hi>Whether the <hi>Laws</hi> were totally <hi>aboliſhed,</hi> and a New Government ſet up, according to the <hi>Arbitrary Will</hi> and Pleaſure of this</hi> Norman Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor?</p>
               <p>And thus he writes, in his Book de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to his preſent Majeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Duke <hi>William,</hi> better known to us<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Winst. Churchill</hi>'s Divi Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. <hi>fol. 189.</hi>
                     </note> here by the Name of <hi>the <hi>Conqueror,</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> who with like Confidence, and not unlike Injuſtice, (as <hi>Rollo</hi> did <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> the ſeventh in Deſcent, from whom was this Duke) <q>invaded <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> pretending a Donation of the Soveraignty from his near Kinſman King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as he alledged, by his laſt Will and Teſtament, in the preſence of moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility. But<note place="margin">Id. <hi>fo. 190.</hi>
                     </note> what we allow to the Courage, we muſt take from the Wiſdom of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> that being ſubdued, they
<pb n="xlviii" facs="tcp:59543:31"/> continued <hi>neſcia vinci,</hi> vexing the Conqueror, after they had ſubmitted to him, by ſuch continual Revolts, as ſuffered him not to ſheath his Sword all his Reign; or if he did, urged him to continue ſtill ſo ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of their Loyalty, that he was forced always to keep his hand upon the Hilt, ready to draw it forth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not leaſure to intend what was before eſtabliſhed, much leſs to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh what he before intended: So that they put upon him a kind of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being a Tyrant, to make good his being a King: Yet ſuch was the moderation of his mind, that he choſe rather to bind them ſtricter to him by the old Laws, than to gall them with any New, guarding his Prerogative within that Citadel of the <hi>Burrough Law</hi> (as they called it) from whence, as often as they began to mutiny, he battered them with their own Ordnance, and ſo made them Parties to their own wrong; and however ſome that deſigned to preoccupate the Grace of Servitude, gave him the ungrateful Title of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror,</hi> which he eſteemed the greateſt misfortune his good Fortune had
<pb n="xlix" facs="tcp:59543:31"/> brought upon him) thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim his <hi>Power</hi> to be as <hi>boundleſs</hi> as his <hi>Will;</hi> which they took to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Limitation or Contradiction; yet we find he ſuffered himſelf to be <hi>ſo far conquered</hi> by them, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of giving to, he took the Law from them, and contentedly bound himſelf up by thoſe, which they called <hi>St. Edward's Laws;</hi> which being an abbreviation of the great Tripple Code of <hi>Danique, Merke,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Sexe Laws,</hi> was ſuch a form of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, as he himſelf could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to introduce a better; and if any thing <hi>look'd</hi> like <hi>Abſolute,</hi> 'twas his diſarming them, when he found them thus <hi>Law-bound</hi> hand and foot.</q>
               </p>
               <p>From this Authority, Sir, I think, it is very plain and obvious, That</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. Here was no <hi>Abſolute Conqueſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. That neither were all the <hi>Saxon</hi> Laws <hi>cancelled</hi> and <hi>aboliſhed,</hi> by the <hi>coming in</hi> of this <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="l" facs="tcp:59543:32"/>
                  <item>I. That here was no <hi>Abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt;</hi> becauſe,
<list>
                        <item>1. Tho' here was an <hi>invading <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                           </hi> yet it was <hi>upon pretence of a Donation of the Soveraignty from <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi>
                           </hi> confirmed by his laſt Will, and that <hi>in the preſence of moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</hi> And ſo it was only an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to get his own upon the Claim of an alledged <hi>juſt Title;</hi> which ſhewed he had, at leaſt, more reaſon to demand, than <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold,</hi> who, at beſt, was an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to detain the Crown: And ſo the Quarrel to be more Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal than National.</item>
                        <item>2. The <hi>Conqueſt</hi> could <hi>not be Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> for tho' he was, by a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſs over <hi>Harold,</hi> poſſeſſor of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne; yet ſaith my Author, The Nation <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, neſcia vinci;</hi> ſo that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was <hi>Tyrannical</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary,</hi> they were continually vexing him with their Revolts.</item>
                        <pb n="li" facs="tcp:59543:32"/>
                        <item>3. This <hi>Conqueſt</hi> could not be <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> becauſe then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> muſt have been <hi>perfect Slaves</hi> and Vaſſals to his <hi>uncontroulable <hi>Beck;</hi>
                           </hi> but (alas!) here Sir <hi>Winſton</hi> tells you, the <hi>Norman Conqueror</hi> could find them no ſuch eaſy Beaſts of Burthen, their Necks would not bear the Yokes of his Severity; for they were ſeveral times up in Arms againſt him, and that <hi>after they had ſubmitted to him:</hi> ſo that at moſt this could be but a ſubmiſſion upon terms.</item>
                        <item>4. He was ſo far from being in love with the gawdy name of <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> that when ſome, that <hi>deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to preoccupate the Grace of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, gave him that ungrateful Title, he eſteemed it the greateſt misfortune his good Fortune had brought upon him.</hi> And,</item>
                        <item>5. The <hi>Conqueſt</hi> ſurely could not be <hi>abſolute,</hi> for then it would have been very idle and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for any one to ſay, what Sir <hi>Winſton,</hi> no doubt, but upon good and mature conſideration, hath thought fit to ſay of him, that <hi>if any thing look'd like <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute;</hi>
                           </hi>
                           <pb n="lii" facs="tcp:59543:33"/> and hereby you may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take notice, that he ſeems to wonder how any Man can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make him an <hi>abſolute Conqueror,</hi> when he could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find ſo much as <hi>any thing to look like it.</hi> But,</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. I ſhall obſerve to you, that neither were all the <hi>Saxon</hi> Laws <hi>cancelled</hi> and <hi>aboliſhed</hi> by the <hi>coming in</hi> of this <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. If King <hi>William</hi> might have done <hi>deſpotically</hi> whatſoever he had a mind to, then what neceſſity was there for <hi>ſuch a moderation of his Mind,</hi> as the Author hints to us?</item>
                        <item>2. Becauſe he found the People were not to be <hi>galled with any New, he choſe rather</hi> (but it was a choice upon Neceſſity) <hi>to bind them ſtricter to him by the Old Laws;</hi> that is, in plain down-right Engliſh, they would not yield to him, nor to his Government, unleſs he reſolved to circumſcribe his ruling of them, within the bounds of the good <hi>Old Laws,</hi> in which
<pb n="liii" facs="tcp:59543:33"/> they were born and bred; and make his <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Normans</hi> come over and buckle to them.</item>
                        <item>3. <hi>He ſuffered himſelf to be ſo far conquered by them,</hi> as to let them have their <hi>Old Laws;</hi> and it was with a kind of good ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction too: For,</item>
                        <item>4. The Book tells you, <hi>He conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly bound himſelf up by thoſe which they called <hi>St. Edward's Laws:</hi>
                           </hi> And was there not, do ye think, very good Reaſon for his ſo doing? when thereby,</item>
                        <item>5. He underſtood at length, that it was a <hi>guarding his Prerogative,</hi> to keep <hi>within that <hi>Cittadel</hi> of the <hi>Burrough Law.</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. And laſtly, We cannot rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think he would, after he had thereby throughly looked into them, <hi>cancel</hi> and <hi>aboliſh</hi> them; ſince thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> were ſuch, as, it is ſaid, <hi>he himſelf could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to introduce a better.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I hope, Sir, all theſe Deductions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe naturally from the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without any force or ſtrain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſence; and what I have ſaid,
<pb n="liv" facs="tcp:59543:34"/> may be ſufficient to convince you, that King <hi>William</hi> ſtill kept to the <hi>Saxon Laws,</hi> and did not change the whole <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> as, you ſay, is very ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly, and with heat, aſſerted by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of our Modern Authors.</p>
               <p>I ſhall yet make bold with your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Sir, and ſhew you what <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius Wigornienſis,</hi> (a famous Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian in King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Time) and <hi>Brompton</hi> from him, ſay upon this Point, and ſo conclude my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henricus primus omnes malas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudines</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Floren. Wig. <hi>fol. 650.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; injuſtas exactiones (qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Regnum Angliae injuſtè opprimebatur) abſtulit, pacem firmam in toto Regno ſuo poſuit, &amp; teneri praecepit. Legem Regis Edwardi omnibus in commune reddidit, cum illis emendationibus, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Pater ſuus illam emendavit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brompton</hi>'s words are the ſame, and<note place="margin">In Hen. 1. <hi>fol. 997, 998.</hi>
                  </note> therefore I ſhall content my ſelf with only referring you to the Book, without repeating them to you. And, Sir, from hence we may learn,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="lv" facs="tcp:59543:34"/>1. That this King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Father, <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, was ſo far from <hi>cancelling</hi> and <hi>aboliſhing</hi> K. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward's Laws,</hi> that he made them to be the Common <hi>ſtanding Laws</hi> of the Land, to be equally and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably obſerved as well by the <hi>Normans</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for he ſays, <hi>omnibus eam in commune red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit;</hi> unleſs you will underſtand the word <hi>Omnibus</hi> to be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Univerſal, and ſo only to include the <hi>Normans:</hi> And if ſo, then it follows likewiſe, That inſtead of the <hi>Normans</hi> giving to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> their <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> were impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Normans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And whereas there were, 'tis confeſt, ſome <hi>Additional Laws</hi> made in his Time, yet you may plainly obſerve hence, that they were grounded upon, and but a better Improvement and Melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Confeſſor's Laws;</hi> and they were for the Sake, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,</hi> and Advantage of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> as you will find hereafter.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="lvi" facs="tcp:59543:35"/>3. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, Son to this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror <hi>William,</hi>
                  </hi> took away <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes malas conſuetudines &amp; injuſtas exactiones,</hi> &amp;c. by which <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had been ſorely oppreſſed, under his Brother <hi>William Rufus,</hi> and reſtored the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to their <hi>former Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> and he renewed and confirmed the Ancient <hi>Saxon Laws,</hi> as his Father had done before him, as it is well noted in the continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hiſtory of <hi>Bede, In</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bede <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 30. <hi>fol. 347.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Concilio peritorum &amp; proborum virorum Regni Angliae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But if there had been <hi>no Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> but the <hi>Normans;</hi> if the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had all the Eſtates of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> given them; if there were none but <hi>Normans</hi> in the <hi>Common Councils</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; how is it poſſible to be ſuppoſed, by any that will allow themſelves the free uſe of their Reaſon, that <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt would ever make ſuch a Grant; or, if he did, that the <hi>Normans</hi> would ever ſubmit to it; or
<pb n="lvii" facs="tcp:59543:35"/> (what is much more unlikely) give their conſent to <hi>out</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all their new-gotten Poſſeſſions, and reduce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves back to this notorious <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma, viz.</hi> either to live <hi>Vaſſals</hi> and <hi>Slaves</hi> under the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or elſe <hi>vertere ſolum,</hi> return to <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> from whence they came.</p>
               <p>There is one thing more which I cannot but mention, and that is, The inconſiderateneſs of thoſe Men, who ſo mightily cry up the <hi>abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> over the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as if they were utterly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and cruſhed, and all their <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Tuſtoms <hi>deſtroyed;</hi>
                  </hi> when, as it is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrably<note place="margin">Sim. Dunelm. <hi>An. 1088. f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 214. Angli e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fideliter juvabant.</note> manifeſt, that at the Time of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> and his <hi>Normans,</hi> Treaſon and <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt <hi>William Rufus</hi> then King, and his Brother, to cut off him, and make <hi>Robert</hi> King in his room; I ſay, then the Intereſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was ſo great and powerful, that it kept the <hi>Crown</hi> upon <hi>Rufus</hi>'s Head, maugre all the Power of the <hi>Normans,</hi> who uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally joined with <hi>Robert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Sir, now I will conſider the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your next Queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <pb n="lvili" facs="tcp:59543:36"/>
               <head>The Third Queſtion.</head>
               <head type="sub">III. <hi>Whether it be true, That the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Anoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Author againſt Mr.</hi> Petyt. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Engliſh <hi>had neither</hi> Eſtates <hi>nor</hi> Fortunes <hi>left, but all was divided between the</hi> King <hi>and his</hi>
                  </hi> Normans?</head>
               <p>THough it be confeſſed, that this firſt <hi>William</hi> obtained the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> yet I think I have clearly made it out to you, Sir, that it was by <hi>a Reception upon Terms,</hi> and not by <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> and it is no leſs obvious, that the <hi>Laws</hi> in general, which were, after ſuch his <hi>Acquiſition,</hi> ratified and confirmed, and which continued in full force and power, were the old <hi>Saxon Laws;</hi> and though it cannot be denied, but that he did introduce ſome <hi>new Laws</hi> of his own, yet thoſe, <hi>quas conſtitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> you have heard, were made, <hi>ad utilitatem Anglorum,</hi> for the Benefit
<pb n="lix" facs="tcp:59543:36"/> and Advantage of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> without the leaſt mention either of the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Normans.</hi> And obſervable too it is, that thoſe Laws<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were made <hi>per Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune Concilium totius Regni. Apud Lambard. inter Leges Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iel. primi, fol. 170. de Statut.</hi> 55.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And if ſo, Sir, me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thinks this ſeems as one ſtrong Argument, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could not have all their <hi>Eſtates</hi> &amp; <hi>Fortunes</hi> violently raviſhed from them; nor the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> at their <hi>coming in,</hi> could not <hi>abſolutely</hi> ſweep away all the Stakes, becauſe the good <hi>Old Law</hi> was ſtill in its full being and virtue; <note n="*" place="margin">Co. 12. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. fol. 65.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>which was the Metwand and Menſure to try the Cauſes of the Subjects;</hi> and, <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In his first Speech to his firſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in Engl. Stat. 1. Jac. c. 2. <hi>fol. 1157.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by which,</hi> ſaith the wife King <hi>James, the People's ſecurity of Lands, Livings, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, were preſerved and maintained; and,</hi> which alſo is, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>K.</hi> Charl. 1. <hi>Declaration to all his Doring Subjects pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with the Advice of his Privy Council.</hi> Exact Collect. &amp;c. <hi>p 28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Inheritance of every Subject, and the only ſecurity he can have for his Life or Eſtate.</hi> And then they could not <hi>loſe</hi> all they had at this rate, but it muſt be by a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>wrong</hi> to the <hi>Priviledg,</hi> as well as <hi>well-being</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> and, no doubt, if the <hi>Law</hi> had its due courſe,
<pb n="lx" facs="tcp:59543:37"/> as I have made that plain it had, but that their <hi>Native Rights</hi> were eaſily <hi>recoverable;</hi> and the ravaging <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> could not keep them in ſpight of all Juſtice; for that were a total <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But in the next place, Sir, I make no queſtion but that I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, that the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> at leaſt thoſe who lived in Peace <hi>before,</hi> and at his <hi>coming</hi> to the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, did quietly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably enjoy their Inheritances; and their Titles and Claims to them from their <hi>Saxon Anceſtors,</hi> were held good and allowed; which, to be ſure, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could have done, had this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom received ſuch an <hi>univerſal Change</hi> and <hi>Revolution,</hi> as ſo many of our late Learned Authors would needs have us firmly to believe.</p>
               <p>Saith Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Ric. Baker'<hi>s Chronic. fol. 23.</hi>
                  </note> of this King's Life and Reign; <q>Though he hath had the Name of <hi>Conqueror,</hi> yet he uſed not the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as gotten by <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> for he took no Man's living from him, nor diſpoſſeſſed any of their Goods, but
<pb n="lxi" facs="tcp:59543:37"/> ſuch only, whoſe demerit made them unworthy to hold them, as appears by his Act to one <hi>Warren</hi> a <hi>Norman,</hi> to whom he had given the Caſtle of <hi>Sherborne</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                  </q> The Story is faithfully this, as you may find in <hi>Cambden</hi>'s <hi>Britannia;</hi> The King, it ſeems, had given away <hi>Sherborne</hi> to <hi>Warren</hi> a <hi>Norman,</hi> and one that was his great Favourite; which <hi>Edwinus de Sherborne</hi> perceiving, who was the true Owner of the Caſtle, and an <hi>Engliſh Man,</hi> demands, before the King, his <hi>right,</hi> in open Court, tells him it did, <hi>de jure,</hi> belong to him, upon this Reaſon of Law, for that he never had took up Arms againſt the King, either before his coming in, or<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Petyt'<hi>s Ancient Right of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>aſſerted.</hi> Pref. <hi>p. 24.</hi>
                  </note> ſince; whereupon the King, <hi>vinculo juramenti aſtrictus,</hi> gave Judgment of <hi>Right</hi> againſt the <hi>Norman,</hi> and <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> recovered the Lordſhip.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> tells you the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he hath taken out of an Ancient Manuſcript, concerning the Family of the <hi>Sharborns,</hi> thus; <hi>Edwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spelm.</hi> Gloſſ. verbo Dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. <hi>p. 184.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>de Sharborne, &amp; quidam alii, qui ejecti fuerunt è terris ſuis, abierunt ad <hi>Conqueſtorem,</hi> &amp; dixerunt ei, quod
<pb n="lxii" facs="tcp:59543:38"/> nunquam ante <hi>Conqueſtum,</hi> nec in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtu</hi> ſuo, nec poſt, fuerunt contra ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Regem in Conſilio &amp; Auxilio, ſed tenuerunt ſe in pace. Et hoc parati ſunt probare quomodo ipſe Rex vellet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinare. Per quod idem Rex fecit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiri per totam Angliam ſi ita fuit, quod quidem probatum fuit: propter quod idem Rex praecepit, ut omnes illi qui ſic tenuerunt ſe in pace in forma praedicta, quod ipſi, rehaberent omnes terras &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationes ſuas adeo integrè &amp; in pace ut unquam habuerunt, vel tenuerunt ante <hi>Conqueſtum</hi> ſuum.</hi> That is;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Edwin</hi> of <hi>Sharborn,</hi> and ſeveral others that were ejected out of their Eſtates and Poſſeſſions, went to the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> and told him, that they never either before, or in, or after the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> were againſt him the ſaid King, either by their Advice, or any other Aid, but kept themſelves peaceably and quietly. And this they were ready to make out, which way ſoever the King pleaſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point. Whereupon the ſaid King ordered an Inquiſition to be made throughout all <hi>England,</hi> whether it were ſo or no; which was plainly proved: Therefore he preſently
<pb n="lxiii" facs="tcp:59543:38"/> commanded, that all thoſe who ſo kept themſelves peaceably in manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as theſe had done, ſhould be repoſſeſſed of all their Eſtates and Inheritances as fully, amply, and quietly, as ever they had or held them before his <hi>Conqueſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is a Caſe ſo full to the Point, and ſo plain to every common Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in its ſelf, that it would be frivolous to make any deductions from it. I ſhall preſume to repeat to you the words of a great and Learned Judg in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, and give you his judicious Aſſertion of this Argument, (tho' it be cited before in that of Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>) becauſe it was agreed on as a main po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Rule of Law; and they are theſe;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Conqueror</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ne vient</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Johannes Shardelowe</hi> unus Juſtic. de Banco. Rot. Pat. 16. E. 3. Pars 1. m. 2. in <hi>Dugdales</hi> Chronica Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>annexed to his</hi> Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Juridicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. <hi>fol. 44.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pas pour ouſter eux, qui avoient droitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell poſſeſſion, mes de ouſter eux que de lour tort avoient occupie aſcun terre en deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance del Roy &amp; ſon Coronne.</hi> 
                  <q>The <hi>Conqueror</hi> came not to ouſt thoſe who had a Right Poſſeſſion, but to diſpoſſeſs thoſe, who, of their own wrong, had enjoyed any Land to
<pb n="lxiv" facs="tcp:59543:39"/> the diſheriſon of the King and his Crown.</q>
               </p>
               <p>What ſhall we think after all this? That notwithſtanding, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> who had not been in Arms againſt <hi>William,</hi> had <hi>no Eſtates</hi> or <hi>Fortunes</hi> left, but <hi>all</hi> was divided between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Normans?</hi> Surely no, but juſt the contrary, that they did enjoy them in as full, peaceable, and quiet a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as ever they did, <hi>before</hi> he <hi>came</hi> to be this high and mighty <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But again, let me give you, Sir, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Inſtance to inforce the Truth of this Argument.</p>
               <p>In the 14. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. ſome 290 Years<note place="margin">Placita coram Rege Hill. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 14. R. 2. Rot. 50. War. vid. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> &amp; <hi>Dugdales</hi> Monaſtic. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican. <hi>Vol. 1. fol. 305. Col. 1.</hi>
                  </note> ago, there happened a <hi>memorable</hi> Suit between the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Prior</hi> of <hi>Coventry,</hi> in the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> the King demanding <hi>Annuam Penſionem pro uno Clericorum Regis,</hi> as holding <hi>de Domino Rege per Baroniam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prior pleads, that he held <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oratum praedictum,</hi> upon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Leofric, quondam Comitis Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriae,</hi> founded in the Time <hi>Sancti
<pb n="lxv" facs="tcp:59543:39"/> Edwardi Regis Angliae,</hi> and produces the Charters in Court, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys the Title of Deſcent, thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibidem recitatur Charta ejuſdem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jus Anglorum ab antiquo. <hi>p. 16. in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Edwardi, quas Donationes &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiones diverſi alii Reges confirmave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp; dicit quod poſtea per proceſſum temporis nomen Abbatiae praedictae diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebatur in nomen Prioratus, eo quod Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ofwinus ad tunc Abbas ibidem creatus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it in Epiſcopum Ceſtriae, &amp; ordinavit per Aſſenſum Monachorum ibidem quod Abbatia praedicta ex tunc foret Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oratus, &amp; quod Superiores ejuſdem Eccleſiae forent Priores ſucceſſivè in perpetuum, &amp; dicit quod</hi> de ipſo Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frico, quia obiit ſine Haerede de corpore ſuo deſcendente, Advocatio Eccleſiae praedictae tempore Willielm' Conqueſt' Angliae cuidam Hugoni Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miti Ceſtriae, ut Conſanguineo &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redi, ipſius Leofrici, viz. Filio Ermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilde<note place="margin">Not. <hi>This is the</hi> Hugh <hi>to whom it is i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined by ſome, that</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>gave all the Lands of the County of</hi> Cheſter.</note> ſororis ejuſdem Leofrici, <hi>&amp; de ipſo Hugone cuidam Richardo ut Filio &amp; haeredi, &amp; de ipſo Richardo cuidam Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulpho, ut Conſanguineo &amp; haeredi, viz. Filio Matildis Sororis praedicti Hugonis &amp; de ipſo Ranulpho cuidam Ranulpho ut Filio &amp; Haeredi, &amp; de ipſo Ranulpho Filio Ranulphi, quia obiit ſine Haerede
<pb n="lxvi" facs="tcp:59543:40"/> de corpore ſuo deſcendente, Advocatio praedicta ſimul cum Comitatu Ceſtriae &amp; Huntingdon, &amp; aliis diverſis Caſtris, Maneriis, terris &amp; tenementis cum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentiis in Anglia &amp; Wallia quibuſdam Matildae, Mabilliae, Ceciliae &amp; Margeriae ut Sororibus &amp; Haeredibus praedicti Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulphi, inter quas propertia facta fuit de praedictis Comitatibus, Advocationibus &amp; Caſtris, Maneriis, Terris &amp; Tenementis cum pertinentiis ſupradictis. Et prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta Advocatio, ſimul cum toto praedicto Comitatu Ceſtriae, cum pertinentiis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locata fuit praedictae Matilde pro proparte ſua in Allocationem diverſorum aliorum Caſtrorum, Manneriorum, Terrarum &amp; Tenementorum cum pertinentiis praedictis Mabilliae, Ceciliae &amp; Margeriae ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim allocatorum, &amp; de ipſa Matilda de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendebant praedicta Advocatio ſimul cum praedicto Comitatu Ceſtriae cum pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis poſt propertiam praedictam cuidam Johanni Scot ut Filio &amp; haeredi praedictae Matildae, qui quidem Johannes Scot Advocationem praedictam ſimul cum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto Comitatu Ceſtriae cum Pertinentiis dedit Henrico quondam Regi Angliae Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Regis Johannis &amp; haeredibus ſuis in perpetuum, &amp;c. Praedictus Prior ſine die.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="lxvil" facs="tcp:59543:40"/>
               <p>From this <hi>great Record,</hi> Sir, I think it is clear and evident;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Leofric</hi> was Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> and that he dying without Iſſue, the Earldom of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and the Right of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowſon of the Priory of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, tempore Willielmi Conqueſtoris Angliae,</hi> deſcended to <hi>Hugh</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter, ut Conſanguineo &amp; Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redi ipſius Leofrici,</hi> as being the Son of <hi>Erminelde,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric;</hi> and that from that <hi>Hugh,</hi> deſcended <hi>Richard</hi> his Son and Heir; and from <hi>Richard</hi> deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ranulf,</hi> as <hi>conſanguineus &amp; haeres,</hi> that is the Son of <hi>Maud,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Hugh;</hi> and from that <hi>Ranulph</hi> another <hi>Ranulph</hi> his Son and Heir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now if <hi>William,</hi> when he came in, made an <hi>abſolute Conqueſt,</hi> this Title had been impoſſible to have been maintained.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="lxviii" facs="tcp:59543:41"/>3. It appears further, That the Plea of the Prior was allowed; for the Record ſaith, <hi>Praedictus Prior ſine die.</hi> And the Advowſon aforeſaid, <hi>ſimul cum Comitatu Ceſtriae &amp; Huntingdon, &amp; aliis diverſis Maneriis, Terris &amp; Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, cum pertinentiis, &amp;c.</hi> did deſcend. And it is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that Judgment being given upon ſolemn Debate and Tryal, neither the Judges, nor the King's Counſel, ſo many hundred Years ago, as in the Age of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, knew any thing of this new received Notion of an <hi>abſolute Conqueſt.</hi> And again,</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis yet further obſervable, that the Charter of <hi>Leofric,</hi> and the Title of the Prior had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>per diverſos alios Reges,</hi> who muſt certainly have greater knowledg of the Nature of <hi>William</hi> the Firſt his <hi>Conqueſt</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> than any Man can pretend to in our Times.</p>
               <pb n="lxix" facs="tcp:59543:41"/>
               <p>But further, Sir, I will make bold with your Patience, and give you ſome few Inſtances, of the very many that I could, out of <hi>Dooms-day</hi> Book, to ſatisfy you, that there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Proprietors</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Men,</hi> who had their Free-hold Eſtates, upon Titles paramount to any of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi>'s Donation. Thoſe I ſhall take from that induſtrious and worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, Mr. <hi>Attwood</hi>'s Book, intituled,<note place="margin">Jus Anglorum ab Antiquo. <hi>p. 80, 81, 83, 87, 89, 90.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jus Anglorum ab Antiquo,</hi> where, in his excellent Hiſtory of the <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> among others he hath theſe following, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surrey.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Hugo de Port</hi> was a very great<note place="margin">Pa. 80. <hi>He was not</hi> Tainus Regis.</note> 
                  <hi>Proprietor,</hi> as may be found under the Title, <hi>Terra Hugonis de Port:</hi> Many <hi>Mannors</hi> he had; and as appears in <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> he had at leaſt two <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Cerdeford</hi> and <hi>Eſchetune,</hi> from his <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> before <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>'s Entrance.</p>
               <pb n="lxx" facs="tcp:59543:42"/>
               <p>And even this is a ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he was a great Man, that he had a Sir-name, or Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</p>
               <p>Becauſe, if we believe the Great Antiquary, Mr. <hi>Cambden, Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Camb. <hi>Rem. p. 136.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>were not ſetled among the Common People fully, till about the Time of</hi> Edw. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Earl of <hi>Moreton,</hi> a very<note place="margin">Ipſe Comes tenuit Eſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. T. R. E.</note> powerful <hi>Prince,</hi> as I may call him, held <hi>Eſtreham</hi> in <hi>Tenrige</hi> Hundred, in the Time of King <hi>Edward.</hi> He enjoyed ſeveral other great Poſſeſſions of the <hi>Gift</hi> of King <hi>William.</hi> I doubt not indeed but he was a <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> born, yet he was here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the entrance of the <hi>Norman</hi> Duke, and might, not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, be in Favour with King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Confeſſor,</hi> who was all<note place="margin">Camb. <hi>Rem. p. 136.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Frenchified.</hi> He, to be ſure, had ſome Lands within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> which he enjoyed not from <hi>William</hi>'s Diviſion.<note place="margin">Pag. 176.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="lxxi" facs="tcp:59543:42"/>
               <p>Hampſhire.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Ralph Mortimer</hi> held ſeveral Poſſeſſions, ſome of which he had <hi>Jure Haereditario,</hi> from before the <hi>Reputed Conqueſt. <hi>Ipſe Radul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus tenet Ordie:</hi>
                  </hi> This Mannor T. R. E. <hi>extra Eccleſiam emptum fuit, eo pacto &amp; conventione, ut poſt tertium haeredem cum omni pecunia Manerium Eccleſia Sancti Petri de Epiſcopatu recuperet; nunc qui tenet Radulphus, eſt tertius haeres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dorſetſhire.<note place="margin">Dorſete.</note>
               </p>
               <p>4. Ten <hi>Thains</hi> hold <hi>Chimedecome. Ipſi tenuerunt</hi> T. R. E. <hi>pro. 1. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerio. Omnes qui has terras te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuerunt</hi> T. R. E. <hi>potuerunt ire ad quem Dominum volebant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Staffordſhire.<note place="margin">Statfordſcire</note>
               </p>
               <p>5 <hi>Alric</hi> holds <hi>Stagriſgeſhowe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ipſi has Terras tenuerunt T. R. E.</note> And <hi>Aſwold</hi> holds <hi>Chrocheſdene.</hi> 14. more hold Lands of Titles, Prior to King <hi>William</hi>'s, amongſt
<pb n="lxxii" facs="tcp:59543:43"/> which, the Earls, <hi>Hugh de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers,</hi> and <hi>Alberic de Vere;</hi> the firſt of which held St. <hi>Warburgh</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in the Time of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. And laſtly; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ctred</hi> held ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Lands in the Time of King <hi>Edward,</hi> as in the Time of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam the Firſt.</hi> Beſides, ſeveral diſpoſſeſſed, who have their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles allowed.</p>
               <p>I think theſe ſix Inſtances are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (referring the more curious to Mr. <hi>Attwood</hi>'s Book before mentioned, or to the great Survey it ſelf) to bear out my Aſſertion, <q>That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> ſtill in their hands, which they held in King <hi>Edward's.</hi> Time, and did not derive under King <hi>William's Title.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Having now given you theſe ſix In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals, I ſhall offer you three more, and they are from the <hi>Charters</hi> of King <hi>William;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> to the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> confirming to him the Lands, &amp;c. belonging to that <hi>Church,</hi> and this was upon the day of his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation</hi>
                  <pb n="lxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:43"/> too: The <hi>other</hi> is to the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by of <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> and the <hi>third</hi> to the <hi>City of London,</hi> granting to them the <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Franchiſes</hi> which they enjoyed in the Time of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To begin with <hi>that</hi> made to the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ego Willielmus Dei Gratia Rex</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carta Regis Williel. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtor. in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendice in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Eccleſ. Cathedr. S. Pauli. <hi>By Sir</hi> Will. Dugdale. <hi>fol. 190.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anglorum, unà cum Mathilda Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ, Principibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meis, coram con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu Sacerdotum Dei, Reverendis ſcilicet Archiepiſcopis Aldredo &amp; Stigando, caeteriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Epiſcopis &amp; Abbatibus hujus Patriae, terras Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterii Sancti Pauli, quae in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Anteceſſorum meorum à qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſlibet hominibus ablatae fuerant, &amp; injuſtè detentae, omnes in die primi Diadematis &amp; <hi>Coronationis meae,</hi> Deo, ejuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Apoſtolo Paulo in Lundonia, &amp; eorum ſervitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in perpetuùm poſſidendas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitui, &amp; eas ex omni parte libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras eſſe conceſſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="lxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:44"/>2. <hi>William the Firſt</hi> gives the<note place="margin">Cartae. Antiq. C. C. n. 31.</note> Church of <hi>Weſtminſter, <hi>deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam de Wic de eadem parte quae ad me pertinebat, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> iterùm red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi eandem partem eis injuſtè ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latam quàm Rex Edwardus antea dederat.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that we ſee, that as on the one hand <hi>William the Firſt</hi> gave them the <hi>Tithes</hi> of that part which was his right; ſo likewiſe he reſtored the <hi>Tithes</hi> of that part which was unjuſtly taken from that <hi>Church,</hi> and which <hi>Edward the Confeſſor</hi> had before gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And <hi>no Conqueſt</hi> was here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but the Precedent proves the quite contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> that there was none inſiſted on.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And now I come to that reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>City of London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Williem King grets Williem Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceop and Godfred <note n="*" place="margin">Porteregra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave. Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicè. Hollinſhead'<hi>s 3d Vol. fol.</hi> 15. 2. Col. n. 21.</note> Porterefan, &amp; ealle ya Burghwarn binnen London Frenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e &amp; <hi>Engliſe</hi> frendlice, &amp; Ic kiden eoy, yeet Ic wille yeet git ben ealra weera l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gayweord, ye get weeran on
<pb n="lxxv" facs="tcp:59543:44"/> Eadwerds daege Kings. And Ic wille yeet aelc child by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yrfnume, aefter his Faders daege. And Ic nelle ge Wolian, yeet adnig man eoy aenis wrang beode. God eoy heald.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willielmus Rex Salutat Willielmum Epiſcopum &amp; Goffridum Porte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grefium, &amp; omnem Burghware in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra London Franſ. &amp;</hi> Angl. <hi>ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabilitèr. Et vobis notum facio, quòd ego volo quòd vos ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> omni lege illa digni quae fuiſtis Edwardi diebus Regis. Et volo quod omnis Puer ſit Patris ſui haeres poſt diem Patris ſui. Et ego nolo pati quòd aliquis homo aliquam inju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam vobis inferat. Deus vos ſalvet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Engliſhed in <hi>Stow</hi>'s Survey of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stow'<hi>s Survey of</hi> London. <hi>fol. 740.</hi>
                  </note> thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>William King grete William Biſhop and Godfrey Porters and al the Burgeis within <hi>London</hi> Frenſh and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And I grant you that I wyll that <hi>yee be all your Lawe worth,</hi> that ye were in <hi>Edwardis dayes</hi> the King. And I wyl that ich Childe be his
<pb n="lxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:45"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="lxxv" facs="tcp:59543:45"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="lxxvi" facs="tcp:59543:46"/> Faders Eyer. And I nyl ſuffur, that ony Man you any wrongys beed. And God you kepe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now 'tis evident from this Charter;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That it was made, immediately upon, or after, the <hi>Coronation</hi> of <hi>William;</hi> becauſe, you ſee, he ſtiles himſelf <hi>King.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. This may ſeem to <hi>juſtify,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what the <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> who lived neareſt his Time, (as <hi>Pictavien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> &amp;c.) but what his <hi>own Laws</hi> do likewiſe declare, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was <hi>crowned</hi> King by <hi>compact</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and at the ſame time ſwore inviolably to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve King <hi>Edwards Laws,</hi> which he confirmed to them.</item>
                  <item>3. With this further, That he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced a <hi>ſevere Prohibition,</hi> that no Man ſhould <hi>offer</hi> any <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front,</hi> or <hi>do</hi> any <hi>wrong</hi> to the <hi>Citizens of London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. And for a compleat aſſurance of all this his <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs</hi> to
<pb n="lxxvii" facs="tcp:59543:46"/> the <hi>City,</hi> he concludes with a Prayer to Heaven, That <hi>God would keep and bleſs them.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>But by the way give me leave to ſhew you (though I think likewiſe it does not a little contribute to the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>validity</hi> of my <hi>Argument</hi>) the Greatneſs and Power of the <hi>City of London</hi> in thoſe early Times, I ſhall <hi>tranſcribe</hi> the words of a <hi>Learned Writer</hi> concerning it, and ſo leave it to your more ſerious conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stephanides,</hi> a Monk of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> born (as <hi>Stow</hi> ſaith in his fore-cited Book) of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Parents in the <hi>City of London,</hi> and who lived in the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stephanid.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptio Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimae Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, <hi>in</hi> Stow'<hi>s</hi> Survey, <hi>&amp;c. fol.</hi> 704. de ſitu ejuſdem.</note> Reign of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> in his deſcription of it, hath theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inter Nobiles <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes Orbis quas fama celebrat, Civitas Londonia, Regni An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum ſedes una eſt, quae famam ſui latiùs diffundit, opes &amp; merces longiùs tranſmittit, caput altius extollit. Foelix eſt aëris ſalubritate, Chriſtianâ Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, firmitate munitionum, naturâ ſitûs,
<pb n="lxxviii" facs="tcp:59543:47"/> honore Civium, pudicitiâ matronali, ludis etiám quàm jucunda, &amp; Nobilium foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda virorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs iſta viris eſt honorata, armis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. <hi>fol. 705.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>multo habitatore populoſa, ut tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Bellicae cladis ſub Rege Stephano bello apti, ex e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exeuntes oſtentatui, haberen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur 20000 Armatorum Equitum, 60 mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Peditum aeſtimarentur. Cives Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doniae ubicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> locorum prae omnibus aliis Civibus ornatu morum, veſtium &amp; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, locutione, ſpectabiles &amp; noti haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which in Engliſh is thus;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Of all the <hi>celebrated Cities</hi> in the World, this of <hi>London</hi> is the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> a <hi>City</hi> of a very extenſive Fame in its ſelf, but much more honourable by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Treaſure and Commodities which ſhe exporteth. Happy is ſhe in the temperature of her Climate, in the ſoundneſs of her Doctrine, ſtrength of her Forts, agreeableneſs of her Situation; in the Credit and Reputation of her Citizens; the unblemiſh'd Chaſtity of the Female Sex; innocently pleaſant, even in
<pb n="lxxix" facs="tcp:59543:47"/> her Recreations, and honoured with a numerous Train of Nobility.</p>
                  <p>The Grandeur of this City chiefly conſiſts in the Properneſs and Valour of her Men; in the bravery of her Armour, the multitude of her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants: ſo that in the fatal Wars in King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Reign, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, on a Muſter, 20000 Horſe, and 60000 Foot, all armed Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. The Citizens of <hi>London</hi> are known and eſteemed beyond all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons, whereſoever they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for their gentile Deportment, their good Apparel, their Table, and Diſcourſe.</p>
               </q>
               <p>So that we ſee from hence, that in the Reign of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> who was <hi>Nephew</hi> to King <hi>William the Firſt,</hi> (from whoſe Death, to King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Reign, there were not fifty Years) the <hi>City of London</hi> was very great and powerful; but had the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Citizens</hi> been all deſtroyed, and had all their <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> been (as is ſo poſitively affirmed) <hi>taken away</hi> from them by <hi>William the Firſt,</hi> it had been impoſſible, in ſo ſhort a Time, for them to have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="lxxx" facs="tcp:59543:48"/> again to that <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Renown</hi> through all this part of the World, as the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who was an <hi>Eye-Witneſs</hi> of it, ſo credibly aſſures us.</p>
               <p>My next deſign is to ſhew you, That from the <hi>General Direction</hi> of the <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Charters</hi> in King <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am the Firſt</hi> his Time, it is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable, that <hi>William,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Conqueror,</hi> did not <hi>divide</hi> all the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>England</hi> amongſt his <hi>Norman</hi> followers to hold of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dugdal. <hi>Hiſt. of St.</hi> Pauls, <hi>in the Appendix. fol. 196.</hi>
                  </note>1. W. Cyng gret Osmund bisceoþ of Hearbyrig &amp; Rob. of Eli. &amp; Piedres of Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniis &amp; ealle his scirgerevan &amp; his holdan Frencisce, &amp; Englisce, frendlisce..</p>
               <p>Id eſt;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>W. Rex Saluto Oſmundum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nota, <hi>Here are Engliſh She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, and other Engliſh Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as well as French.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Saresburienſem, &amp; Robertum de Ely, &amp; Petrum de Valoniis, omneſque praefectos ſuos et fideles, Frances et</hi> Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, <hi>amicè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="lxxxi" facs="tcp:59543:48"/>2. Willem <note place="margin">Chart. Antiq. 1.</note> Cyng gret mines b'pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; mind Eorles &amp; ealle mind Degnes freneisse &amp; Englisce.</p>
               <p>Willem gret mines Biſhops, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Here were Engl. Thains.</hi> Thani Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione viri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, interdum liberae Conditionis Homines, interdum Magiſtratus, atque ſaepenumero Miniſtri notantur. Gloſſ. in fin. <hi>Lambard,</hi> de priſ. Angl. leg. <hi>fol. 223. Col.</hi> 1. tic. Thanus.</note> mind Eorles, and ealle mind Thegnes, Freneiſſe and <hi>Engliſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>W. Rex Anglorum O. Epiſcopo</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Monaſt. Angl. <hi>Vol. 1. fo. 185.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sarisburienſi et L. Abbati Glaſtonienſi et A Vicecomiti omnibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Baronibus Francigenis et</hi> Anglis <hi>de Sumerſeta, et de Wiltunſcire, Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Willielmus Rex Angliae Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. <hi>fol.</hi> 397. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>T. Eboraci, et Juſticiariis et Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitibus, et omnibus Baronibus &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delibus ſuis, Francis et</hi> Anglis <hi>de Ebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caciſtire, et de Carleoli, Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Willielmus Rex Anglorum Walte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. <hi>fol. 29.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vicecomiti, et omnibus Baronibus ſuis Franeigenis, et</hi> Anglis <hi>de Comitatu de Gloceſtre, Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="lxxxii" facs="tcp:59543:49"/>6. <hi>Willielmus Dei Gratia Rex Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Fidelibus ſuis Francigenis et</hi> Anglis, <hi>Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Willielmus Rex Anglorum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>de Suthſexa et Vicecomiti, et caeteris Baronibus ſuis Francigenis et</hi> Anglis, <hi>Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Willielmus Rex Angliae, G. Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com</hi>'<note place="margin">Id. <hi>Vol. 2. fo. 845.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>et Baronibus ſuis</hi> de Caerleil, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Willielmus Rex Angliae Thomae</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. <hi>fol. 845.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Archiepiſcopo et Bertramo de Verdun, et Baronibus ſuis, Francis et</hi> Anglis <hi>de Everwicſcire, Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Henricus Rex Angliae Richardo</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cart. Antiq. N</note> 
                  <hi>Epiſcopo London, et Vic' et Praepoſito, et omnibus Baronibus et Fidelibus ſuis, Francis et</hi> Anglis, <hi>de London et Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex, Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Henricus Rex Angliae Vic' et</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. Ibid.</note> Baronibus London.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Henricus Dei Gratia Rex Angliae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dugdal. <hi>Hiſt. of St.</hi> Pauls, <hi>in the Appendix. fol. 197.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Archiepiſcopis et Epiſcopis, et Comitibus
<pb n="lxxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:49"/> Angliae; et Hugoni de Boclande, et om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Baronibus &amp; ſidelibus ſuis, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis et</hi> Anglis, <hi>de</hi> Lundonia, <hi>et de</hi> Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſexa, <hi>et de tota</hi> Anglia, <hi>Salutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Charters,</hi> Sir, (though many more of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might eaſily be given) I think, with ſubmiſſion, my <hi>Argument</hi> is firmly maintained; and the <hi>plain Engliſh</hi> of them all is, no more than this, That in <hi>William the firſt's</hi> Time there were <hi>Engliſh Barons</hi> as well as <hi>French Barons,</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhire;</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Carliſle;</hi> in <hi>Glouceſterſhire</hi> and in <hi>Suſſex:</hi> and the <hi>direction</hi> of the <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> is equally given to them both, without any <hi>difference</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> mentioned, otherwiſe, than that the <hi>French</hi> Barons had the <hi>prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Charters:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>As is aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid Anonimus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor againſt Mr.</hi> Petyt, p. 151.</note> With what force of truth then can it be defended, That the <hi>Norman Nobility</hi> were at that time the <hi>only Nobility,</hi> I appeal to the World.</p>
               <pb n="lxxxii" facs="tcp:59543:50"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="lxxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:50"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="lxxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:51"/> But, I pray, now hear two Branches of his MAGNA CHARTA, or <hi>Great Charter,</hi> which he granted to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and they run thus;</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Volumus etiam ac firmiter praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud Cl. Lambard. LL. Will. prim. <hi>fol.</hi> 170. c. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; concedimus, ut omnes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri homines totius Monarchiae Regni noſtri praedicti, habeant &amp; teneant terras ſuas, &amp; poſſeſſiones ſuas, bene &amp; in pace liberè</hi> AB OMNI EXACTIONE INJUSTA, &amp; AB OMNI TALLAGIO; <hi>ita quod nihil ab eis exigatur, vel capiatur, niſi</hi> SERVITIUM SUUM LIBE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RUM, <hi>quod de Jure nobis facere debent, &amp; facere tenentur, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut</hi> STATUTUM <hi>eſt eis, &amp; illis à nobis datum et conceſſum</hi> JURE HAEREDITARIO <hi>in perpetuum,</hi> PER COMMUNE CONCILIUM TOTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>US REGNI NOSTRI <hi>praedicti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second Branch is;</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Hoc quoque praecipimus,</hi> UT OMNES<note place="margin">Id. <hi>c. 63.</hi>
                  </note> HABEANT ET TENEANT LEGES ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARDI REGIS <hi>in omnibus rebus, adau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis hiis quas conſtituimus</hi> AD UTILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATEM ANGLORUM.</p>
               <pb n="lxxxv" facs="tcp:59543:51"/>
               <p>Sir, I think by theſe two Branches, you may plainly ſee, King <hi>William</hi> when he came in, was ſo far from <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly taking</hi> away the <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſesſions</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſharing them among his <hi>Normans;</hi> that he doth, if poſſible, more ſtrongly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their <hi>Eſtates</hi> to them, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the good and <hi>ancient Laws</hi> of <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> which were their beſt ſecurity of all they enjoyed before his entrance; and not only ſo, but by freeing them from all <hi>unjuſt Taxes</hi> and <hi>Exactions,</hi> excepting only their <hi>free Service,</hi> which <hi>of right</hi> was owing to him, and which they were to do, as it was agreed on by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and granted by him to them by <hi>hereditary Right</hi> for ever, and that <hi>by the <hi>Common Council</hi> of the whole Kingdom;</hi> and this was done too <hi>wholly</hi> for the <hi>ſake</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall trouble you, Sir, with one more very memorable <hi>Record,</hi> as late as to the 26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. which ſhews, That from before the <hi>coming in</hi> of this <hi>Norman Conqueror,</hi> down to that
<pb n="lxxxvi" facs="tcp:59543:52"/> Time, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had a <hi>Property</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to them; and ſo then this MIGHTY MAN of VICTORY did not govern them as an <hi>entire</hi> and <hi>abſolute <hi>Conqueror,</hi>
                  </hi> what-ever our <hi>late Writers</hi> have been pleaſed to <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> to the World.</p>
               <p>The words of the <hi>Record</hi> are;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro Jacobo Archamgere.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">Communia de Term. Sanct. Mich. 35. fin. &amp; An. 36. inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pien. H. 3. Rot. pr. penes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem. dom. Theſ. Jus Anglorum ab Antiq. <hi>p.</hi> 112, 113. Serjantia tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Edwardi Confeſ.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex Baronibus; Mandamus vobis quod occaſione arrentationis Serjantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, aſſeſſae per</hi> Robertum Paſſelewe, <hi>non diſtringas</hi> Jacobum <hi>de</hi> Archamge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re <hi>per 2. Marc. &amp; dimid. de Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento quod de nobis tenet per Serjantiam in</hi> Archamgere, (<hi>in Comitatu</hi> Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, &amp;c.) <hi>per Chartam Beati Regis</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi <hi>Anteceſſoribus ipſius</hi> Jacobi <hi>ſuper hoc confectam, ſed ipſum</hi> Jacobum <hi>de praedictis 2. Marcis &amp; dimid' quietum eſſe faciatis in perpetuum; quia Chartam praefati beati</hi> Edwardi <hi>confirmavimus, &amp; ipſam volumus inviolabiliter obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Breve eſt in forulo Mareſcalli, &amp; Mandatum est Vicecomiti</hi> South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton
<pb n="lxxxvii" facs="tcp:59543:52"/> 
                  <hi>comparat. die Jovis, die 15. Jan. Anno Domini,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh of it is this:</p>
               <p>For <hi>Jacob Archamgere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The King to the Barons: We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, that by the occaſion of the Rent of Serjanties, aſſeſſed by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Paſſelewe,</hi> you ſhall not diſtrain <hi>Jacob</hi> of <hi>Archamgere</hi> by two Marks and an half, for the Tenement which he holds of us by Serjantie in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamgere,</hi> in the County of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and granted by the <hi>Charter</hi> of the Bleſſed King <hi>Edward,</hi> to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors of this <hi>Jacob;</hi> but he the ſaid <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall for ever be freed from the aforeſaid two Marks and an half; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have <hi>confirmed</hi> the <hi>Charter</hi> of the aforementioned <hi>St. Edward;</hi> and we will have it to be inviolably obſerved.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall make no Remarks upon this <hi>Charter,</hi> becauſe it is obvious to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intelligent Reader; the thing I drive at, is, to prove, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were <hi>not</hi> violently <hi>diſpoſſeſſed</hi> of their
<pb n="lxxxviii" facs="tcp:59543:53"/> 
                  <hi>Properties,</hi> which they <hi>quietly</hi> held and enjoyed in the Time of <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> but that they ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed them as before, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the vain pretences to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, I ſhall cloſe up this third Point, with a remarkable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage or two out of <hi>Ordericus Vitalis,</hi> a famous <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who lived and <hi>writ</hi> in the latter <hi>end</hi> of the Reign of <hi>H.</hi> 1. and <hi>beginning</hi> of K. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and for that reaſon muſt needs be admitted (next to a <hi>Teſtis Ocularis</hi>) for a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony beyond all exceptions.</p>
               <p>His words are,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Omnia diſponente Deo in ſpatio<note place="margin">Orderic. Vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Eccleſ Hiſt. lib. 3. <hi>fol. 503.</hi>
                     </note> trium menſium per Angliam pacata ſunt, cuncti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Praeſules Regni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres cum Willielmo concordiam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt, ac ut Diadema Regium ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meret, (ſicut Mos Anglici Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus exigit) oraverunt. Hoc ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moperè flagitabant Normanni, qui pro faſce Regali nanciſcendo ſuo Principi ſubierunt ingens diſcrimen maris &amp; Praelii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hoc etiam divino
<pb n="lxxxix" facs="tcp:59543:53"/> Nutu ſubacti optabant Indigenae Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, qui niſi coronato Regi ſervire hactenus erant ſoliti.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next Paragraph but one to this goes on thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Denique Anno ab incarnatione Domini MLXVII. Indictione V. in die Natalis Domini, Angli Lundoniae ad Ordinandum Regem convenerunt, &amp; Normannorum Turmae circa Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterium in armis &amp; equis (nè quid doli &amp; ſeditionis oriretur) praeſidio diſpoſitae fuerunt. Adelredus ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Archiepiſcopus in Baſilica Sancti Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri Apoſtolorum Principis, quae Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterium nuncupatur, ubi Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardus Rex venerabiliter humatus quieſcit, in praeſentia Praeſulum &amp; Abbatum Procerum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> totius Regni Albionis, Gulielmum Ducem Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannorum in Regem Anglorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecravit, &amp; Diadema Regium capiti ejus impoſuit.</p>
                  <p>Gulielmus Rex multa Lundoniae<note place="margin">Id. lib. IV. <hi>fol.</hi> 505, &amp; 506.</note> poſtquam coronatus eſt, prudentèr, juſtè, clementer<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diſpoſuit: quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ad ipſius Civitatis commoda vel dignitatem, alia quae genti profice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:59543:54"/> Univerſae: Normulla quibus conſuleretur Eccleſiis terrae. Jura quaecum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dictavit optimis rationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſanxit; Judicium Rectum nulla perſona nequicquam ab eo poſtulavit. Neminem, niſi quem non damnare iniquum foret, damnavit. Suis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Primatibus digna ſe &amp; gravitate praecepit, &amp; diligenter aequitatem ſuaſit; Eſſe jugiter in Oculis haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum aeternum Regem, cujus vicerint praeſidio. Nimium opprimi victos non opportere, victoribus profeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſtianâ pares, nè quos juſtè ſubegerint, injuriis ad rebellandum cogerent. Seditiones interdixit, cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, &amp; omnem rapinam fraenans, ut Populos armis, ita legibus Arma. Tributis &amp; cunctis rebus ad Regium fiſcum reddendis, modum, qui non gravaret, impoſuit, Latrociniis, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſionibus, Maleficiis, locum omnem intra ſuos terminos denegavit. Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; quaelibet itinera Negotiatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus patere, &amp; nullam injuriam fieri juſſit. Sic omnino proba ejus in regnando initia fuere, &amp; incrementa probitatum ad utilitatem Subditorum liquidò fulſere, que in bonis perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verantia laudabiliſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> finis evidentibus ſignis confirmavere.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="xli" facs="tcp:59543:54"/>
               <p>The ſence of which is,</p>
               <p>King <hi>William</hi> having ſworn <hi>invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> as I have already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you, and being crowned King, the whole <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> in three months time quietly ſubmitted to him; which the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> obſerves to be by <hi>Divine Providence:</hi> And they much relyed upon the <hi>force</hi> of that <hi>Solemn Oath</hi> he took; and great cauſe they had for their doing ſo; for,</p>
               <p>Remarkable is it, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Reign, he made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to keep it; and this the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> plainly proves: for ſo <hi>far</hi> was he from <hi>pretending</hi> to be a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> or from exerciſing <hi>abſolute Power</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> over the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that you ſee he denied to none right Judgment who required it of him; he <hi>condemned none</hi> but thoſe who deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it by the <hi>condemnation</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> he ſtrictly commanded his great Men, to whom he had <hi>given</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> of thoſe who had been <hi>hold</hi> in <hi>Arms againſt</hi> him, under King <hi>Harold,</hi>
                  <pb n="xcii" facs="tcp:59543:55"/> that they ſhould behave themſelves with <hi>all</hi> due <hi>moderation</hi> and <hi>temper;</hi> and he <hi>invited</hi> them to <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by his <hi>Example:</hi> He charged them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to have God before their Eyes, by whoſe Arms they had ſo far over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; That they ſhould, nay ought, not too much to oppreſs thoſe they had got the better of, who were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians with them, leſt thoſe whom they had juſtly ſubdued, ſhould by ſuch their Oppreſſions be forced to rebel again; he ſtrictly forbad them all Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, that they ſhould reſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from all Cruelties and Rapines; <hi>That as the People ſhould be kept in Peace by his Arms; ſo their Arms ſhould ſubmit to, and be governed by the Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor did he only give this admirable Advice, but he prudently governed himſelf, and ſet eaſy Boundaries to thoſe Services, Taxes, &amp; Aids, <hi>quod de jure</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud Lambar. LL. Wil. prim. <hi>fol. 170. c. 55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>facere debent,</hi> which were due to him by the Law; he abſolutely denied all Pardons and Grace to Robbers, and all diſturbers of the Publick Peace, and wicked Perſons: He commanded all the Roads to be free and open for
<pb n="xciii" facs="tcp:59543:55"/> Travellers, and that no Injuries ſhould be done them; ſo that the <hi>beginning</hi> of his <hi>Reign</hi> was, as it were, <hi>a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Age;</hi> and his Clemency, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of Goodneſs, ſtill ſhone brighter to the happineſs of his Subjects, which was confirmed towards the Loyal and Dutiful, by his ſteady and commendable perſeverance.</p>
               <p>Where, in all this, is there any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to <hi>abſolute Conqueſt</hi> and deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Dominion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now to conclude; I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an Evidence, that is <hi>omni excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione major;</hi> it is <hi>Gulielmus Pictaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> who, (as <hi>Ordericus Vitalis in fine litri tertii</hi> writes) was, <hi>Regis Gulielmi Capellanus,</hi> and writ the Acts of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Firſt. And he categorically ſays it, That <hi>Nulli tamen Gallo datum eſt quod Anglo cuiquam injuſtè fuerit ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum;</hi> that is, according to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given in <hi>Sharborn</hi>'s caſe, That thoſe who had kept themſelves uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and had neither, <hi>conſilio vel auxilio,</hi> aſſiſted <hi>Harold</hi> againſt <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> had the full and free <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Saxon Laws,</hi> and had <hi>not</hi> their
<pb n="xliv" facs="tcp:59543:56"/> 
                  <hi>Eſtates</hi> unjuſtly <hi>taken</hi> from any of them, and given to his <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Normans. <hi>Gulielm. Pictavenſ. in Geſta Gulielm. Ducis Norman. &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Anglorum. fol.</hi>
                  </hi> 208.</p>
               <p>But I will leave this, Sir, and now come to your fourth and laſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <pb n="xlv" facs="tcp:59543:56"/>
               <head>The Fourth Queſtion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>IV. Whether it be not a <hi>Grand</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Anonim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Author a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Mr. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyt.</hi> p. 37.</note> 
                     <hi>Error</hi> to affirm, That there were <hi>no Engliſh Men</hi> in the <hi>Common Council</hi> of the <hi>whole Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Government,</hi> ſaith the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Biſhops Right in judging in Capital Cauſes in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</hi> p. 2.</note> and moſt judicious Mr. <hi>Hunt, by a King and Eſtates of Parliament, is as ancient as any thing can be remembred of the Nation. The attempt of altering it in all Ages accounted Treaſon, and the puniſhment thereof reſerved to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by</hi> 25. Ed. 3. <hi>The conſervancy of the Government being not ſafely to be ledged any where, but with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf. Offences of this Kind not pardonable by the King, becauſe it is not in his Power to change it. This is Our Government, and thus it is eſtabliſhed, and for Ages, and immemorial Time hath thus continued; a long ſucceſſion of Kings have recognized it to be ſuch.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="xcvi" facs="tcp:59543:57"/>
               <p>This too perhaps will be granted, Sir, in ſome ſence, that for a long Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Tract of Time, the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath been ſo; but the main <hi>pinch</hi> and <hi>ſtreſs</hi> of your <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as I apprehend it, is this, Whether after <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> had ſetled himſelf as well as he could on the <hi>Engliſh Throne,</hi> he did admit any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to fit in the <hi>Great Council</hi> of the Nation, and to Adviſe and Conſult, <hi>de arduis &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgentibus nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis Regni?</hi> And I hope this I ſhall make plain and evident to you, That the <hi>Grand Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> was in ſubſtance the ſame that it was <hi>before</hi> the <hi>coming in</hi> of this <hi>Conqueror,</hi> and that there were <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> Members of it in the Time of the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis not to be denied, but that the <hi>ſame Courts,</hi> that were in the <hi>Saxon Time</hi> for adminiſtration of Juſtice, continued after <hi>William the firſt</hi> was made King, and the Footſteps of them remain yet to this day: I ſhall mention a few, and ſo come to the main Point in Argument.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="xcvii" facs="tcp:59543:57"/>1. As it was their Wiſdom to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. County Courts.</hi> LL. Hen. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6 apud Lambard <hi>fol. 180.</hi>
                  </note> the Ancient Land-marks; ſo was it likewiſe both their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and their Care to continue their due Privileges and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts. Their County Courts were ſtill kept up, and every County had its Court, and every Court its wonted Juriſdiction: no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint<note place="margin">LL. Guil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 42 <hi>fol. 168.</hi>
                  </note> muſt be to the King's Court, if Right might be done in the County; no Diſtreſs muſt be taken but by Warrant from the County, and that muſt be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter complaint thrice made. The<note place="margin">LL. Guil. <hi>c. 64.</hi>
                  </note> County Court muſt be called, as our Anceſtors have appointed: ſuch as will not come as they ought, ſhall be firſt ſummoned, and in caſe of default, diſtrained; at the fourth default, <hi>Reddatur de rebus hujus hominis quod calump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatum eſt, quod dicitur</hi> Ceargel, <hi>&amp; inſuper Regis forisfactura;</hi> that is, The Complainant ſhall be ſatisfied out of the Diſtreſſes ſo taken, and the King alſo for his Fine. Theſe are the <hi>expreſs Laws</hi> of the <hi>Conqueror</hi>'s own
<pb n="xcviii" facs="tcp:59543:58"/> eſtabliſhment. The <hi>laſt</hi> of which alſo was confirmed by another expreſs <hi>Law,</hi> ſaving that he would <hi>allow</hi> but of <hi>two Summons</hi> and <hi>two Diſtreſſes</hi> before <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall give you a memorable caſe to prove the continuance of this Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Odo,</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi>'s half Brother,<note place="margin">Selden'<hi>s Titles of Honour, 2d Part</hi> c. 5 <hi>f. 581 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Eadmer. <hi>Hiſ. Nov. l.</hi> 1. p. 9 &amp; videſis notas ad eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. <hi>p.</hi> 197. de placito a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Pinende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem inter Lanſrancum Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum &amp; Odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Bajocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum.</note> was by him made Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> and therewith had the Gift of a large Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory in <hi>Kent,</hi> and taking advantage of the King's diſpleaſure at <hi>Stigand,</hi> the Arch-biſhop, of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf by Diſſeiſin of divers Lands and Tenements belonging to that See. <hi>Lanfrank,</hi> the ſucceeding Arch-biſhop being informed hereof, petitioned to the King that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> might be done him <hi>ſecundum Legem Terrae,</hi> and the King ſends forth a Writ to ſummon a <hi>County Court:</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate laſted three days before the <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> in the preſence of many <hi>chief Men, Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> and others <hi>skilful in the Laws;</hi> and the <hi>Iudgment</hi> paſſed for
<pb n="xcix" facs="tcp:59543:58"/> the Arch-biſhop <hi>Lanfrank,</hi> upon the <hi>Votes</hi> of the <hi>Freemen.</hi> This <hi>County Court</hi> was holden by <hi>ſpecial Summons,</hi> and not by <hi>adjournment,</hi> as was allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the <hi>Saxon Law</hi> upon ſpecial occaſions: And this <hi>Suit</hi> was <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> begun, and had its <hi>final deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> in the <hi>County Court.</hi> And the <hi>County Courts,</hi> in thoſe days, were of ſo great eſteem, that <hi>two</hi> of the <hi>greateſt Peers</hi> of the Realm, one a <hi>Norman,</hi> the other an <hi>Italian,</hi> did <hi>caſt a Title</hi> in fifteen Mannors, two Lordſhips, with many Liberties upon the <hi>Votes</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Freeholders</hi> in a <hi>County Court;</hi> and that the <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> was <hi>allowed</hi> and <hi>commended</hi> by the <hi>King,</hi> and ſubmitted to by all. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Hundred Courts</hi> were ſtill<note place="margin">2. Hundred Courts.</note> continued, and they were of <hi>two ſorts.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> whereof was holden <hi>twice</hi> a Year, and all the <hi>Free-holders</hi> within the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,</hi> were bound to appear for the <hi>ſervice</hi> of their <hi>Fees;</hi> and was the <hi>Sheriff's Court,</hi> and ſuch <hi>appearances</hi> were called the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs Turnes,</hi> where it belonged
<pb n="c" facs="tcp:59543:59"/> to <hi>Sheriffs</hi> to enquire of all <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Offences,</hi> and of all their <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> done within thoſe <hi>Hundreds.</hi> The <hi>other</hi> was the more <hi>ordinary Court,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Hundred,</hi> to whom alſo belonged the <hi>Fines</hi> in caſes there concerned. This <hi>Court</hi> was to be held <hi>once</hi> in <hi>each</hi> Month; and no ſuit to be begun in the <hi>King's Court,</hi> that regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ought to begin in the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</hi> No <hi>Diſtringas</hi> to iſſue forth till <hi>three demands</hi> made in the <hi>Hundred.</hi> And <hi>three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes</hi> then to iſſue forth; and if upon the <hi>fourth</hi> the Party <hi>appear</hi> not, <hi>execution</hi> then to be by <hi>Sale</hi> of the <hi>Diſtreſs,</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainant</hi> to receive <hi>ſatisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And ſo likewiſe were the <hi>Court Barons,</hi> &amp;c. continued, and the <hi>Lords</hi> held <hi>Pleas</hi> either in their <hi>own Perſons,</hi> or by their <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But not to forget, Sir, your Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I ſhall now ſhew you what the <hi>Soveraign Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi>
                  <pb n="cl" facs="tcp:59543:59"/> was, and <hi>whom</hi> it <hi>conſiſted</hi> of in the <hi>Saxon Times;</hi> and for this I think it will be <hi>needleſs</hi> to give you any more than <hi>one Inſtance</hi> (which, as by the way, it does impreguably aſſert, That the <hi>Commons of England</hi> were an <hi>Eſſential</hi> and <hi>Conſtituent Part</hi> of the <hi>Saxon General Councils;</hi> ſo doth it, I think, <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>clearly</hi> refute and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> p. 20. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n the Margin.</hi>
                  </note> baffle that <hi>novel Erroneous Notion, viz.</hi> That there are <hi>no Commons</hi> to be found in the <hi>Saxon great Councils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem. <hi>p. 13. 14.</hi>
                  </note> nor any thing that tends towards the proof of the <hi>Commons</hi> of thoſe Times to have had <hi>any ſhare</hi> in making <hi>Laws</hi> in thoſe <hi>Councils.</hi>) The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Inſtance, is the <hi>mighty Law</hi> of <hi>Tythes,</hi> which was made and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Rege, Baronibus, &amp; Populo.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſcis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Legi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>39 <hi>Spelm.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tom. 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>By the King, his Barons, and his People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>William the Firſt,</hi> in that little time of Reſt he had from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Wars with the <hi>French</hi> King, and his <hi>Neighbouring Princes</hi> to <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> did apply both it and himſelf in
<pb n="c" facs="tcp:59543:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="cl" facs="tcp:59543:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="cii" facs="tcp:59543:61"/> the <hi>ſetling</hi> of <hi>Laws</hi> here, which was done, not <hi>ex plenitudine Regiae Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatis;</hi> no, nor by the <hi>Norman Barons</hi> co-operating with that Power; but by the <hi>joint Advice,</hi> and <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Conſent</hi> of the <hi>Grand Council</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>wiſe Men</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England:</hi> To prove which, I ſhall produce the Teſtimony of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers,</hi> whom no Man of <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical</hi> underſtanding can modeſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach of Partiality, Faction, or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, in the Caſe in Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt ſhall be taken out of the<note place="margin">Lambard. <hi>fol. 158.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chronicle</hi> of <hi>Litchfield,</hi> which tells us, That <hi>this William,</hi> in the fourth Year of his Reign at <hi>London, <hi>Conſilio Baronum ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  </hi> by the Advice of his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, cauſed a General Meeting, or Aſſembly, to be ſummoned, <hi>Per univerſos Angliae Comitatus, omnes Nobiles, Sapientes, &amp; ſuâ Lege eruditos, ut eorum Leges &amp; conſuetudines audiret; i. e.</hi> 
                  <q>of all the Nobility, wiſe Men, and ſuch as were skilled in the Laws, through all the Counties of <hi>England,</hi> to hear what their
<pb n="ciii" facs="tcp:59543:61"/> Laws and Cuſtoms were.</q> And after this was done, at the <hi>requeſt</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Community,</hi> he did <hi>conſent</hi> that they ſhould be <hi>confirmed;</hi> and ſo they were <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified</hi> and <hi>kept</hi> throughout all his Kingdom. The words are, <hi>Ad preces Communitatis Anglorum, ex illo die Magna Authoritate vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratae, &amp; per univerſum Regnum corroboratae &amp; conſervatae ſunt Leges Sancti Regis Edwardi, prae caeteris Regni Legibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this Teſtimony, I think it will plainly appear;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Barones ſui</hi> here of <hi>William,</hi> cannot <hi>abſolutely</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and only ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify his <hi>Norman</hi> Barons, upon thoſe <hi>Authorities</hi> and Reaſons, I have already offered, to prove, That there were equally <hi>Barones <hi>Francigeni &amp; Angli noſtri,</hi>
                  </hi> in his Time, (as you may ſee in my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument under the third Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.)</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="civ" facs="tcp:59543:62"/>2. That the King having, by the Counſel of theſe his Barons, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned all the Nobility, wiſe Men, and thoſe that were <hi>skilled</hi> in the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> throughout <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Counties</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> he then and there <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>St. Edward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And to prove that this <hi>general Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Nobility, wiſe Men,</hi> and <hi>able Lawyers,</hi> were a PARLIAMENT, I ſhall now give you the Judgment of Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> in his own words,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en</hi>'s Tit. of Hon. <hi>f. 580.</hi>
                  </note> which are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>William the firſt,</hi> in the <hi>fourth</hi> Year of his Reign, or MLXX. (which was the Year wherein he <hi>firſt</hi> brought the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Abbots</hi> under the <hi>Tenure</hi> of <hi>Barony) Conſilio Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſuorum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hoveden</hi> 
                  <note n="p" place="margin">In Hen. 2. <hi>p.</hi> 343. E. Lond.</note> out of a Collection of Laws, written by <hi>Glanvill) Fecit ſummoniri per uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſos Conſulatus Angliae, <hi>Anglos</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, &amp; Sapientes, &amp; ſua Lege eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos, ut eorum jura &amp; Conſuetudines
<pb n="cv" facs="tcp:59543:62"/> ab ipſis audiret.</hi> And twelve were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned out of every County, who ſhewed what the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the Kingdom were, which being written by the hands of <hi>Aldred</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Hugo,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> were, with the <hi>Aſſent</hi> of the ſame <hi>Barons,</hi> for the moſt part, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> in that Aſſembly, which was a <hi>Parliament</hi> of that Time.</q>
               <p>And a little lower, he ſaith, <q>This might be the ſame <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein the Controverſy between <hi>Thomas</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>York</hi> (he was conſecrated after the death of <hi>Aldred,</hi> the ſame Year; and to the ſame Year this Controverſy is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted) and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſtan</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> touching certain Poſſeſſions, was determined.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So that from hence, 'tis eaſy to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; That</p>
               <p n="1">1. There were <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> in this <hi>Council,</hi> by the words ANGLOS NOBILES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="cvi" facs="tcp:59543:63"/>2. Beſides the <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>St. Edward</hi> here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, it may reaſonably be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, That the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>bringing the Biſhops and Abbots under the Tenure of Barony,</hi> was <hi>firſt</hi> made in this <hi>Parliament.</hi> And that</p>
               <p n="3">3. Likewiſe, the <hi>great Caſe</hi> between the Arch-biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and this ſame Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was here <hi>judicially</hi> determined. And,</p>
               <p n="4">4. If there were no <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> in this <hi>great Council,</hi> how then came it to paſs that the Biſhop of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>London</hi> were <hi>there,</hi> who certainly were <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Saxon Times?</hi> And it may alſo ſeem not improbable, that there was <hi>then</hi> an <hi>univerſal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> among them, that theſe two Biſhops ſhould be intruſted to write down for them the <hi>Engliſh Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And there is <hi>one great Thing</hi> more, to cloſe withal, which is,
<pb n="cvii" facs="tcp:59543:63"/> That at <hi>this Parliament,</hi> when the <hi>Saxon Laws</hi> were <hi>confirmed,</hi> there was a <hi>particular Law</hi> paſt<note place="margin">Carta Regis Wil. ielm. apud Lambard. <hi>c. 54. fol. 170.</hi>
                  </note> in <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>Normans, <hi>qui ante adventum Guilielmi Cives fuerant Anglicani,</hi>
                  </hi> that they ſhould be <hi>participes Conſuetudinum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum, quod ipſi dicunt <hi>Anhlote</hi> &amp; <hi>Anſcote,</hi> &amp; perſolvant ſecundum Legem Anglorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meaning of the words <hi>Anhlote</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> H. Spelm. Gloſſ. verbo. Anhlote. <hi>f. 31.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Anſcote,</hi> as Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, is <hi>vulgò <hi>Scot &amp; Lot;</hi>
                  </hi> that is, That every ſuch <hi>French Man</hi> ſhould not be charged with <hi>double Taxes</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> as a <hi>Foreigner,</hi> but that he ſhould pay his <hi>eaſy ſhare</hi> and proportion as any natural <hi>Engliſh Man.</hi> But then,</p>
               <p n="2">II. It was in ſuch a <hi>grand Aſſembly</hi> of wiſe Men of the Kingdom, where <hi>Lanfranc</hi> was elected to the See of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> for it was by the <hi>Aſſent</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Prelats,</hi> and of the <hi>whole People;</hi> that is to ſay, by the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> This likewiſe was about the <hi>fourth
<pb n="cviii" facs="tcp:59543:64"/> Year of the <hi>Conqueror;</hi>
                  </hi> And an Ancient <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> writes thus of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gervaſ. Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernenſ.</hi> Act. Pont. Cant. <hi>fol. 1653, l. 5.</hi>
                  </note> his Election: <hi>Eligentibus eum Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioribus ejuſdem Eccleſiae cum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis ac Principibus, <hi>Clero</hi> &amp; <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo</hi> Angliae, in Curia Regis in Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umptione Sanctae Mariae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But another Contemporary Writer gives it you in theſe words;<note place="margin">Relat. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielm. prim. ad finem tract. de Gavelkind à Syla Taylor. <hi>p. 194.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex mittens propter illum in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manniam, fecit eum venire in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliam, ei<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Conſenſu</hi> &amp; <hi>Auxilio</hi> omnium <hi>Baronum</hi> ſuorum, omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Epiſcoporum</hi> &amp; <hi>Abbatum, totiuſque Populi</hi> Angliae commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ei Dorobernenſem Eccleſiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. There was another <hi>General</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex Cartulario Coenobii Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterienſis in Biblioth. <hi>Cotton.</hi> ſub effigie Fauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. A. 3. <hi>Dugdal.</hi> Orig. Juridic. <hi>ſol. 16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Council</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> held at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the <hi>fourteenth</hi> Year of this King, where, by his <hi>Charter,</hi> he confirmed the <hi>Liberties</hi> of that Church, after he had ſubſcribed his own Name, with the Sign of the Croſs; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many of the great Clergy, and Temporal Nobility; and inſtead of <hi>cum multis aliis,</hi> ſays,
<pb n="cix" facs="tcp:59543:64"/> 
                  <hi>multis praeterea illuſtriſſimis Viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum perſonis, &amp; Regni Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus diverſi ordinis omiſſis, qui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militèr huic confirmationi piiſſimo affectu Teſtes &amp; Fautores fuerunt. Hii autem illo Tempore à Regia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Provincia, <hi>i. e.</hi> Comitatus. <hi>Seld.</hi> Tit. Hon: <hi>fol. 273. Spelm.</hi> Gloſſ. Tit. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincia. <hi>f. 471.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>diverſis Provinciis <hi>&amp;</hi> Vrbibus, <hi>ad</hi> Vniverſalem Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodum <hi>pro cauſis cujuſlibet Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anae Eccleſiae audiendis &amp; tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, ad praeſcriptam</hi> Celeberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Synodus magna nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patur. Somne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri Gloſſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Synodum <hi>quod Weſtmona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium dicitur, Convocati,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. In the Margin of the Book, there is writ this Remarque, <hi>Nota hic hos omnes convocari à Rege ſuâ aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ad cauſas Religionis tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, tàm Nobiles de Clero, quàm Principes Regni, cum aliis inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris gradus, Convocatio quorum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur eſſe Parliamentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. I think, by the <hi>general direction</hi> of the <hi>Writs</hi> of this King, as alſo by that of his <hi>Charters,</hi> (ſome of which I have given you in my <hi>Argument</hi> to your <hi>third</hi> Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and therefore ſhall refer you back to them) it is plainly demonſtrable, that <hi>William</hi> had
<pb n="cx" facs="tcp:59543:65"/> as well <hi>Engliſh <hi>Barons</hi>
                  </hi> as <hi>French</hi> Barons; and that <hi>his</hi> Barons were always a <hi>part</hi> of his <hi>great Council,</hi> will hardly, I ſuppoſe, be denied by any. And that <hi>one Law</hi> of his, which may be called the <hi>Firſt</hi> MAGNA CHARTA in the <hi>Norman</hi> Times, by which the King reſerved to himſelf <hi>from the Free Men of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> nothing but their free Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices due to him according to Law; in the concluſion ſaith, That <hi>they,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">LL. Guilielm. c. 55.</note> ſhall <hi>hold</hi> and enjoy their <hi>Eſtates</hi> well, and in peace, free from all unjuſt Exactions and Tallage; and this <hi>ratified</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> by the <hi>Common Council</hi> of the <hi>whole Kingdom,</hi> which cannot be reſtrained to the <hi>Norman Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> only. So that herein is aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Free-men, and of the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Body</hi> of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Theſe, I think, are uncontroverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proofs and Evidences.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="cxi" facs="tcp:59543:65"/>1. That there were <hi>General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> or <hi>Parliaments,</hi> in this <hi>firſt William</hi>'s Time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That in theſe <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Barons as well as the <hi>French</hi> Barons were preſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And laſtly, That there likewiſe was, as an <hi>eſſential part</hi> thereof,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Communitas Anglorum,</hi> the Community of Engliſh-men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides the Biſhops and Nobility, there were the <hi>Clerus &amp; Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the Inferior Clergy and People of <hi>England.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not only the Great Clergy, and the Temporal Nobility, but the <hi>Principes diverſi Ordinis, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>già poteſtate diverſis Provinciis &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbibus ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalem Synodum Convocati,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> The Chief and Principal Men of ſeveral Ranks and Degrees in Condition, were ſummoned by <hi>virtue</hi> of the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> out of their ſeveral
<pb n="cxii" facs="tcp:59543:66"/> 
                  <hi>reſpective Counties, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Burroughs,</hi> to this <hi>General Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> or <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, Sir, if this be ſo, I doubt not but that both your ſelf, and all judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and unbiaſſed Perſons, (who have not reſolved to eſpouſe a Party, and who will not ſuffer themſelves to be drawn aſide by any novel unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable Opinions, but will fairly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their Judgments to clear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous Truth, when once it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appears) I ſay, both you and they will certainly reſt ſatisfied in theſe great and powerful Authorities, which I have here preſented to publick view, and ſerious conſideration: and I think theſe have ſufficiently made out and proved, That</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>William the firſt,</hi> vulgarly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> did <hi>not</hi> get the <hi>Imperial Crown of England</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> nor made an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Conqueſt</hi> of the Nation at his <hi>firſt entrance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor that he <hi>aboliſhed</hi> all the <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> or changed the
<pb n="cxiii" facs="tcp:59543:66"/> 
                  <hi>whole</hi> Frame and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Saxon Government.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had ſtill <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> continued to them; and that it was a <hi>great miſtake</hi> in any to affirm, That the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Normans</hi> divided and <hi>ſhared</hi> them all among them. As likewiſe,</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the fourth place, It has been a grand Error to aſcertain, That there were no <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> in the <hi>Common Council</hi> of the whole Kingdom, in the Reign of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Sir, as a corroborating Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, to explain and enforce what I already have ſaid, I ſhall conclude my Diſcourſe at preſent with a very <hi>memorable</hi> and <hi>ſtudied Speech</hi> of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of great Learning and Abilities in his Time, collected out of a large <hi>Original Manuſcript</hi> (which I have ſeen) of Sir <hi>Roger Owen,</hi> a very <hi>great Antiquary,</hi> that lived in the Time of <hi>King James;</hi> and one, who, as appears by that Book, was a Man not
<pb n="cxiv" facs="tcp:59543:67"/> only of wonderful Knowledg, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Obſervation in the Records and Hiſtories of his own Nation, but alſo in thoſe of Foreign Countries.</p>
               <p>This was a Speech of the <hi>then</hi> Lord <hi>Whitlock,</hi> in <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1650. upon the <hi>Houſe's</hi> long and ſmart Debate touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Act for putting all the Books of</hi> Law, <hi>and the Proceſs and Proceedings in Courts of Juſtice into the <hi>Engliſh Tongue:</hi>
                  </hi> In which <hi>Debate</hi> ſome ſpake in <hi>derogation</hi> and <hi>diſhonour</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſome vindication whereof, and for ſatisfying ſome Miſtakes, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Opinion in the Houſe to this effect.</p>
               <p>It is now <hi>newly printed,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s MEMORIALS OF THE ENGLISH AFFAIRS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is here truly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="cxv" facs="tcp:59543:67"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Mr. Speaker;</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>THe Queſtion upon which your preſent Debate ariſeth, is of no ſmall moment, nor is it eaſily or ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to be determined; for it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends no leſs than a <hi>total Alteration</hi> of the <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of our <hi>Law,</hi> which have been eſtabliſhed and continued for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years.</p>
                           <p>I ſhould not have troubled you with any of my weak Diſcourſe, but that I apprehend ſome Miſtakes and <hi>diſhonour</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> if paſſed by without any Anſwer, may be of ill conſequence; and having attended to hear them anſwered by others, who are not pleaſed to do it;</p>
                           <p>I held my ſelf the more engaged, in the <hi>duty</hi> of my <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> to offer to your Judgment (to which I ſhall always ſubmit) what I have met with, and do ſuppoſe not to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, for the rectifying of ſome Miſtakes which are amongſt us.</p>
                           <pb n="cxvi" facs="tcp:59543:68"/>
                           <p>A worthy Gentleman was pleaſed to affirm, with much confidence, (as he brought it in upon this Debate) That the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced</hi> by <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> as (among other Arguments, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted) might appear by their being <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>French Tongue.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In his firſt Aſſertion, that our <hi>Laws</hi> were <hi>introduced</hi> by <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> out of <hi>France,</hi> I ſhall acknowledg, that he hath ſeveral both <hi>Forreign</hi> and <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, whom he may follow therein; The <hi>Forreign</hi> Authors are, <hi>Jovius, Aemilius, Bodine, Hottoman, Dyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus, Volateran, Berault, Berkley, Choppinus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſpargenſis, Malines,</hi> and <hi>Polidore,</hi> who affirm this erròneous piece of Doctrine; but the leſs to be regarded from them, becauſe they were <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to our <hi>Laws,</hi> and took up upon <hi>truſt</hi> what they <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> in this Point.</p>
                           <p>Of our <hi>own Country-men,</hi> they have <hi>Paris, Malmesbury, Matthew Weſtminſter, Fox, Coſins, Twyne, Heyward, Milles, Fulbeck, Cowell,
<pb n="cxvii" facs="tcp:59543:68"/> Ridley, Brown, Speed, Martyr,</hi> and ſome others.</p>
                           <p>All of them affirm, That the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>introduced by Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam the Conqueror:</hi> But their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are refuted by Sir <hi>Roger Owen</hi> in his <hi>Manuſcript;</hi> who ſaith, That <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Wendover,</hi> and <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> were the <hi>firſt Monks</hi> that <hi>hatched</hi> theſe <hi>addle Eggs.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you, That the <hi>Original</hi> of our <hi>Laws</hi> is <hi>not</hi> from the <hi>French;</hi> that they were <hi>not introduced</hi> by <hi>William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> out of <hi>Normandy:</hi> And I ſhall humbly offer to you my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to ſome of their <hi>Arguments,</hi> who are of a contrary opinion.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Polydore,</hi> Hiſt. Angl. <hi>l.</hi> 9. affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, That <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> firſt appointed <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> erected <hi>Tenures,</hi> brought in <hi>Trials</hi> by <hi>twelve</hi> Men, and ſeveral other <hi>Particulars</hi> of our <hi>Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>For <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> their name <hi>Scire Reeve,</hi> ſhews them to be of the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Inſtitution. And our Hiſtories mention the <hi>diviſion</hi> of <hi>Shires</hi> by
<pb n="cxviii" facs="tcp:59543:69"/> King <hi>Alphred;</hi> but in truth, it was much more ancient.</p>
                           <p>And it is apparent by our <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> ſome whereof are in the <hi>Huſtings</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and in the <hi>Tower,</hi> that the ſame things were in uſe here long before the Time of King <hi>Will.</hi> 1.</p>
                           <p>Sir <hi>Roger Owen</hi> ſhews at large, That <hi>Livery of Seiſin,</hi> Licenſes, or Fines for Alienation, Daughters to inherit, <hi>Trials by Iuries,</hi> Abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Utlaries, Coroners, diſpoſing of Lands by Will, Eſeheats, Gaols, Writs, Wrecks, Warranties, Catalla Fellonum, and many other parts of our <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Forms</hi> of our <hi>Parliaments</hi> themſelves, were here in being <hi>before</hi> the Time of <hi>Duke William.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Agreeing hereunto are many of our <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> and learned <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But it is objected, That in the <hi>Grand Cuſtumary</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> are almoſt <hi>all</hi> the ſame with ours of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>form</hi> of their <hi>Parliaments</hi> the ſame with ours.</p>
                           <pb n="cxix" facs="tcp:59543:69"/>
                           <p>That the <hi>Writer</hi> of the <hi>Preface</hi> to that <hi>Book,</hi> ſaith, It contains only the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> which were made by the Princes of <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> by the <hi>Councel</hi> of their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, Earls, Barons,</hi> and other <hi>Wiſe Men;</hi> which ſhews the <hi>forms</hi> of their <hi>Parliaments</hi> to be the <hi>ſame</hi> with <hi>ours,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> in that <hi>Book</hi> to be the <hi>proper Laws</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and ours to be the ſame; therefore they argue, that our <hi>Laws</hi> were <hi>introduced</hi> from thence by <hi>William the Conqueror.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>This will be fully anſwered, if that <hi>Grand Cuſtumary</hi> of <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> was compoſed in our King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. his Time, (as good Authors hold it was) then it cannot be, That our <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Parliaments</hi> could be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived</hi> from <hi>thence.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Theſe Learned Men ſay, That this <hi>Cuſtumary</hi> was a <hi>meer Tranſlation</hi> of our <hi>Law-Book, <hi>Glanvill;</hi>
                              </hi> as the Book of <hi>Regia Majeſtas</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> is; and the like of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxx" facs="tcp:59543:70"/>
                           <p>They farther add, That the firſt eſtabliſhing of the <hi>Cuſtumary</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> was in <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. his Time; and afterwards again, about the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. his Time.</p>
                           <p>If the <hi>Laws</hi> in the <hi>Cuſtumary</hi> were <hi>introduced</hi> there from <hi>England,</hi> it will then be granted, that the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>not introduced</hi> here by <hi>William the Conqueror:</hi> But I think it very clear, that their <hi>Laws</hi> were brought to them out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and then you will all agree to the concluſion.</p>
                           <p>Our King <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. conquered <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> from his Brother <hi>Robert,</hi> and was a <hi>Learned</hi> King, as his Name <hi>Beauclerke</hi> teſtifies; whom <hi>Ivo</hi> calls, an <hi>eſpecial Eſtabliſher of Iuſtice. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querius</hi>
                              </hi> relates, That this King <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Herewith do agree <hi>Gulielmus Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Armoricus, Rutclurius,</hi> and other <hi>French</hi> Writers; who mention alſo, That the <hi>Laws</hi> in the <hi>Cuſtumary</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> are the <hi>ſame</hi> with the <hi>Laws</hi> collected by our <hi>Engliſh King Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> who was <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxi" facs="tcp:59543:70"/>
                           <p>An additional Teſtimony hereof, is out of <hi>William de Alenſo Revile,</hi> who, in his <hi>Comment</hi> upon the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumary,</hi> ſaith, That all the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Normandy</hi> came from the <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> and <hi>Nation.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In the <hi>Cuſtumary,</hi> there is a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Nampes,</hi> or <hi>Diſtreſſes,</hi> and decreed, That one ſhould not bring his <hi>Action</hi> upon any <hi>Seiſure;</hi> but from the Time of the <hi>Coronation</hi> of King <hi>Richard;</hi> and this muſt be our King <hi>Richard the firſt,</hi> becauſe no King of <hi>France</hi> was in that Time of that Name; and the words <hi>Nampes</hi> and <hi>Withernams,</hi> were <hi>Saxon</hi> words, taken out of the <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> ſignifying a <hi>Pawn,</hi> or <hi>Diſtreſs,</hi> and in the ſame ſence are uſed in the <hi>Cuſtumary.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>That which puts it further out of ſcruple, is, That there are yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant the <hi>Manuſcripts</hi> themſelves of the <hi>Saxon Laws,</hi> made in the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Councils</hi> held by them here; which are in the Language and Character of thoſe Times; and contain in them many of thoſe things which are in the <hi>Norman Cuſtumary.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxli" facs="tcp:59543:71"/>
                           <p>It is no improbable Opinion, That there was a <hi>former Eſtabliſhment</hi> of our <hi>Laws</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> before the Time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. and that it was by <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> who (as all <hi>Writers</hi> of our <hi>Hiſtory</hi> agree) was a great <hi>Collector</hi> and <hi>Compiler</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>He <hi>lived</hi> a long time with his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Duke William</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> who was <hi>willing</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> in hopes to be <hi>appointed</hi> by him to be his <hi>Succeſſor;</hi> wherein the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Expectation did <hi>not fail</hi> him.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>Confeſſor</hi> having no <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and finding <hi>Normandy</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>ſetled Government,</hi> and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Laws,</hi> adviſed with his Kinſman, <hi>Duke William,</hi> to receive from him the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which he had <hi>collected,</hi> and to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> them in <hi>Normandy;</hi> which Duke <hi>William</hi> and his <hi>Lords</hi> readily accepted, for the <hi>good</hi> of their <hi>People;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>obliged</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Another proof hereof is, That <hi>ſuch Laws</hi> as the <hi>Normans</hi> had <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the Time of <hi>Duke William,</hi>
                              <pb n="cxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:71"/> were <hi>different</hi> from <hi>thoſe</hi> in the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumary,</hi> and from the <hi>Engliſh Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>As their <hi>Law,</hi> That the <hi>Husband</hi> ſhould be <hi>hanged</hi> if his <hi>Wife</hi> were a <hi>Thief,</hi> and he did <hi>not diſcover</hi> it: The <hi>meaner</hi> People were <hi>as Slaves,</hi> and the like: and the <hi>Trial</hi> of <hi>Theft</hi> by <hi>Ordeil,</hi> which then was <hi>not</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Wigornienſis</hi> reports, That the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> who came in with Queen <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Ethelred,</hi> were ſo hated of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for their <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and <hi>falſe Judgment,</hi> that in the Time of King <hi>Canutus,</hi> they were, for this cauſe, <hi>baniſhed;</hi> and it is the <hi>leſs</hi> probable, that <hi>they</hi> being ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt</hi> themſelves, ſhould <hi>introduce</hi> ſo <hi>juſt Laws</hi> as <hi>ours</hi> are.</p>
                           <p>Between the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> by <hi>Roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>o,</hi> and the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Duke William,</hi> there were not above 160 Years; that of <hi>Normandy</hi> was about <hi>Anno</hi> 912. that of <hi>England <hi>Anno</hi>
                              </hi> 1060.</p>
                           <p>It is not then <hi>conſonant</hi> to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that thoſe <hi>Normans, <hi>Pagans,</hi>
                              </hi> a rough <hi>Martial</hi> People, <hi>deſcended</hi>
                              <pb n="cxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:72"/> from ſo many <hi>Barbarous Nations,</hi> ſhould, in the time of 150 Years, eſtabliſh ſuch <hi>excellent Laws</hi> among <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſo <hi>different</hi> from the <hi>French Laws,</hi> among whom <hi>they</hi> were, and all parts in the World except <hi>England.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And <hi>ſuch Laws</hi> which were not only fit for their <hi>Dukedom</hi> and <hi>ſmall Territory,</hi> but fit alſo for <hi>this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> which in thoſe days was the <hi>ſecond</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> for <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Worth,</hi> by <hi>confeſſion of <hi>moſt</hi> Forreign Hiſtorians.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>If we will give <hi>credit</hi> to their <hi>own Authors,</hi> this Point will be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evinced by them. Theſe words are in the <hi>Proem</hi> of the <hi>Cuſtumary,</hi> which is entituled <hi>Deſcriptio Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manniae.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Hucuſque Normannicae CONS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUDINES LATOREM ſive Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem SANCT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M EDWARD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M <hi>Angliae</hi> Regem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>The ſame is witneſſed by <hi>Chronica Chronicorum,</hi> That <hi>St. Edward,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> gave the <hi>Laws</hi> to the <hi>Normans,</hi> when he was long har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured there.</p>
                           <pb n="cxxv" facs="tcp:59543:72"/>
                           <p>And that he made both the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Normandy,</hi> appears ſufficiently by the conformity of them, for which he cites ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, as of <hi>Appeals,</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of <hi>England, <hi>ad probandum aliquid per credentiam duodecim ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum vicinorum,</hi>
                              </hi> which, he ſaith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in <hi>Normandy</hi> to that day.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Polydore</hi> forgetting himſelf what he wrote in another place, ſaith, of King <hi>Henry the Seventh,</hi> that when a Doubt was made upon the Propoſal of <hi>Marriage</hi> of his <hi>Daughter</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> that thereby <hi>England</hi> might in time be <hi>ſubject</hi> unto <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The King anſwered, <hi>No;</hi> and that <hi>England,</hi> as the Greater, will draw it to <hi>Scotland</hi> being the leſs, and <hi>incorporate</hi> it to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as (ſaith the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi>) it did <hi>Normandy,</hi> though the <hi>owner</hi> thereof was <hi>Conqueror</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And Sir <hi>Roger Owen,</hi> in his <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript,</hi> affirms, That there is <hi>not any</hi> of our <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> that lived in the ſpace of 200 Years, immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="cxxvi" facs="tcp:59543:73"/> the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> which doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe our <hi>Laws</hi> to be <hi>taken away,</hi> and the <hi>Norman <hi>Cuſtom</hi> introduced</hi> by the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Some of them (and not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) mention the <hi>alteration</hi> of <hi>ſome part</hi> of them, and the <hi>bringing</hi> in <hi>ſome Norman <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi>
                              </hi> effectual for the <hi>keeping</hi> of the <hi>Peace.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>There is yet behind the <hi>great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> moſt inſiſted on, and often urged by the Gentlemen of another Opinion, which is the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>William,</hi> who is called the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror;</hi> from whence they conclude, That by his <hi>Conqueſt</hi> he <hi>changed</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that his <hi>Succeſſors</hi> reckon the <hi>beginning</hi> of their Reigns from his <hi>Conqueſt.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>To this is anſwered, That <hi>a poſſe ad eſſe non valet Argumentum:</hi> the <hi>Conquering</hi> of the Land is <hi>one</hi> thing, the <hi>introducing</hi> of <hi>new Laws</hi> is <hi>another</hi> thing; but there is direct proof to the contrary of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                           <pb n="cxxvii" facs="tcp:59543:73"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Duke William <hi>never</hi>
                              </hi> Sir-named himſelf the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> nor was ſo <hi>called</hi> in his <hi>life</hi>-time, as may appear by all the <hi>Letters Pattents</hi> and <hi>Deeds</hi> that he made, wherein he is called <hi>Guilielmus Rex, Dux,</hi> &amp;c. never <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtor;</hi> and our <hi>Ancient Hiſtorians</hi> give him the ſame Titles, and <hi>not</hi> that of <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In the Title of <hi>Nubrigenſis</hi>'s Book, he is Sirnamed <hi>William the Baſtard. Malmsbury</hi> calls him <hi>William the Firſt; Hoveden, William the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Adam de Monmoth</hi> ſaith, That 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. this word (<hi>Conqueſt</hi>) was found out to denote and diſtinguiſh the certain <hi>Edward;</hi> becauſe two of the ſame name were <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> to this King, and to the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> who claimed the Crown as Heir to <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> but (ſaith he) we call him the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> for that he <hi>overcame <hi>Harold.</hi>
                              </hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Duke William</hi> himſelf claimed to be King of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> and <hi>Adopted Heir</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> by his <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Harold</hi>'s renounce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>Title</hi> by <hi>Oath.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxviii" facs="tcp:59543:74"/>
                           <p>The Regiſter of St. <hi>Albans, Matth. Paris,</hi> and others, atteſt, That the <hi>Barons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> did homage to him as <hi>Succeſſor;</hi> and he relied on them in his Forreign Wars, and the Check given to him by the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Men, and the Forces gathered by the Abbot of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> brought him to engage to <hi>confirm</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſor;</hi> and as his <hi>Succeſſor</hi> by <hi>legal Right,</hi> they <hi>admitted</hi> him to be their King.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Volaterus</hi> writes, That he was made <hi>Heir</hi> to the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> and was <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> to him.</p>
                           <p>Another affirms, That <hi>Edward</hi> by his <hi>Will</hi> left <hi>England</hi> to him.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> and <hi>Fulgaſius,</hi> are to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                           <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>11th,</hi> ſent him a <hi>Banner,</hi> as Witneſs, that with a ſafe Conſcience he might expel <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold</hi> the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Crown</hi> was <hi>due</hi> to him by the <hi>Confeſſor's Will,</hi> and by <hi>Harold's Oath.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxix" facs="tcp:59543:74"/>
                           <p>Agreeable hereunto are <hi>Gemiticen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, Walſingham, Malmesbury, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington, Ingulphus, Paris, Pike, Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dover, Gaxton, Gisburn,</hi> and others.</p>
                           <p>The Antient Deeds of the Abby of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (which were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in my Cuſtody) do prove this.</p>
                           <p>King <hi>William,</hi> in his <hi>Charter</hi> to them, ſets ſorth his <hi>own Title</hi> to the Crown, thus, <hi>Beneficio Conceſſionis &amp; Cognati mei glorioſi Regis Edwardi.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In his ſecond <hi>Charter,</hi> dated <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 15. of his Reign, he ſaith, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>King Edward,</hi> who <hi>made</hi> me his <hi>Heir,</hi> and <hi>adopted</hi> me to Rule over this Nation.</p>
                           <p>In his <hi>Charter,</hi> dated 1088. of the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>St. Martins the Great,</hi> in the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> thereof, are theſe words;</p>
                           <p>In Example of <hi>Moſes</hi> who built the <hi>Tabernable,</hi> and of <hi>Solomon</hi> who built the <hi>Temple,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ego Guilielmus Dei diſpoſitione, &amp; conſanguinitatis Haereditate Anglorum Baſileus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           <pb n="cxxx" facs="tcp:59543:75"/>
                           <p>The <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. his Son, to this Abby, in honour of <hi>Edward</hi> my Kinſman, who <hi>adopted</hi> my <hi>Father</hi> and his <hi>Children</hi> to be <hi>Heirs</hi> to <hi>this</hi> Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In another <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. in the Book of <hi>Ely,</hi> he calls himſelf the Son of King <hi>William the Great,</hi> who by <hi>Hereditary Right</hi> ſucceeded <hi>King Edward.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>It is true, as to his pretence of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle by the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſor, <hi>Mathew Paris</hi>
                              </hi> objecteth, That the Deviſe was void, being without the conſent of the <hi>Barons.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>To which may be anſwered, That probably the <hi>Law</hi> might be ſo in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. Time, when <hi>Paris</hi> wrote, and was ſo taken to be in the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> and in the Caſe of King <hi>John.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But at the time of <hi>Duke William</hi>'s Invaſion, the <hi>Law</hi> was taken to be, That a <hi>Kingdom</hi> might be <hi>transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> by <hi>Will.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxxi" facs="tcp:59543:75"/>
                           <p>So was that of <hi>Sixtus Rufus,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> came to the <hi>Romans</hi> by the <hi>Will</hi> of King <hi>Attalus;</hi> the words by <hi>Annaeus Florus</hi> are, <hi>Populus Romanus Bonorum meorum HAERES eſto.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Bithinia</hi> came to the <hi>Romans</hi> by the <hi>laſt Will</hi> of their King <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> which is remembred by <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tropius,</hi> together with that of <hi>Libia.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Oration tells us, That the Kingdom of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> by the <hi>laſt Will</hi> of their King, was <hi>devolved</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And <hi>Praſutagus Rex Icenorum</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> upon his Death-bed, gave his Kingdom to the Emperor <hi>Nero.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>As to Examples in this Point at Home, This King <hi>William the firſt,</hi> by his <hi>Will,</hi> gave <hi>England</hi> to his younger Son <hi>William Rufus.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>King <hi>Stephen</hi> claimed by the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Henry the firſt.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxxii" facs="tcp:59543:76"/>
                           <p>King <hi>Henry the eight</hi> had Power, by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> to order the <hi>Succesſion</hi> of the Crown as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by Will.</p>
                           <p>And the Lords of the Council, in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Time, wrote to her, That the Lady <hi>Iane's Title</hi> to the Crown, was by the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Edward the ſixth.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>As the caſe of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. was by <hi>Act of Parliament;</hi> ſo <hi>Duke Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> after he had <hi>conquered Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold,</hi> was, by the <hi>general conſent</hi> of the <hi>Barons</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England</hi> accepted for their King; and ſo his <hi>Title</hi> by <hi>Will</hi> confirmed.</p>
                           <p>And he both <hi>claimed,</hi> and <hi>govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> the Kingdom, as an <hi>Heir</hi> and <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> confirmed their <hi>Antient Laws,</hi> and ruled according to them: This appears by <hi>Chronica Chronico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>William the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> he ſaith, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, as <hi>St. Edward</hi> had no <hi>Heir</hi> of <hi>England, William</hi> having <hi>conquered Harold,</hi> the <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> obtained the
<pb n="cxxxiii" facs="tcp:59543:76"/> Crown under <hi>this Condition,</hi> That he ſhould <hi>inviolably</hi> obſerve thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> given by the ſaid <hi>Edward.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>It is teſtified likewiſe, by many of our <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> That the <hi>Ancient Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>confirmed</hi> by Duke <hi>VVilliam.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Jornalenſis</hi> ſaith, That out of the <hi>Merchen-Lage, Weſt-Saxon-Lage,</hi> and <hi>Dane-Lage,</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> compoſed the <hi>Common Law,</hi> which remains to this day.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> who lived in Duke <hi>William</hi>'s Time, ſaith, That the <hi>Kings</hi> were <hi>ſworn</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> ſo called, (ſaith he) becauſe he <hi>obſerved</hi> them moſt <hi>religiouſly.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But to make this Point clear out of <hi>Ingulphus,</hi> he ſaith, in the end of his <hi>Chronicle,</hi> I <hi>Ingulphus</hi> brought with me from <hi>London,</hi> into my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, (<hi>Crowland</hi>) the Laws of the moſt Righteous King <hi>Edward;</hi> which my Lord King <hi>William</hi> did
<pb n="cxxxiv" facs="tcp:59543:77"/> command, by his Proclamation, to be Authentick and Perpetual, and to be obſerved throughout the whole Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> upon pain of moſt heinous puniſhment.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>Lieger-Book</hi> of the Abby of <hi>Waltham,</hi> commends Duke <hi>William</hi> for <hi>reſtoring</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-men</hi> out of the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of their Country.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Radburn</hi> follows this Opinion, and theſe <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Edward the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> are the ſame in part which are continued in our GREAT CHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER of LIBERTIES.</p>
                           <p>A Manuſcript entituled, <hi>De Geſtis Anglorum,</hi> ſaith, That at a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> 4. <hi>W.</hi> 1. the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers alſo preſent, that the King might hear their Laws, he <hi>eſtabliſhed Saint Edward's Laws,</hi> they being <hi>former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> uſed in King <hi>Edgar</hi>'s Time.</p>
                           <p>There is alſo mention of the <hi>twelve</hi> Men out of every County, to deliver truly the <hi>Eſtate</hi> of their <hi>Laws:</hi> The ſame is remembred by <hi>Selden</hi>'s Hiſtory
<pb n="cxxxv" facs="tcp:59543:77"/> of Tythes, and Titles of Honour, and in a <hi>Manuſcript Chronicle</hi> bound with the Book of <hi>Ely</hi> in <hi>Cotton</hi>'s Library.</p>
                           <p>One of the worthy Gentlemen, from whom I differ in Opinion, was pleaſed to ſay, That if <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> did not <hi>introduce</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Normandy</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> yet he conceives <hi>our Laws</hi> to be <hi>brought</hi> out of <hi>France</hi> hither, in the time of ſome <hi>other</hi> of our <hi>Kings,</hi> who had large Territories in <hi>France,</hi> and brought in <hi>their Laws</hi> hither; elſe he wonders how <hi>our Laws</hi> ſhould be in <hi>French.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Sir, I ſhall endeavour to ſatisfy his Wonder therein by and by; but, firſt, with your leave, I ſhall offer to you ſome <hi>Probabilities</hi> out of the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> That the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were by ſome of thoſe Kings <hi>carried</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> rather than the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>France <hi>brought</hi>
                              </hi> hither.</p>
                           <p>This is expreſly affirmed by <hi>Paulus Jovius,</hi> who writes, That when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings reigned in a <hi>great part</hi>
                              <pb n="cxxxvi" facs="tcp:59543:78"/> of <hi>France,</hi> they <hi>taught</hi> the <hi>French</hi> their <hi>Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Hiſtorian, writes, That the <hi>Normans,</hi> in their Manners, and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> followed the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Polydore Virgil;</hi> contradicting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in another place than before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, relates, That in our King <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. Time, the Duke of <hi>Bedford</hi> called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the <hi>Chief Men</hi> of all the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and delivered in his Oration to them, the many <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> afforded them, eſpecially in that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> gave to them their <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>By the Chronicle of <hi>Eltham, <hi>H.</hi>
                              </hi> 5. ſent to <hi>Cane</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> not only Divines, but <hi>Engliſh</hi> Common Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, by the agreement at <hi>Troys.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>So there is much more probability that the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>introduced</hi> into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> than that the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> or any other part of <hi>France,</hi>
                              <pb n="cxxxvii" facs="tcp:59543:78"/> were <hi>introduced</hi> into <hi>England.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>If the <hi>Normans</hi> had been <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as they were not; but their <hi>Duke</hi> was only a <hi>Conqueror</hi> of <hi>Harold,</hi> and received as <hi>Hereditary</hi> King of <hi>England;</hi> yet is it <hi>not</hi> probable they would have <hi>changed</hi> our <hi>Laws,</hi> and have <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi> theirs; becauſe they did not uſe to do ſo upon other <hi>Conqueſts.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The <hi>Normans <hi>conquered</hi>
                              </hi> the Iſles of <hi>Guernſey</hi> and <hi>Jerſey,</hi> yet <hi>altered not</hi> their <hi>Laws,</hi> which in their local Cuſtoms are like unto ours.</p>
                           <p>The like they did in <hi>Sicily, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and <hi>Apulia,</hi> where they were <hi>Conquerors;</hi> yet the <hi>Ancient Laws</hi> of thoſe Countries were continued.</p>
                           <p>I hope, Mr. Speaker, I have, by this time given ſome ſatisfaction to the Worthy Gentlemen who differed from me, that the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>not impoſed</hi> upon us by the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> nor <hi>brought</hi> over hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either out of <hi>Normandy,</hi> or any <hi>other part</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> but are our <hi>Ancient</hi> Native <hi>Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cxxxviiiX" facs="tcp:59543:79"/>
                           <p>I muſt now come to indeavour alſo to ſatisfy the Wonder; If they were <hi>not brought</hi> out of <hi>Normandy,</hi> or ſome <hi>other part</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> how come they then to be <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Language!</p>
                           <p>Sir, It is to me an Argument, That becauſe they are <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> therefore they were <hi>not brought</hi> in by Duke <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Norman;</hi> for the <hi>French</hi> Tongue was not the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Duke <hi>William,</hi> and the <hi>Normans.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>They had not been then in Duke <hi>William</hi>'s Time, paſt four <hi>deſcents</hi> in that part of <hi>France;</hi> and it is impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that they, in ſo ſhort a Time, ſhould loſe their <hi>Native Tongue,</hi> and take up, and uſe the Language of another Countrey, which was <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered</hi> by them.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>Normans</hi> came from <hi>Sweden, Gothland, Norway,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> between whoſe Languages, and with the <hi>High-Dutch,</hi> their Neighbours, there is a great affinity; but between theſe Languages, and the <hi>French,</hi> there is none at all.</p>
                           <pb n="cxxxix" facs="tcp:59543:79"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lphilus</hi> holds, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tongue came from the <hi>Goths. Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandus</hi> ſaith, The <hi>Goth's</hi> Tongue came from the <hi>Dutch.</hi> All agree, That between thoſe Languages and the <hi>French</hi> there is no affinity.</p>
                           <p>It is ſo improbable, that Duke <hi>William</hi> ſhould cauſe our <hi>Laws</hi> to be in <hi>French,</hi> that when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed them, (as <hi>Ingulphus</hi> teſtifies) he commanded that they ſhould be uſed in the ſame Language they were <hi>written</hi> (in <hi>Engliſh</hi>) to his Juſtices, and gives the Reaſon, Leſt by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance we ſhould happen to break them.</p>
                           <p>But it hath been further objected, If Duke <hi>William</hi> did <hi>not</hi> cauſe our <hi>Laws</hi> to be <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> what then ſhould be the Reaſon, that the <hi>Grand Cuſtumary</hi> of his <hi>Norman Laws</hi> were <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue?</p>
                           <p>The Reaſon thereof is given, That the <hi>Normans,</hi> being a Rough and Martial People, had few Clerks
<pb n="cxl" facs="tcp:59543:80"/> amongſt them, but made uſe of thoſe <hi>French,</hi> amongſt whom they then lived, and whoſe Language they then began to be acquainted with, and to underſtand.</p>
                           <p>But when they were in <hi>England,</hi> they had not ſo much uſe of thoſe Clerks, and that Language, but more of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And probably it might be, that the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> had been ſo long in <hi>France,</hi> that he was more Maſter of that Language than the <hi>Normans,</hi> and that the <hi>Normans</hi> underſtood that Language better than the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and thereupon the <hi>Cuſtumary</hi> was <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue.</p>
                           <p>But it doth not therefore follow that Duke <hi>William</hi> muſt cauſe the <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> to be <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue: but it is more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he might cauſe them to be continued in their <hi>Native Idiom,</hi> which was much <hi>nearer</hi> in affinity to his own <hi>Northern</hi> Language than the <hi>French</hi> was.</p>
                           <pb n="cxli" facs="tcp:59543:80"/>
                           <p>That the <hi>French</hi> Tongue was <hi>not introduced,</hi> as to our <hi>Laws</hi> and other things, by Duke <hi>William</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> appears, in that the <hi>French</hi> was in great uſe with us here, both before, and ſome-time after his Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Beda</hi> affirms, That in <hi>Anno</hi> 640, it was the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to ſend their <hi>Daughters</hi> into the <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to be brought up there; and that <hi>Ethelbert, Ethelwulf, Ethelred,</hi> and other <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, married into the <hi>Royal Blood</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Glabor</hi> notes, That before the Time of Duke <hi>William,</hi> the <hi>Normans</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> did ſo link together, that they were a Terror to <hi>Forreign</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ingulphus</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Saxon</hi> Hand was uſed until the Time of King <hi>Alfred,</hi> long <hi>before</hi> the Time of Duke <hi>William;</hi> and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought up by <hi>French</hi> Teachers, uſed the <hi>French</hi> Hand.</p>
                           <pb n="cxlii" facs="tcp:59543:81"/>
                           <p>And he notes many <hi>Charters</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> written in the <hi>French</hi> Hand, and ſome <hi>Saxon</hi> mixt with it, as in the Book of <hi>Dooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>That <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> by reaſon of his long being in <hi>France,</hi> was turned into the <hi>French</hi> Faſhion, and all <hi>England</hi> with him.</p>
                           <p>But that <hi>William the firſt</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded our <hi>Laws</hi> to be <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, becauſe moſt Men underſtood it, and that there be many of his <hi>Patents</hi> in the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Tongue.</p>
                           <p>I ſuppoſe we may be ſatisfied, that <hi>William the firſt</hi> did <hi>not</hi> cauſe our <hi>Laws</hi> to be <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> though the <hi>French</hi> Language was much in uſe here before his Time.</p>
                           <p>And if he did <hi>not introduce</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Language into <hi>England,</hi> the Argument falls, That becauſe they are <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> therefore he <hi>brought</hi> them in.</p>
                           <pb n="cxliii" facs="tcp:59543:81"/>
                           <p>But, Sir, I ſhall offer you ſome Conjectures, how it came that our <hi>Laws</hi> were <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> which I ſuppoſe might be begun in the Time of our K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. who was a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> born, and had large Territories and Relations in <hi>France,</hi> and with <hi>French-men,</hi> of whom great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers came into <hi>England;</hi> and they and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> matched, and lived together, both here, and in ſome parts of <hi>France.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Hence it came to paſs, (as <hi>Giral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Cambrenſis</hi> notes) that the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Tongue was in great uſe in <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> and in other parts of <hi>France,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> were reſident and converſant; the like was, when the <hi>French-men</hi> were ſo converſant in <hi>England.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Mathew Weſtminſter</hi> writes, That he was in hazard of loſing his Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe he underſtood not the <hi>French</hi> Tongue: and that in King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. and King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Time, who had large Dominions in <hi>France;</hi> their Native Country, and
<pb n="cxliv" facs="tcp:59543:82"/> the Number of <hi>French,</hi> and of Matches with them, was ſo great, that one could hardly know who was <hi>French,</hi> and who <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Gervaſius Tilsberienſis</hi> obſerves the ſame: And <hi>Brackland</hi> writes, That in <hi>Rich.</hi> 1. Time, preaching in <hi>England,</hi> was in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue. Probably Pleading might be ſo likewiſe; and in King <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Time, <hi>French</hi> was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the <hi>Mother</hi> Tongue.</p>
                           <p>There are ſcarce any Deeds of our Kings in <hi>French</hi> before <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. his Time, the moſt are in <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. their Time.</p>
                           <p>That <hi>our Laws</hi> were <hi>pleaded</hi> and <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French</hi> before <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. his Time, appears by the <hi>Stat.</hi> 36. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 15. which recites the <hi>Miſchief</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> being in <hi>French;</hi> and enacts, That the <hi>Law</hi> ſhall <hi>thereafter</hi> be <hi>pleaded</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>enrolled</hi> in <hi>Latin.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>This is one ground of the miſtaken Opinion of <hi>Lambard, Polydore, Speed,</hi> and others, That Duke <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> brought in hither both the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws</hi> and Language; which I
<pb n="cxlv" facs="tcp:59543:82"/> apprehend to be fully anſwered, and the contrary manifeſted by what I have ſaid before on this Subject.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Polydores</hi> Miſtake may appear the more, when he aſſerts; that by the <hi>Stat.</hi> 36. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Matters are to be <hi>enrolled</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expreſs Words, that they are to be <hi>enrolled</hi> in <hi>Latin.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Many of our <hi>Law-Books</hi> were <hi>written</hi> in <hi>Latin</hi> before the <hi>Norman</hi> Invaſion; as appears by the <hi>Ancient Rolls</hi> of <hi>Mannors,</hi> and <hi>Court Barons,</hi> and our Old Authors, <hi>Glanvill, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton, Tilsbury, Hengham, Fleta,</hi> the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Entries.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The Records at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and the <hi>Tower,</hi> and other Records yet extant, are in <hi>Latin;</hi> and many Books of our <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> were tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> about <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. his Time.</p>
                           <p>Moſt of our Statutes, from <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. his Time, till about the middle of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. his Reign, are <hi>enrolled</hi> in
<pb n="cxlvi" facs="tcp:59543:83"/> 
                              <hi>French,</hi> notwithſtanding this <hi>Stat.</hi> 36. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. except the <hi>Stat.</hi> 6. <hi>R.</hi> 2. &amp; ſome others in <hi>Latin</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>R. 2. H. 4. H.</hi> 5. and <hi>H.</hi> 6. uſed to write their Letters in <hi>French;</hi> and ſome of our <hi>Fleadings</hi> are in <hi>French,</hi> and in the <hi>Common Pleas</hi> to our Time.</p>
                           <p>But, Sir, our <hi>Law</hi> is, <hi>Lex non Scripta.</hi> I mean our <hi>Common Law</hi> and our <hi>Statutes Records</hi> and <hi>Books,</hi> which are <hi>written</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> are no <hi>Argument</hi> that therefore the <hi>Original</hi> of our <hi>Laws</hi> is from <hi>France:</hi> but they were in being <hi>before</hi> any of the <hi>French</hi> Language was in our <hi>Laws.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Forteſcue</hi> writes, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> kept their Accounts in <hi>French,</hi> yet doubtleſs they had Accounts here, and Revenues <hi>before</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage was in uſe here.</p>
                           <p>My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Conqueror</hi> taught the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the <hi>Norman</hi> Terms of <hi>Hawling, Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                              <pb n="cxlvii" facs="tcp:59543:83"/> and <hi>Gaming,</hi> &amp;c. yet no doubt but that theſe Recreations were in uſe with us before his Time.</p>
                           <p>And tho' Duke <hi>William</hi> or any other of our Kings before, or after his Time, did bring in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue amongſt us, yet that is <hi>no <hi>Argument,</hi>
                              </hi> that he or they did <hi>change,</hi> or <hi>introduce</hi> our <hi>Laws,</hi> which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly were here <hi>long before</hi> thoſe Times; and ſome of them, when the <hi>French</hi> Tongue was ſo much in uſe here, were <hi>tranſlated, written,</hi> and <hi>pleaded,</hi> and <hi>recorded,</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, yet remained the <hi>ſame Law</hi> ſtill.</p>
                           <p>And from the great uſe of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue here, it was, That the <hi>Reporters</hi> of our <hi>Law-Caſes</hi> and Judgments, which were in thoſe Times, did write their Reports in <hi>French,</hi> which was the pure <hi>French</hi> in that Time, tho' mixt with ſome words of Art.</p>
                           <p>Thoſe <hi>Terms</hi> of <hi>Art</hi> were taken; many of them, from the <hi>Saxon</hi>
                              <pb n="cxlviii" facs="tcp:59543:84"/> Tongue, and may be ſeen by them yet uſed; and the <hi>Reporters</hi> of later Times, and our <hi>Students</hi> at this day uſe to take their <hi>Notes</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> following the <hi>Old Reports</hi> which they had ſtudied, and the <hi>Old French,</hi> which, as in other Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by time came to be varied.</p>
                           <p>I ſhall not deny, but that ſome <hi>Monks</hi> in elder Times, and ſome <hi>Clerks</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> might have a Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for their private Honour and Profit, to keep up a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> to have as much as they could of our <hi>Laws,</hi> to be in a kind of <hi>Myſtery</hi> to the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> to be the leſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by them: But the <hi>Councellors</hi> at <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> can have no advantage by it; but perhaps it would be found, that the <hi>Law,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and generally more underſtood, yet not ſufficiently, would occaſion the more Suits.</p>
                           <p>And poſſibly there might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the like nature as to the <hi>Court Hand;</hi> yet if the more <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hands</hi> were uſed in our <hi>Law-writings,</hi>
                              <pb n="cxlix" facs="tcp:59543:84"/> they would be the more ſubject to <hi>change;</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and other Languages are, but not the <hi>Latin.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Surely the <hi>French</hi> Tongue uſed in our <hi>Reports</hi> and <hi>Law-Books,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not to be ſo enviouſly decried, as it is by <hi>Polydore, Aliot, Daniel, Hottoman, Cowell,</hi> and other Cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
                           <p>But, <hi>Mr. Speaker,</hi> if I have been tedious, I humbly ask your pardon, and have the more hopes to obtain it from ſo many worthy <hi>Engliſh Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> when that which I have ſaid, was chiefly in vindication of their own <hi>Native Laws,</hi> unto which I hold my ſelf the <hi>more obliged</hi> by the <hi>Duty</hi> of my <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it an <hi>honour</hi> to me to be a <hi>Lawyer.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>As to the Debate, and Matter of the Act now before you, I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered no Opinion againſt it, nor do I think it reaſonable, that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England</hi>
                              <pb n="cxlviii" facs="tcp:59543:85"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="cxlix" facs="tcp:59543:85"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="cl" facs="tcp:59543:86"/> ſhould, by an Implicit Faith, depend upon the knowledg of others, in that which concerns them moſt of all.</p>
                           <p>It was the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Policy, to keep them in <hi>Ignorance</hi> of Matters pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their <hi>Souls</hi> Health; let them not be in <hi>Ignorance</hi> of Matters per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to their <hi>Bodies, Eſtates,</hi> and all their <hi>worldly</hi> Comfort.</p>
                           <p>It is not unreaſonable, that the <hi>Law</hi> ſhould be in the Language which may <hi>beſt</hi> be <hi>underſtood</hi> by thoſe, whoſe <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> are <hi>ſubject</hi> to it, and are to be <hi>governed</hi> by it.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Moſes</hi> read all the <hi>Laws</hi> openly before the <hi>People</hi> in their <hi>Mother</hi> Tongue: God directed him to write it, and to expound it to the <hi>People</hi> in their own <hi>Native</hi> Language, that what concerned their <hi>Lives, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> might be made <hi>known</hi> unto them in their moſt <hi>perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous</hi> way.</p>
                           <pb n="cli" facs="tcp:59543:86"/>
                           <p>The <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Nations were in their <hi>proper</hi> Tongue.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>Laws</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> were in <hi>Greek;</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Latin;</hi> in <hi>France, <hi>Spain, Germany, Sweden, Denmark,</hi>
                              </hi> and other Nations, their <hi>Laws</hi> are <hi>publiſhed</hi> in their <hi>Native Idiom.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>For your own Country, there is no Man that can read the <hi>Saxon</hi> Character, but may find the <hi>Laws</hi> of their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> yet <hi>extant</hi> in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Tongue.</p>
                           <p>Duke <hi>VVilliam</hi> himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Laws</hi> to be <hi>proclaimed</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that none might pretend <hi>ignorance</hi> of them.</p>
                           <p>It was the Judgment of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> 36. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. That <hi>Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> ſhould be in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and in the Reigns of thoſe Kings, when <hi>our Statutes</hi> were <hi>enrolled</hi> in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> yet then the <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> in their ſeveral <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
                              <pb n="clii" facs="tcp:59543:87"/> were to <hi>proclaim</hi> them in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>I ſhall conclude with a Complaint of what I have met with abroad, from ſome <hi>Military</hi> Perſons; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Scoffs</hi> and <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt our <hi>Law,</hi> and Threats to take it away; <hi>but the <hi>Law</hi> is above the reach of thoſe Weapons, which at one time or another will return upon thoſe that uſe them.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Solid Arguments, ſtrong Reaſons and Authorities, are more fit for Confutation of any Error, and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of different Judgments: When the <hi>Emperor</hi> took a Biſhop in <hi>compleat Armour</hi> in a <hi>Battle,</hi> he ſent the <hi>Armour</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> with theſe words, <hi>Haeccine ſunt veſtes Filii tui?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>So may I ſay to thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> abroad, as to their <hi>Railings, Taunts,</hi> and <hi>Threats</hi> againſt the <hi>Law, Haeccine ſunt Argumenta horum Antinomiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum?</hi> They will be found of no force, but <hi>recoiling Arms.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="cliii" facs="tcp:59543:87"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Nor is it ingenious or prudent for ENGLISH-MEN to deprav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> their Birth-right, the Laws of their own Country.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Thus, Sir, have I impartially given you my Sentiments of <hi>VVilliam the firſt</hi> his <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> which hath been ſo <hi>terribly</hi> and <hi>frightfully</hi> repreſented and <hi>publiſhed</hi> to the <hi>VVorld,</hi> by the <hi>Ignorance, Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Artifice</hi> of ſome <hi>Modern VVriters:</hi> Thus have I, as an <hi>Engliſh Man,</hi> endeavoured to do my <hi>Country</hi> Juſtice, and to <hi>ſupport</hi> the <hi>true Honour,</hi> both of our worthy <hi>Saxon</hi> Anceſtors, and of our <hi>excellent</hi> and famous <hi>Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Conqueſt</hi> and <hi>Slavery;</hi> as alſo to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify the <hi>Ancient Parliamentary</hi> Right as well of <hi>Lords</hi> as <hi>Commons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet for your <hi>fuller</hi> and <hi>clearer</hi> ſatisfaction in this ſo weighty a Point, I ſhall refer you, if you pleaſe, to the <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judicious Diſcourſes</hi> writ, in ſome meaſure, more particularly
<pb n="cliv" facs="tcp:59543:88"/> upon this Subject, <hi>never</hi> yet ſufficiently <hi>anſwered</hi> to my <hi>Conviction,</hi> though I have <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> compared and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered all the <hi>pretended Anſwers</hi> and them together, (without the leaſt of <hi>byaſs</hi> or <hi>prepoſſeſſion;</hi> and I heartily could wiſh others would do the like, and that for TRUTH's ſake.)</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Diſcourſes are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Selden's Jani Anglorum Facies Alter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Sytas Taylor</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velkind.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Petyt</hi>'s Rights of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> aſſerted.</item>
                  <item>And Mr. <hi>Attwood's, Jani Anglorum Facies Nova.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And his, —<hi>Jus Anglorum ab Antiquo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>You would likewiſe, I ſuppoſe, be extreamly pleaſed in the peruſal of another Learned and Modeſt Book,
<pb n="clv" facs="tcp:59543:88"/> written by an <hi>Anonymous</hi> Author, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patriarcha non Monarcha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Authors, for whoſe Names Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will have a greater reſpect than we at preſent have; and that for their diſcovery of Truth, and refuting ſo many Vulgar Errors.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>I am, <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful Servant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:89"/>
            <pb n="clvii" facs="tcp:59543:89"/>
            <head>The Appendix.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ABbas de Middleton tenet in Capite de Domino Rege Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerium de Middleton,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ex Feoffamenti Regis Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtani &amp; nullum ſervitium fecit niſi Orationes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Rotulo de Inquiſitionibus Dominicorum Dorſetſhire. An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 4to. R. H. Fil. R. I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we ſee that King <hi>Aethelſtan,</hi> who reigned above 740 Years agoe, <hi>infeoffed</hi> the Abbey of <hi>Middleton,</hi> of the <hi>Mannor</hi> of <hi>Middleton;</hi> and that by virtue thereof, the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> held it <hi>in Capite, 4. H.</hi> 3. and did <hi>no Service</hi> for it, but only to <hi>pray</hi> for the <hi>Souls</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and other <hi>ſucceeding Kings;</hi> and all this, you ſee, found by <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> in the Fourth Year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rot. Cartar. 19. H. 6. Nu. 16. m. 27. per Inſpex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pro Decano &amp; Capitulo Sancti Martini Magni London. per Inſpeximus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſpeximus Cartam, quam celebris Memoriae Dominus Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus quondam Rex Angl. progenitor' noſtri, fecit Deo &amp; Eccleſiae Sancti Martini Magni London. in hec verba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>QUia inter multa bona opera, quae fideles Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti pro anima<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> ſua<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> ſalute operantur, hoc <abbr>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pun</abbr> eſtimatur &amp; tenetur, Quod <abbr>inſtitution</abbr> &amp; <abbr>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification</abbr> Sanctae Matris <abbr>Eccle</abbr> devota mente impendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="clviii" facs="tcp:59543:90"/> in qua <abbr>suorum</abbr> Dei ſupplicationibus peccata a pio Deo diluuntur, quod Moiſes in myſtici Tabernaculi conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one <abbr>pmonſtravit,</abbr> quod etiam Salomonis induſtria <abbr>pfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit,</abbr> dum Templum <abbr>Dno</abbr> Artificioſum &amp; honorabile edificaret, futuram ſignificans <abbr>Eccleam</abbr> ſummo a fidelibus debere honore decorari, quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> 
               <abbr>vidlt</abbr> exemplo in nomine <abbr>Dm</abbr> 
               <abbr>nri</abbr> Ieſu Chriſti, Ego <abbr>Willus</abbr> Dei diſpoſitione &amp; <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitatis haereditate</hi> Anglorum Baſileus Normanno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Dux, &amp; Rector cujuſdam fidelis mei Ingelrici ſcilicet <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioni</hi> acquieſcens <hi>Archiepiſcoporum, Epiſcoporum, Abbatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Comitum &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſorum</hi> procerum <hi>meorum, Sacro Conſilio parens omnes poſſeſſiones terrarum, quas tempore ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rabilis ac dilectiſſimi cognati &amp; predeceſſoris mei Regis Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi.</hi> Idem Ingelricus acquiſierat ꝙ ipſius inſigniſſimi Regis Animae Salute, necnon &amp; peccatorum meorum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione, concedo &amp; Regia auctoritate <abbr>imꝑpm</abbr> corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boro &amp; confirmo Deo &amp; <abbr>Eccle</abbr> Beati Martini, quam <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra muros London.</hi> ſitam <abbr>pfatus</abbr> Ingelricus &amp; Erardus <abbr>Frat</abbr> ejus de propriis ſuis Redditibus in delicto<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> ſuo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> 
               <abbr>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</abbr> honorabiliter ad Dei laudem, &amp; Canonicalem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulam <abbr>imꝑpm</abbr> 
               <abbr>ſervand</abbr> &amp; <abbr>tenend</abbr> conſtruxerunt. Sunt igitur haec terrarum nomina, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Et ſi quas alias <abbr>libtates</abbr> vel conſuetudines, aliqua <abbr>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clea<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan>
               </abbr> Regni mei <abbr>Angl</abbr> meliores <abbr>het;</abbr> ſi quis vero hoc in aliud quam conceſſimus transferre <abbr>pſumpſerit,</abbr> cum Juda Proditore Dei haeredibas luat penas. Scripta eſt haec Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula An ab Incarnatione <abbr>Dm</abbr> M. LX. VIII. ſcilicet ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Anno Regni mei; ꝑacta vero eſt haec Donatio die Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <abbr>Dm</abbr>, &amp; poſtmodum in die <abbr>Pentecoſt</abbr> 
               <abbr>confirmat</abbr>, quando <abbr>Matil</abbr> conjux mea in Baſilica Sancti Petri <abbr>Weſtm</abbr> in Reginam divino nutu eſt conſccrata, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ego <abbr>Willus</abbr> Rex Anglorum &amp; Dux Normannorum ſub Sigillo Sancte, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> quas indeclinabiliter conſenſi at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> 
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> roloravi. Ego Matil Regina conſenſum prebui. Ego <abbr>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</abbr>
               <pb n="clix" facs="tcp:59543:90"/> Regis <abbr>Fil</abbr> annui. Ego Stigandus Archiepiſcopus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſi. Ego Aldredus Archiepiſcopus confirmavi. Ego <abbr>Willus</abbr> 
               <abbr>Lond</abbr> Epiſcopus, infra cujus muros <abbr>pfatum</abbr> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterium ſitum eſt, ſignaculo Sancte Crucis ſubarravi, &amp; <abbr>libtatem</abbr> omnimodam quantumcum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> mee ꝑtinet poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litati, conceſſi. Ego Odo Baiocenſis Epiſcopus conceſſi. Ego Hugo Luxonienſis Epiſcopus interfui. Ego Goiffri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Epiſcopus corroboravi. Ego Hermannus Epiſcopus conceſſi. Ego Leouricus Epiſcopus conceſſi. Ego Giſo Epiſcopus conceſſi. Ego Edwious Abbas. Ego Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waldus Abbas. Ego Baldwinus Abbas. Ego Agelſinus Abbas. Ego Turſtinus Abbas. Ego Brand Abbas. Ego Alſwinus Abbas. Ego Sithricus Abbas. Ego <abbr>Wills</abbr> 
               <abbr>Fil</abbr> 
               <abbr>Osbti</abbr> Comes. Ego <abbr>Robtus</abbr> 
               <abbr>Frat</abbr> Regis Comes. Ego Edwinus Comes. Ego <abbr>Robtus</abbr> Comes. Ego Marchere Comes. Ego Waldeof Comes. Ego Rogerus de Monte Goverii Comes. Ego <abbr>Ricus</abbr> Fil <abbr>Giſlebti</abbr> Princeps. Ego <abbr>Wills</abbr> Malet Princeps. Ego Arfaſtus Regis Cancellarius. Ego Michael Regis Capellanus. Ego <abbr>Giſlbtus</abbr> Capellanus. Ego Osbinus Capellanus. Ego <abbr>Wills</abbr> Capellanus. Ego Thomas Capellanus. Ego Bernardus Capellanus. Ego Walterus Capellanus. Ego <abbr>Robtus</abbr> Capellanus. Ego <abbr>Johes</abbr> Sancte Romane <abbr>Ecclie</abbr> Cardinalis <abbr>Presbit</abbr> per Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias &amp; <abbr>Angl</abbr> concedente Papa Alexandro vices Apoſtolicas gerens, huic conſtitutioni interfui, &amp; quantum Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Sedi ꝑtinuit <abbr>libtatem</abbr> 
               <abbr>Ecclie</abbr> 
               <abbr>pſenti</abbr> Signo confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi. Ego Petrus Sancte Romane <abbr>Ecclie</abbr> 
               <abbr>ſimilit</abbr> Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <abbr>Presbit</abbr> &amp; Cancellarius, ab eodem Papa in <abbr>Angl</abbr> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> huic Conſtitutioni acquieſcens propria Manu ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſi.
<pb n="clx" facs="tcp:59543:91"/> I give you this <hi>Charter,</hi> Sir, as a <hi>further Proof</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> for me, in theſe <hi>Particulars,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You may obſerve by theſe words, <hi>Conſanguinitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haereditate Anglorum Baſileus,</hi> that here King <hi>William</hi> made an <hi>abſolute diſclaimer</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> in the ſecond Year of his <hi>Reign,</hi> and only inſiſted on, (what he knew full well was his <hi>ſurer hold,</hi>) his <hi>claim</hi> by <hi>Hereditary Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And this is ſo much the <hi>more conſiderable,</hi> as it was done in his <hi>Great Council</hi> of Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, Earls, <hi>&amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſorum</hi> procerum <hi>ſuorum,</hi> a word of a <hi>large ſignification,</hi> as well in <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> as in <hi>Ancient Records,</hi> for under the word <hi>Proceres</hi> were comprehended <hi>Principes Civium, vel Civitatis;</hi> And the <hi>former Inſtances</hi> I have given you of other <hi>General Councils,</hi> and the <hi>Parts</hi> thereof in this King's Reign, <hi>fully agree</hi> with <hi>this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Claim and Proteſtation of the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Parl. 2. H.</hi> 5. Pars ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda <hi>N. 10.</hi>
               </note> Commons made the Parl. <hi>2d H.</hi> 5. which ſays, <hi>That ſo as hit hath</hi> ever <hi>be their</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte <hi>and</hi> Freedom, <hi>that thar ſhould no</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, <hi>ne</hi> Law, <hi>be made of laſſe then they</hi> yaffe <hi>thereto their</hi> aſſent, <hi>conſidering that the</hi> Commune <hi>of your Lond, the which that</hi> is, <hi>and</hi> ever <hi>hath be a</hi> Membre <hi>of your</hi> Parliament, <hi>been as well</hi> Aſſentirs <hi>as</hi> Petitioners. And which was <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> and ſo became an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> was, but an <hi>Affirmation</hi> and <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the <hi>Ancient Law</hi> of the <hi>Land:</hi> And the <hi>ſame Right</hi> cannot be <hi>denied</hi> by any Man to the <hi>Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And that he <hi>confirmed</hi> (as the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of <hi>ſucceeding Kings</hi> have done to <hi>this day</hi>) all the <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> of thoſe Lands to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>St. Martins le Grand,</hi> which they had in the Time of <hi>EDWARD</hi> the CONFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOR.</p>
            <p>Now if this <hi>fond Notion</hi> of <hi>William</hi>'s <hi>Abſolute Conqueſt</hi> be
<pb n="clxi" facs="tcp:59543:91"/> true, then either the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Earls, Barons, and Commons, in <hi>Parl. 15. R. 2. knew</hi> it, or they did <hi>not.</hi> That they were <hi>ignorant</hi> of it, is not <hi>eaſily</hi> to be <hi>preſumed,</hi> becauſe they <hi>lived</hi> within <hi>ten</hi> of <hi>three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> Years ago, and no doubt but there were ſome <hi>Learned</hi> Men among them, that knew the <hi>ancient Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> of the <hi>Nation:</hi> And if they <hi>did,</hi> then were they <hi>guilty</hi> of the <hi>greateſt madneſs</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> that ever was, when the <hi>Commons</hi> prayed that <hi>King; En</hi> plein <hi>Parlement que noſtre Seigneur le Roy ſoit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. 15. R. 2. N. 13.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; eſtoiſe auſi frank en ſa</hi> Regalie Liberte <hi>&amp;</hi> Dignite Royale <hi>en</hi> ſon temps <hi>come</hi> aſcuns de ceſt Noble Progenitors, Roys d' Eng† <hi>furent en</hi> lour temps <hi>nient contreſteant aſcun Eſtatut ou Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance fait devant ceſt hures a contraire &amp; meſment en</hi> dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>de la</hi> Libertee <hi>&amp;</hi> Franchiſe <hi>de la</hi> Corone <hi>qu'il ſoit</hi> adnulle <hi>&amp; de</hi> nul force <hi>&amp; puis touz les Prelates &amp; Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neures Temporels prierent en meſme le manere &amp; ſur ce noſtre Seigneur ledit Roy</hi> mercia <hi>les dits Seigneurs &amp; Communes de la grant tendreſſe &amp;</hi> affection <hi>qu'ils avoient a la</hi> Salvation <hi>de ſon</hi> Honeur <hi>&amp; de ſon</hi> Eſtate <hi>&amp; a cauſe que lour dit</hi> priers <hi>&amp;</hi> requeſtes <hi>luy ſemblerent</hi> honeſtes <hi>&amp;</hi> reſonables <hi>il</hi> ſagrea <hi>&amp;</hi> aſſenta pleinement <hi>a ycelles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now can any Man, of but an <hi>ordinary underſtanding,</hi> think, That the <hi>Parliament</hi> intended, by this <hi>Act,</hi> to <hi>out</hi> themſelves of all their <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Legal Rights,</hi> and <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi> to give up their <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> to the King's <hi>abſolute Diſpoſition?</hi> Is it <hi>poſſible almoſt</hi> to be <hi>ſuppoſed,</hi> that they <hi>deſigned</hi> to <hi>confound</hi> and <hi>overthrow</hi> the <hi>whole Polity and Government of the Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>reduce</hi> all to the <hi>Arbitrary Will</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of a <hi>New Conqueror,</hi> without a <hi>Conqueſt?</hi> What Man is there (that is not become <hi>ſervile</hi> to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Opinion,</hi> and <hi>implicit Suppoſitions</hi>) of ſo <hi>Inventive</hi> a Faculty, as to conjecture ſuch grand Abſurdities? And
<pb n="clxii" facs="tcp:59543:92"/> yet theſe, and many more, are the direct Conſequences of thoſe that endeavour to maintain and juſtify theſe pernicious Principles.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> is, that <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. ſhould be as <hi>free</hi> in his <hi>Regality, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> Royal, as <hi>any</hi> of his <hi>Noble Progenitors</hi> Kings of <hi>England;</hi> then it <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally</hi> follows, That he was to be as <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>Abſolute</hi> as <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror:</hi> And then what is the Concluſion and Reſult, But that the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Author againſt Mr.</hi> Petyt. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> were <hi>neither</hi> to have <hi>Eſtates</hi> nor <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> left them: and therefore it could be no great Matter to them, by <hi>what Law, Right,</hi> or <hi>Property,</hi> Men <hi>held</hi> their <hi>Eſtates;</hi> And ſo <hi>farewel</hi> to <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we know, and are well aſſured, That <hi>never</hi> any <hi>ſuch Imagination</hi> entred into the<note place="margin">Raſ. Stat. 15 R. 2. f. 161.</note> 
               <hi>Minds</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> in 15. <hi>R.</hi> 2. not only by the Laws made then in that Parliament, but by thoſe in the next<note place="margin">Id. 16. <hi>R. 2. fo. 163.</hi>
               </note> Parliament, held the next Year after.</p>
            <p>The Commons granted to the King, That (<hi>pur la grant Affiance, Affection, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Parl. 16 R. 2. N. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſurance</hi>) for the great Truſt, Affection, and Aſſurance they had in the Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King, in his moſt excellent Knowledg, and his moſt ſage Diſcretion; and alſo for the great tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they had for his Crown and the Kingdom (<hi>&amp; les drots dicels</hi>) and the Rights thereof, (<hi>s'accorderant &amp; aſſenterent</hi>) they agreed and aſſented, in <hi>full Parliament,</hi> That the <hi>King,</hi> by <hi>good deliberation,</hi> and <hi>Aſſent</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Wiſe Council,</hi> might take the whole Matter, touching the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Proviſors,</hi> to him; and that he ſhould have <hi>full Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>modify</hi> the ſaid <hi>Statute</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain,</hi>
               <pb n="clxiii" facs="tcp:59543:92"/> by the <hi>Deliberation</hi> and <hi>Aſſent</hi> aforeſaid, in ſuch manner as he ſhould think beſt, to the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Holy Church,</hi> and the <hi>Salvation</hi> of the <hi>Rights</hi> of his <hi>Crown,</hi> and of the <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> of this <hi>Realm,</hi> and to put the ſame in execution when done.</p>
            <p>And that (<hi>au proſchein Parlement</hi>) at the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all the Matter aforeſaid ſhould be fully ſhewn (<hi>as ditz Communes</hi>) to the ſaid Commons; and the Reaſon thereof is memorable, <hi>viz. (au fin quils purront alors par bon aviſement agreer, ſi Dieu pleſt, a ycelles;</hi>) That the <hi>Commons</hi> then might, upon <hi>good advice,</hi> agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, if it ſhould ſo pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>From all which it evidently appears;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>no Law</hi> could be made in <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi>'s Time, or in <hi>any</hi> of his <hi>Progenitors,</hi> Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (which cannot but take in <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Aſſent</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>none</hi> of thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> could <hi>abrogate</hi> or <hi>make void</hi> ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> when <hi>made,</hi> without the <hi>like aſſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That though the <hi>General Phraſe, viz.</hi> That King <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould <hi>be</hi> and <hi>ſtand</hi> as <hi>free</hi> in his <hi>Regality, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Dignity Royal</hi> in <hi>his</hi> Time, as <hi>any</hi> of his <hi>Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> were in <hi>Theirs;</hi> and that the <hi>King</hi> ſays, That the <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Requeſts</hi> of the <hi>Commons,</hi> ſeemed <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>reaſonable</hi> to him, and therefore he gave his <hi>Royal Aſſent</hi> to <hi>that Law:</hi> Yet <hi>neither</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> nor the <hi>Lords,</hi> could ever believe, that it was <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>reaſonable;</hi> or that it was <hi>any part</hi> of the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> to <hi>change</hi> the <hi>whole Frame</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> by <hi>altering</hi> and <hi>making Laws</hi> at <hi>Will;</hi> by <hi>taking away</hi> the <hi>Subjects Poſſeſſions,</hi> and beſtowing them upon whomſoever he pleaſed; by deſtroying the <hi>ancient Courſe</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Parliaments;</hi> and, in a word, by <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> all things <hi>topſy turvy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="clxiv" facs="tcp:59543:93"/>
            <p>And thus we have the <hi>Evidence</hi> and <hi>Proof</hi> of the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Authority</hi> that can be <hi>given,</hi> againſt the <hi>Abſurdity,</hi> as well as <hi>falſeneſs,</hi> of King <hi>William</hi>'s <hi>Abſolute Conqueſt, viz.</hi> a <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Statute</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, I ſhall make bold to borrow the words of that great Aſſertor of the Proteſtant Cauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Intollerable Uſurpations of Papal Power, the ſo eminently Learned and Pious <hi>Thomas</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Popery, or the Principles and Poſitions approved by the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Quarto, pag.</hi> 116. and ſay, If <hi>any Man</hi> can <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>impartially (as to the ſum and ſubſtance of the Teſtimonies here cited, for I neither need, nor will undertake for every particular Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, or Typographical Error) either ſhew,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That I have miſquoted the Authors and Books I cite; and that ſuch Paſſages do not occur in the places quoted.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Or (if they do occur) that I have miſtook their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to the Purpoſes for which they are produced.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſay, If <hi>any Man</hi> can, and will <hi>ingeniou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> ſhew me ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, I ſhall be ſo far from <hi>not confeſſing</hi> my <hi>Fault,</hi> or declaring how I was <hi>miſled</hi> into it; that I ſhall have a <hi>hearty value</hi> for any ſuch <hi>friendly admonition,</hi> and receive it with all the <hi>grateful acknowledgment</hi> as becomes me: For my <hi>only deſign</hi> is, the <hi>Detection</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> to <hi>future Generations,</hi> and not to have the <hi>World impoſed upon</hi> by the <hi>Tricks, Impoſtures,</hi> and <hi>Artifices,</hi> which <hi>too many</hi> have been <hi>guilty of,</hi> either to <hi>promote</hi> their own <hi>particular</hi> Gain and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> (to which <hi>ſuch</hi> care not <hi>what</hi> they <hi>Sacrifice</hi>) or, upon a far <hi>worſe,</hi> and more <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Conſideration,</hi> to bring the <hi>whole Nation</hi> into <hi>dividing Parties</hi> and <hi>Factions;</hi> and thus by <hi>Embroyls</hi> and <hi>Entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to <hi>throw</hi> them at laſt into <hi>fatal Convulſions,</hi> to the <hi>deſtruction</hi> both of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59543:93"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
